<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Publick sorrovv A remedy for Englands malady. Being an explanation of the fourteenth verse of the first chapter of the prophet Joel. By Ellis Weycoe, M.A.</title>
            <author>Weycoe, Ellis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825022</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2162:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Publick sorrovv A remedy for Englands malady. Being an explanation of the fourteenth verse of the first chapter of the prophet Joel. By Ellis Weycoe, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Weycoe, Ellis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72, 57-64, 81-103, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Stephen Bulkley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Gateshead :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>Stained; print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Joel I, 14 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Publick Sorrovv A Remedy for ENGLANDS MALADY.</p>
            <p>Being an Explanation of the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth verſe of the firſt Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Joel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Ellis Weycoe,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>Weep for your ſelves, <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 23.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Be Afflicted, and Mourne, and Weepe, let your Laughter be turned into Mourning, and your Joy into Heavineſſe, <bibl>
                  <hi>James 4.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Bleſſed are they that Mourne, for they ſhall be Comforted, <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 5.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>GATESHEAD. Printed by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29387:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29387:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29387:3"/>
            <head>To his very much beloved Friends and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the Inhabitants of the Towne of <hi>Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington,</hi> and the <hi>Key;</hi> and to all the Pariſhioners there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, <hi>Grace, Mercy, and Peace from God the Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian and endeared Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VPon that Edict of the firſt of <hi>January 1655.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting Sequeſtred and Ejected Miniſters from Pulpit, and all other imployments (though I verily beleeve, that his Highneſſe and Councill chiefly aymed at the muzling of the Mouthes of ſuch turbulent Spirits, and Martiall Miniſters, as are no ſooner claſpt in their Pulpits, but preſently Proclaym War, in ſtead of Preaching Peace; Sedition, in ſtead of Obedience; and Confuſion in ſtead of Order; without the leaſt intent of prejudice to ſuch as were quiet and peaceable in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and not hearing as yet of any limitation) being (amongſt many others) by force thereof, not onely diſuſed from officiating in Publick, but likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred of all wayes and means, through which, by my coſtly Education, I might have procured ſome reaſonable compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency for my ſelfe, and the many depending wholly upon me; I have had leiſure enough to bewayle both mine own and others miſeries. And after not a few melancholy Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, finding my ſelfe an <hi>Achan,</hi> a great troubler of this poor Church and People; and ſeeing mine, as much (if not far more) then others ſins to be the onely cauſe of all our woes; I ſet my ſelfe to find out ſome Remedy for diſtreſſed
<pb facs="tcp:29387:4"/>
               <hi>Englands</hi> Malady: Hereupon I ſometimes Mournfully, yet willingly, ſate downe by the Banks of <hi>Babylon,</hi> there making Sorrow my Soules Solace, finding indeed no greater joy in my heavineſſe, then in <hi>Sorrow for ſin:</hi> Sometimes I walked abroad into the pleaſant Meadows, greene Fields, and freſh Paſtures of holy Scriptures, there to ſeek and ſinde ſome ſoure Hearbes, and of the tarteſt reliſh, and ſome Flowers of the darkeſt hew, and ſtrongeſt ſcent, that their ſad complexion might beſt pleaſe the weeping Eyes of a penſive Heart, and their bitter ſmell might beſt affect the diſtaſted Pallat of a ſin ſick-ſorrowfull Soule. Of both which ſorts, I found the <hi>Pſalmes, Ezekiel, Hoſea, Joel, Neho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> and the <hi>Lamentaions</hi> of <hi>Jeremy</hi> well ſtored, and thick Planted; and gathering ſome of them, ſuch as I thought for my purpoſe. I then took a turne into the delightſome Gardens of holy Writ, to ſeek out ſome ſweet flowers of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; and finding plenty, I cropt ſome few, to mix with the other, that the ones ſweetneſſe, might ſomething alay the others tartneſſe. And though thus full furniſht, yet diſtruſting my own Skill and Judgement in ſo great a Cure of ſuch a dangerous and deadly Diſeaſe; I went to View the Receipts of far more Able, Wiſe, and Learned ſpirituall Phyſitians, and from them extracted the beſt directions; which together, with my own weake Meditations, I mixt with all the other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients; and having firſt waſhed them well in the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> have of all theſe ſeverals or ſimples, made up ſuch a Compound, as I hope will be a good Preſervative againſt <hi>the Infectious poyſon of ſin,</hi> and a good Salve <hi>for Englands preſent Sore.</hi> And upon ſome thoughts, that if this Medicine were good for my ſelfe, it might, by Gods bleſsing, be comfortable to others alſo: Conſidering alſo, that a <hi>Book</hi> perhaps may ſpeake, when an <hi>Author</hi> may not; not
<pb facs="tcp:29387:4"/>harbouring the leaſt thoughts of Vain-glory, or Popular Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe; I reſolved with my ſelfe to make my Meditations <hi>Publick,</hi> like our <hi>Sorrows.</hi> And not knowing how to doe it any other way, I took this occaſion of manifeſting my deareſt affections, and beſt wiſhes, to you, amongſt whom I had my firſt Breathing, and have lived ſo long, as that none, better then your ſelves, are able to give evidence both of my former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and preſent condition. It may be (meane and plain as it is) it may conduce to the benefit of many; but my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall intent in it, was the zeale I have to your Soules, the ſalvation of which, <hi>I</hi> ſhall ever moſt heartily pray for. Accept therefore <hi>I</hi> beſeech you of theſe my poor Endeavours, and make uſe of this Phyſick <hi>I</hi> have prepared for you: But give me leave to give you ſome Directions in the taking of it; You muſt Chew it, Swallow it, and Digeſt it, not throwing it up ſo ſoon as you have received it, for then it will doe you no good; but if you can keep it <hi>in the Stomack of your Souls,</hi> you will find it to be ſuch a <hi>Violent Purge, and working Vomit,</hi> as will force you to Caſt or Spue up all the <hi>Poyſon of Sin.</hi> If you think it be toe much to ſwallowow all at once, you may divide it, at you pleaſe, into ſeverall Potions; yet, <hi>I</hi> think, the whole will be but three eaſie Mornings Draughts for your Soules; however, leave it not in the halfe, though you take longer time to Drink and Digeſt it all, and then <hi>I</hi> doubt not, but as it bath been to me, ſo it may be to you that takes it, ſomewhat uſefull and helpfull; And if any of you find eaſe, or get help by this <hi>Publick Sorrow,</hi> the onely Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick for a ſin burthened Soule; then Prayſe God, and Pray for,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The unworthy Servant of the Lord,</hi> Ellis Weycoe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29387:5"/>
            <head>To the Sin-ſick Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9 12.</note>
               <hi>THey that be whole,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>need not a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, but they that are ſicke.</hi> This Phyſick I have here prepared for thee, is made up of bitter Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſowre Druggs; which, taken according to the Direction in the <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory,</hi> will Purge corrupt Humours, ſcoure away the <hi>filthineſſe of ſin,</hi> and bring health and happineſſe to <hi>thy ſin-ſick ſoule.</hi> The ſeverall Ingredients, at the firſt, I intermixed and framed into this Compound, onely for my own uſe, and have had from them the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I deſired; namely, they have made many irkſome houres the leſſe tedious to me, and much heavineſſe to ſit a great deale the lighter upon me: It was far from my thoughts ever to trouble the too much oppreſſed Preſſe, I am ſo conſcious of my owne weakneſſe, as I cannot but bluſh in ſecret, that ever I was prevailed with to make my ſelfe thus open. I know not how my ſcribled Papers chanced to come to the view of ſome <hi>Perſons of Judgement,</hi> by whom I have been not intreated onely, but very much importuned alſo, to make this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> like the title of it, <hi>Publick.</hi> They ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me with ſome Arguments which I could not gain-ſay; truth is, they have overcome me, and made me at laſt (though moſt unwillingly) willing to expoſe my ſelfe to the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of this Cenſorious Age. Good Reader, my <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Sorrow</hi> hath long layd hid by me in the wombe of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, but is now after nine Moneths delivered to the Light; if it prove fruitfull or uſefull to thee or any other it will be an ample compenſation to my poore Labours. That great and good Phyſitian of our Soules, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> bleſſe it to thee, is the humble requeſt of his, and in him,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Servant,</hi> Ellis Weycoe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:29387:5"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>HOw the Church of <hi>England</hi> ever obſerved Faſts, and Holy-dayes, <hi>Fol. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Prince or Governour, may appoint a Faſt, <hi>Fol. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Princes or Governours are to be Obeyed in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>Fol. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Foure Cautions to be obſerved in keeping a Faſt, <hi>Fol. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to keep every day holy-day, <hi>Fol. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>God is never angry but for ſin, <hi>Fol. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sin is the cauſe of all miſery, <hi>Fol. 7. 8. 9. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mourners marked, and thereby preſerved, <hi>Fol. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Soules ſorrow, <hi>Fol. 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Better to deale with God by Teares then Words, <hi>Fol. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Antiquity of Faſting, <hi>Fol. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Foure Rules to be obſerved in Faſting, <hi>Fol. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Who muſt give to the Poor, how much, in what manner, and to whom they muſt give, <hi>Fol. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſts Schoole, a Schoole for all ſorts, <hi>Fol. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Kingdom of Chriſt admits of no diſtinction, <hi>Fol. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The beſt place of Refuge to fly unto in time of warre, or any Calamity, <hi>Fol. 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Five Rules to be obſerved in Gods publick wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſervice, <hi>Fol. 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three Rules that ſit us for a right behaviour in Gods Houſe, <hi>Fol. 46.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:29387:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>Three Rules to binde us to the good-behaviour; before we come to Heare, at the time of Hearing, and after we have Heard the Word, <hi>Fol. 47.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Our Hearing of the Word muſt be accompanied with foure concurring Circumſtances, <hi>Fol. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prayer the Art of Arts that adornes a Chriſtian, <hi>Fol. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Godly ſorrow and affliction, the beſt remedy in any ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and affliction, <hi>Fol. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The greateſt affliction which ſhould touch our Hearts, is the Churches affliction, <hi>Fol. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>We muſt never make an end of Mourning, till God make an end of Afflicting, <hi>Fol. 71. 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>No diſtreſſe whatſoever can hinder Gods people from praying, <hi>Fol. 78.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Knowledge of Gods power and mercy, is the onely cauſe of bringing Chriſtians into his preſence, and of moving them to call upon him in their miſeries. <hi>Fol. 83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Men can never truely ſeek God by Prayer, till they know, underſtand, and apply his Name, <hi>Fol. 83. 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>We muſt not onely Pray, but Cry, <hi>Fol. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Good Suiters alwayes good Speeders, <hi>Fol. 44. 95.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three Rules to be obſerved if we expect help from God in diſtreſſe, <hi>Fol. 96. 97.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29387:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joel 1. Chap. 14. Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Sanctifie a Faſt, call a ſolemne Aſſembly, gather the Elders, and all the Inhabitants of the Land into the Houſe of the Lord your God, and cry unto the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wiſeſt Preacher of a mortall Man, and of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall memory that ever was, or ſhall be inſpired with the ſpirit of God, ſaith, <hi>That there is a time to Weep as well as to Laugh, a time to Mourn as well as to Dance:</hi> And ſurely, ſeeing every Man and Woman under their own Vines and Figtrees, have a long time ſatiated themſelves with Laughing and Dancing, or making merry with their Friends; doubtleſſe now, theſe ſad and cloudy times are the times that call for <hi>Weeping and Mourning, for Baldneſſe and girding with ſackcloth,</hi> For hath not God ſhot divers of his Arrows, and have not ſome Bullers fallen from his Warning peeces? which Arrows and Bullets, poyſoned with the Peſtilence, have not many years agoe hit and ſlain ſome People, not onely in and about out Mother Cities, but elſe-where in the ſpatious Countries. Who perceiveth not how the deſtroying Angell hath of late unſheathed his Sword, and brandiſhed it over us of this Nation of <hi>England?</hi> Who knows not, how in reſpect of thoſe unhappy differences amongſt us, Warr thundred in our trembling Countries lap, the Sword devoured the <hi>Grace of England,</hi> and became drunk with the Bloud of Natives;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rovel.</hi> 6.4.</note> The <hi>red Horſe, with him that ſate thereon, to whom was given power to take Peace from the Earth, and a great Sword,</hi> ſtill prancing and trampling in our ſtreets, both at Noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and at Midnight? Now though the ſinfull Sons and Daughters of men have and ſtill doe lye nevertheleſſe ſleeping in their ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities, yet, the vigilant Watchmen of our <hi>Engliſh Iſrael,</hi> our late
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29387:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Royall <hi>Kings</hi> in their ſeverall Reignes and Governments, obſerving Gods begun Jadgements, and further threatned Puniſhments, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Proclaimed <hi>Eaſts</hi> in the times of common calamity. And his Highneſſe, (under whoſe protection and government we now live) hath ſet a part many dayes of Humiliation, appointing us a place of refuge, or ſacred Sanctuary to fly unto,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10.</note> that ſtrong <hi>Tower,</hi> that right <hi>Arke,</hi> or little <hi>Zoar,</hi> unto which the righteous run, and are preſerved, even unto the Houſe of the Lord our God, carried thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the feet of Prayer; there, with all fervency, to Pray for the preventing and diverting of Gods further furious hand againſt us, crying unto the Lord to ſpare this Land, to ſpare this People, to ſpare us from the Sword, to ſpare us from the Famine, and from all his ſore Judgements which our ſins moſt juſtly have deſerved; for which purpoſe the Trumpet hath been often blown in this our <hi>Sion,</hi> the Faſt Proclaimed and the Aſſembly gathered, according to this of <hi>Joel, Sanctifie a Faſt, call a ſolemne Aſſembly, gather the Elders, and all the Inhabitants of the Land into the Houſe of the Lord your God, and cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Fountain might divide it ſelfe into ſeverall Streames; but waving unneceſſary Fractions, I ſhall confine my Diſcourſe to theſe two Heads:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>A duty enjoyned,</hi> Sactifie a Faſt.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>A method, or order preſcribed for the ſolemne performance of it,</hi> Call a ſolemne Aſſembly, gather the Elders, &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Duty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned.</note>1. The <hi>duty enjoyned,</hi> A duty no leſſe neceſſary then ſeaſonable, For, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerves, Before the fall there needed but one glorifying of God, that was, <hi>by giving of thanks;</hi> But now ſince the fall, by reaſon of our many backſlidings, there muſt be alſo, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium tribulati cordis,</hi> the Sacrifice of a troubled Spirit, for the mortifying of this fleſh of ours, which by being too much pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perd by us, hath been ſo rebellious againſt God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſſe by the firſt, <hi>the duty enjoyned, or Faſt proclaimed;</hi> my meditations intending to fix upon nothing but that which ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford ſit matter for mourning, though the Proclamation it ſelf being alwayes occaſioned either upon begun Judgements, or threatned Puniſhments, might give juſt cauſe to hoiſe up ſaile in a Sea of ſorrows, but delighting onely in that heart-breaking, and yet wel pleaſing penſiveneſſe; and therefore haſtening to that Ocean o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29387:7"/>ſorrow in the <hi>exit,</hi> or end of the verſe, <hi>ſighing, ſobbing, crying;</hi> I will but ſalute the <hi>Faſt enjoyned,</hi> and ſtay but a while to bewayle theſe miſerable times into which we are fallen, which being the laſt, muſt needs be the worſt, wherein ſo many are carried away with the ſeverall blaſts of vain Doctrine, from Gods true Religion, to theſe follies and fancies, whereby they doe not onely wound Chriſts myſtieall Body, but alſo diſmember it in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, making ſo many Factions as there are Functions in the Church, ſo many fancies as men, and as many opinions as fancies; and to that height of impiety ſome are arrived, as that being Chriſts Free-men, they ought not to be ſubject to any, but are ſet free by Chriſt from the obſervation of Faſts or Feaſts appointed by the Prince or Governour, and not ſubmitting to the Government un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they live, will hold faſt their liberty purchaſed by Chriſt, though the appointment of them by the Governour be onely for the aſſembly of Gods people, and that upon ſpeciall occaſions, for the exerciſes of the Word and Prayer, without placing the worſhip of God, or any force of Religion in the obſervation of them, or without any opinion of holineſſe, in thoſe dayes, more then other dayes. And thus the Church of <hi>England</hi> did ever obſerve Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, Faſts, or Feaſts, and no otherwiſe; and yet did not fore goe their liberty purchaſed by Chriſt. I might give way to my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in this, and enlarge it to a Volume, but I had rather mourn for this kind of people (the onely troublers of our <hi>Engliſh Iſrael</hi>) then meddle with them: But to you that are peaceable in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> willingly ſubmitting your ſelves to the Government under which God hath placed you, <hi>and that for Conſcience ſake;</hi> know you, that it is lawfull for the Dominator or Governour to appoint a Faſt, or day of Hamillation, and you are bound to obey.</p>
            <p>For the lawfulneſſe of their Edicts, I need not ſtand at all upon it; it hath ever been uſed by Princes of all Ages, for which I might produce clouds of witneſſes, but ſearch you the Scriptures, and trace all the Kings.</p>
            <p>For our obedience to their commands, know, that we are bound to obey them in their abſolute commands ſo far forth as they are warranted by the Word of God: And for this, let that praecept of St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſerve for all;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> and if every ſoule, then no man is free. And again, <hi>Submit
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29387:8"/>your ſelves to all manner of Ordinance of man, for the Lord ſake, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be unto the King, as unto the Superiour; or unto Governors, as unto them that are ſent of him:</hi> So that people that obey not the wholeſom Laws of the Magiſtrate, ſin greatly; and if any refuſe to be ordered by them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2</note> 
               <hi>they reſiſt the Ordinance of God,</hi> and are ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally threatned, <hi>that they ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I ſhowed you, That Princes, or Governours may in the time of War, or other Judgement, <hi>enjoyne us a Faſt, and Proclaime a ſolemne aſſembly,</hi> to the end we may teſtifie our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, and better attend on the exerciſes of the Word and Prayer, and that we are to obey them; but withall, in keeping of a Faſt, let theſe cautions be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That our Faſting be voyd of ſuperſtition, and that we place no worſhip of God in it, but hold it onely as an help to further us in the duties of Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we have no opinion of merit by it, that thereby we merit forgiveneſſe of ſins, increaſe of grace, or the like.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we hold it not of abſolute neceſſity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, That it be without, breach of the rule of charity, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurting our ſelves, or making us thereby unfit for good duties, or giving offence to others, ſuch as are weak in knowledge, cauſing them to call our Chriſtian liberty into queſtion; rather Informing them, that the Magiſtrate hath power to enjoyn, and we are bound to obey, who by his Authority doth not take away the uſe of the things we abſtain from, but onely orders and moderates the ſame.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid for Feaſts, dayes of Thankſgiving, or holy dayes; but I paſſe them: onely I could wiſh, That every one of you would keep every day a Chriſtian Feaſt, even every day holy day, which you may doe, by purpoſing every day to avoyd all and every ſin, and by ſetting your ſelves every houre of the day in the ſight of God, and walking, as before him, carefully and conſcionably, in all good duties; and ſo doing you ſhall keep a good Conſcience, and that the wife man tels us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prev.</hi> 15, 15.</note> 
               <hi>is a continuall feaſt,</hi> even every day holy day.</p>
            <p>And now being fully reſolved. That the King or Governour may Lawfully enjoyn us a Publick Faſt in the time of extremity, or any common calamity whereby we may teſtifie our Humiliation with out the leaſt opinion of meriting forgiveneſſe of our ſins (the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of all our miſeries) and that he may Proclaim a ſolemn aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29387:8"/>and that we are to obey, not with any opinion of holineſſe in the time; but that the appointed day is for the aſſembly and holy convocation of Gods people, for the exerciſe of the Word and Prayer. Let us all then, as at all times, ſo eſpecially upon theſe dayes of Humiliation ſet a part, <hi>turne unto the Lord our God, with faſting, weeping, and mourning, and cry unto the Lord to ſpare this Nation, and command his deſtroying Angel to ſheath his Sword, and ceaſe from puniſhing, that there may be no more complaining, no more leading into captivity. Let us implore Gods gracious power, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his angry moved hand againſt us; and let us beg of the God of mercy, to ſtay his further dreadfull vengeance, and threatned puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from any further diſplaying horrour throughout all our Nation.</hi> And for that purpoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let us run to our place of refuge, <hi>the Houſe of the Lord, upon the feet of Prayer, and there cry unto the Lord to ſpare this Land, to ſpare this People, to ſpare, us from the Sword, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, or cauſe of the faſt.</note>The next is, <hi>the occaſion, or cauſe of this Faſt,</hi> and that, if you pleaſe to look into the verſes foregoing the Text, you will find to be a great Plague of Famine for the ſpace of no leſſe thou foure years;<note place="margin">Ver. 20.11.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>Their field waſted, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mourning, their corne deſtroyed, their vines dryed up, their oyle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their harveſt periſhed, all the trees of the field withered, and joy withered away from the Sons of Men</hi> So that juſt cauſe had they to lament, and howle, and lye in ſackc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and aſhes; nay, in duſt and aſhes. But ſhould I proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute my weak apprehenſions in this, I ſhould but draw the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe beyond a juſt extent: Let it ſuffice, That their Land was ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeted with a bloodleſſe Famine, a dreary puniſhment, Heavens curſe, and the engine of deſtruction; which doth bring terrour to mortals, death to all things; and therefore good cauſe had they, <hi>to call a ſolemne aſſembly, to ſanctifie a Faſt, to gather the Elders, and all the Inhabitants of the Land into the houſe of the Lord their God, and there cry unto the</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p>And as theirs was <hi>Famine;</hi> ſo, the cauſe of our ſolemne aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, or dayes of Humiliation (for ſome years by-paſt) hath been <hi>Warre,</hi> and the worſt of Wars, a civill War, our Land unnaturally embroyled in her own blood, and not long agoe, could have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented you even in the middeſt of her own bowels, with whole heaps of ſlain: This Land of <hi>England,</hi> that for many Ages conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the happieſt Nation on the habitable Earth, under the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29387:9"/>our Government of many famous Princes; and we of our times cannot deny, but we have enjoyed the higheſt bleſſings that either Heaven could give, or the Earth receive, <hi>the fruition of the Goſpel,</hi> which then ſetled a firme Peace, and which Peace occaſioned a full plenty to us, a then thriving, and I think, a well-contented people; inſomuch, that this Land then became the <hi>Earths Paradiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Worlds Wonder,</hi> or rather, <hi>Envy;</hi> Now alas! the Nurcery of all <hi>Sects,</hi> and of late years, <hi>the Stage of Blood, the Theatre of Warre,</hi> having had her Peace violated, her Plenty waſted, and her People diſcontented; and though now (thanks be to God) we heare not the ratling of Drums the claſhing of Armour, the neighing of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the ſounding of Trumpets, the thundring of Guns, or the roaring of Cannons; yet it is to be feared, the Lord is ſtill up in Armes againſt us, his hand is ſtretched out ſtill; elſe, what means theſe reports of Wars vaſt ſlaughters, and murders on the Seas? our Merchants and Traders ſpoyled their Goods Plundered, their Ships burnt, ſunk, or taken; and themſelves in their own defence, either flain, or carried away Captives: So that all this little while, or few years we ſeemed to enjoy a Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, every man again ſatiating himſelf under his own vine and firtree, was ſo far from a true Peace with God; as that rather, it forms it was but a Truce for a time, (God expecting our amendment) which being expired, and we ſtill continuing in our ſins, the Lord is again up in Arms for further revenge againſt us. And what is the reaſon that the Lord is ſtill thus incenſed againſt this Land, and people of <hi>England?</hi> Surely it is againſt the nature of God to be continually chiding, and ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and whipping, and wounding; for the Lord our God hath no other Bowels, then the Bowels of compaſſion; no other Riches, then the riches of his mercy; nay, the unlimited extent of Gods gracious mercy and goodneſſe, is beyond all imaginable proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. How coms then his favours to be turned into frownes, his mercies into diſpleaſures? Why? Surely if you will but trace the Seriptures, you ſhall never find God angry, but for fin; nor grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly angry, but for grievous fin; ſo that the fins of this Nation muſt needs be mounting, towring fins, ſins of the higheſt elevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and its the height of our ſins that hath alwayes brought down the weight of his judgements upon us; and the eart ropes of our ſins, have hurried down his vengeance: So that if we will but reflect
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29387:9"/>upon our ſelves, we ſhall find within our ſelves the cauſe of all our ſufferings, Plagues, puniſhments, and Woes; our ſins being the occaſion of all our evils, and the cauſe of all our miſeries, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining our ſouls, and drawing deſtruction after them, and of all things elſe moſt hurtfull unto us. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> confirms this, ſaying,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</note> 
               <hi>For this cauſe many are weak and ſick amongſt you, and many ſleep.</hi> And this was the reaſon, why the Diſciples queſtioned their Maſter, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>Quis peccavit?</hi> Who did ſin, this man, or his Parents? <hi>Celidonius</hi> was born blind, and our Saviour Chriſt going out of the Temple, ſeeking to ſhun thoſe ſtones which they intended to throw at him; he caſt his eye upon this poor blind man: for the eye of divine pitty is ever fixed upon poverty; and it is the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of humane miſery, to have the eye of divine pitty to look down upon it, and to favour the ſame; ſo that he healed him at once both in body and ſoule: The Hiſtory is no leſſe large, then pleaſing; you may reade it at your leiſures. Now the Diſciples having whiſpered amongſt themſelves touching this mans misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune (well knowing that ſin what the occaſion of all evill) they askt our Saviour, <hi>Quis peccavit?</hi> what ſin and? wherein they went wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to work, in attributing puniſhment in the generall to ſin. One treating of thoſe tears which our Saviour ſhed at <hi>Lazarus</hi> his death ſaith, <hi>That he did not bewayle his Buriall, for he know how happy he was in being out of the World; but the occaſion,</hi> ſinne; <hi>He thought upon</hi> Adams <hi>Apple, that had been the cauſe of ſo much hurt; and this was it that made him to weep; and this his weeping was, as if he ſhould have ſaid, What a deale of ſorrow hath this one act of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience in him brought upon all Mankind, and conſequently upon me, who muſt bear the burthen of his, and their offence: O ſin, how dear wilt thou coſt both men, and me!</hi> Trace but the Scripture, and you ſhall not find any one thing ſo often repeated there as, <hi>That ſin is the cauſe of our miſeries.</hi> How often doth the word of God paint out the foulneſſe, and grievouſneſſe of ſin, and the hurt that coms thereby? making fin the very center of all poſſible infelicity and misfortune that can befall a man. Sin was it that made our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>a Man full of ſorrow,</hi> when he took upon him the Perſon of an Offender, turning the moſt favourable countenance of the moſt pittifull Father, into frowns and florce diſpleaſure againſt his onely begotten, and dearly beloved Sonne, diſcharging upon him the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29387:10"/>tempeſt of his wrath, and made him, of all other men, the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. So that we may conclude, Sin to be the cauſe of all our harm, and that all poſſible ill that can be imagined, is to be reduced un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, as to its Center. Make a muſter of all the enemies of man, as <hi>Death, the Devill, the World, and the Fleſh,</hi> and not any one of them; nay, not all of them together, have the leaſt power to hurt us, without ſin; And therefore in our Lords Prayer ſilencing all other our enemies; onely we beg of God, <hi>that he would free us from ſin. But deliver us from evill;</hi> which, although ſome doe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it to be ſpoken of the Devill; yet (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith) <hi>He can but barke, he cannot bite, onely Sin is able to doe both.</hi> And <hi>Anſelme</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he had rather fry without ſin in the flames of Hell, then with ſin enjoy Heaven.</hi> He might well ſay ſo in regard of Hell; for although that one drop of the water of Paradiſe might be ſufficient to quench the ſlames of Hell; yet ſhall it not be able to waſh away the foulneſſe of ſin. The Prophet deſired of God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>that he might dye under the Juniper tree,</hi> and yet he would not be rid of his life by <hi>Jezabel,</hi> in regard of the ſinne that tyraunicall Queen ſhould have committed; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that, even in his mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſo great an ill ſeemeth intollerable to him. And though ſin be ſo great an evill; yet to this ſo great an hurt, may be added ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is far greater; and that is, Obſtinacy in ſin, never to be cured. <hi>Job</hi> painting out this evill, ſaith. <hi>That the ſinner taketh pleaſure therein, and that it ſeemeth ſweet unto him;</hi> it is as pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of ſugar under his tongue; he firſt delights in the company of ſin; then he marries himſelfe unto ſin, and leaves her not, till death them depart. Thus ſin creepeth into the heart by ſteps and degrees, till at laſt, it ſinks him down to the bottom of Hell: But woe is pronovnced to that ſinfull Nation, to that people that are laden with iniquity;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>Woe unto them that draw iniquity with cord of vanity, and ſin, as with cart ropes.</hi> For God is a ſevere puniſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſin and his wrath fails not to come and ſeize on thoſe that ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pillows underneath their ſins.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.6</note> So S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul, Let no man deceive y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with vain words, for, for ſuch things commeth the wrath of God upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the children of diſobedience.</hi> Was it not ſin that brought the curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and all his Poſterity? his Apple proves his poyſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23, 28.</note> Saul <hi>for his diſobedience, was turned out of his Kingdom.</hi> What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ruine and deſtruction of Countres, and Cities, but the ſins <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29387:10"/>the People?<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam</hi> 24, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Davids ſins, and his Pride,</hi> was the death <hi>of ſeventy thouſand</hi> in an inſtant; there the people periſheth for the ſin of the Prince. I could tell you of a Prince that periſhed for the ſins of the people, whoſe like was no King before him, neither after him aroſe there any like him: You may find him your ſelves.<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 23 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>Like unto him was there no King before him, that turned to the Lord with all his heart, and with all his ſoule, and with all his might, according to all the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>neither after him aroſe there any like him Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Lord turned not from the fierceneſſe of his wrath, wherewith he was angry againſt</hi> Judah <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22, 2.</note> Joſiah <hi>a good King, one, whoſe like was not before him;</hi> Joſiah <hi>who did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord; yet</hi> Joſiah <hi>muſt be ſlain.</hi> Thus you ſee when iniquity hath playd her part, vengeance will leape upon the ſtage. What was the reaſon why Gods hand was ſtretched over this Land, why the Sword devoured, and the people periſhed; but the <hi>ſins</hi> of the Nation? And was there ever more ſinning, or ever leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe for ſin? What is this world but the region of <hi>ſin,</hi> a Sea of filthineſie; and whilſt men are bewitched with the delight thereof, how, like Swine doe they wallow in the filthy mire and puddle of their ſins? It may be their bodies are curiouſly deckt, and ſhining; but alas they have naſty and abominable ſoules. Is not our Land ſtill full of <hi>Achans, looking upon the Wedge of Gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7, 21.</note> 
               <hi>or Babyloniſh Garment?</hi> How is the beauty of <hi>Bathſheba</hi> able to entice the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt number? <hi>Gehazi</hi> will ſtill poſt after <hi>Naaman</hi> for rich preſents;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>but the leproſie follows him cloſe at his heels,</hi> vengeance attends him neer. Was there ever more Drinking, Swearing, Stealing, Lying, Envying &amp;c. and ſince our <hi>ſins</hi> thus cry for vengeance, what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is it that the Lord is ſtil up in arms againſt us? O then put away your ſwiniſh drunkenneſſe, your prophane ſwearing, your brutiſh fleſhlineſſe, your deviliſh lying and deceiving, your helliſh cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, your ſavage eruelty, and all your other notorieties; and frame the whole courſe of your lives according to the rules of Temperance, Chaſtity, Truth, Righteouſneſſe, and holineſſe; and ſo though our ſouls be yet all ſtaind with <hi>ſinue,</hi> they may in time become cleerer and whiter then <hi>ſnow.</hi> Let as all, with a ſpirituall eye, behold the things of the world ſeparate from their ſeeming beauty, and ſo we ſhall not be bewitcht therewith. Let us conſider Gold and Silver, not as gliſtring and ſhining, but as droſſe and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29387:11"/>dung; yea, as poyſonous, through a curſe incorporated herewith-all, if our hearts be inſected with the love thereof, or by any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull means we doe ſeek after it; Let us conſider the beauty of the faireſt woman, as vanity; or as a piece of painted clay; or as a ſtale ſet for the taking of ſilly fooles: And laſtly, Let us conſider all other pleaſing things, as Drinking, Banqueting, Gaming, Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp;c. as the very ſtinging of a Scorpion, which giveth incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble delight for the preſent, but is by and by turned into tormenting and deadly pangs, till the man thus ſtung, periſheth. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince <hi>ſinne</hi> is thus hurtfull, let it be as hatefull unto us, and let us hereafter ſtrive as reſolutely againſt <hi>ſin,</hi> as we have formerly ſerved cheerfully under it. Let us hate all <hi>ſins,</hi> of all ſuits, and keep our ſelves from all ſpot of <hi>ſin;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5, 22.</note> And with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul, Abſtaine from all appearance of evill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude, ver. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> And with <hi>Iude, Hate the very garment ſpotted with the fleſh.</hi> In a word, Let us avoyd all <hi>ſins,</hi> and have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with theſe filthy inmates, that are dayly plotting and contriving to ſet the whole tenement on fire, and are good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but to bring rottenneſſe into our bones and bowels. And let us not defer to turn from <hi>ſin,</hi> nor delay till the Morning, but take warning by the fooliſh Virgins, <hi>for to morrow</hi> (for ought we know) <hi>may be the midnight of Chriſts call,</hi> when if we be found wallowing in the mire of our <hi>ſins,</hi> and ſtinking puddles of our iniquities, how can we hope or expect to be taken as aſſociates to ſo glorious a Bridegroom? And thus having found the cauſe of our ſufferings to be in our ſelves, let us lament for our <hi>ſins,</hi> that have brought upon us a burthen ſo heavy, the onely way to re-infavour us again with our juſtly offended God: And for that purpoſe, I ſhall endeavour my ſelfe to the utmoſt of my skill, to clothe every one of you with a livery of ſorrow, which is the next in the Text, <hi>the aſſembly called muſt be ſolemne; Call an aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Firſt part of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, or order.</note>
               <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the largeſt map of miſery that ever eye beheld, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been often threatned, often battered, and her viſitation grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neerer and greater then before; Salem <hi>being to become a tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary City,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.4.</note> Jeruſalem <hi>a ſolitary widow, the wayes of</hi> Sion <hi>to mourne, her ſtreets to be empty, her gates deſolate, her feaſts unfrequented, her Prieſts to ſigh, and her Virgins to be afflicted,</hi> ſhe her ſelfe the object of this ſight, and ſubject of this ſorrow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>to weep day and night, and the tears to run down her cheeks continually,</hi> her plagues
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29387:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>growing mighty, becauſe her <hi>ſins</hi> were waxen many; many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them, few mourning for them.<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.2.5.6.</note> The Lord now ſendeth <hi>ſix</hi> to deſtroy this City, <hi>commanding them to ſpare none, nor take no pitty, but to deſtroy young and old, Maids, Children, and Women; yet to touch none that had the Marke:</hi> and what this marke is, you may ſee in the fourth verſe, <hi>Sighing, ſobbing, crying for the abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, weeping and mourning for the wickedneſſe that is committed:</hi> there you ſhall find a publick Notary ſent to take the liſt of mourners, their ſorrow is their ſafety their lamentation the cauſe of their preſervation; for, for our comforts, mercy hath her lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings taken up in every Town, in every City, in every Country; be Gods judgements never ſo great, mercy cannot, mercy will not be excluded; the Saints are alwayes priviledged men, they have ſpeciall in munities, <hi>an Arke a Goſhen, a Zoar, a City of Refuge</hi> ſhall be ever prepared.<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>5.</hi> to the <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The meek, the mercifull, the Peace-maker, the perſecuted the poor in ſpirit, the pure in heart, and thoſe that hunger annd thirſt for righteouſneſſe,</hi> all theſe ſhall be bleſſed; and not onely theſe, but <hi>mourners</hi> ſhall have a part.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.5.</note> 
               <hi>The godly may ſow in tears but ſhall reape in joy; thouſands ſhall fall before them, and ten thouſands at their right hand, but the plague ſhall not come nigh them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Engliſh Sion</hi> (while thoſe unhappy differences, and wofull diviſions continued amongſt us) was like <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the very map of miſery; the Sword devoured, the people periſhed, our ſons butcherd, our young men ſlain, our Goods plunderd, our Lands ſequeſtred, and our bodies Catived; our plagues then grew migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe our ſins were waxen many; the moſt committing them, few mourning for them: and it is ſtill to be feared, though we have thus ſinned, and have thus been puniſhed, that there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more ſinning, nor never leſſe remorſe for ſin; and if againe the Lord ſhould ſtill be incenſed, and up in arms againſt us; what ſtrength were there in us (who are but ſtubble) to ſtand before ſuch a conſuming Fire: And therefore to prevent Gods further revenge, and threatned puniſhments, ſince you have ſeen in <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> that tears are the preſervatives of the living (for not a ſigh is ſent out, but is heard in Heaven, not a teare but is kept nor a groane, but it coms before God) let us ſigh and cry for all the abominations of the times let us weep for the ſins of the Nation,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29387:12"/>let us lament for out ſins, the cauſe of all our ſufferings, and wee; let ſorrow now cloath us, and mourning cloud us; let our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads be marked with a down-right ſolemne mourning; the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly called muſt be ſolemne, <hi>Call a ſolemne Aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word <hi>ſolemne,</hi> which is as much as <hi>ſerious, ſad, and heavy,</hi> me thinks may well contain furniture for the times of mourning, and having never more cauſe, I wiſh I might robe you with the garment of heavineſſe: The Text Proclaims <hi>a ſolemne aſſembly,</hi> and wills you to mourn for the ſins of the Land; the word <hi>ſolemn,</hi> me thinks, wills us all to lay aſide our wanton, ſuperfluous, and ſupercilious ſales of Pride, and put on ſables, mourning habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I mean, heavy, ſad, and ſolemn countenances outwardly, to teſtifie our ſorrow inwardly; becauſe the Lord hath turn'd his favours into frowns; He that formerly cloathed us with Beauty, did again cloath us with Leproſie; He that formerly cloathed us with Health and Happineſſe, did again, in ſtead of a Garment, give us a Rent, and plagued us with the Sword, and other deadly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous, and Infectious Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Will you look a little into the rifling of a Wardrobe in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the Inventory you will find taken in the third chapter, from the 18. ver. to the end of the 23. <hi>The bravery of their ornaments, and chains, and bracelets, and mufflers, and bonnets, and tablets, and eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and rings, and ornaments of the legs; and changeable ſults of apparell, and mantles, and wimples, and criſping pins, and glaſſes, and boods, &amp;c.</hi> But the deſtruction of all this Foeminine Furniture, you ſhall find in the next verſes, from the 24. to the end. <hi>It ſhall come to paſſe that in ſtead of a ſweet ſmell, there ſhall be a ſtinke; in ſtead of a girdle, a rent: in ſtead of well ſet haire, baldneſſe; and in ſtead of a ſtomacher, a girding with ſackcloth; and burning in ſtead of beauty. The gates ſhall lament and mourne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtory ſheweth what our ſtate was (God grant we have not cauſe again to ſay, is) for, ſo we ſinned, ſo we were plagued; and, me thinks, ſhould be ſufficient to ſtir up all the powers, and paſſions of ſorrow in every one of us; this, me thinks, ſhould be ſufficient to ſet open thoſe ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terns of our ſouls, that rivers of tears may flow from our heart-breaking, yet well-pleaſing penſiveneſſe; for the nature of griefe doth utterly exile all objects of pleaſure; and when true ſorrow ſits her down in a ſtupid, and a ſtupendious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29387:12"/>manner, and calls for Heaven above to weep with her, the Earth beneath to lament, the Rocks to cleave, the Mountains to Eccho forth groans, and the Rivers to run with tears of griefe, the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> did not more loath, then ſuch ſorrow as this doth delight to ſit down on the banks of <hi>Babylon;</hi> her Muſick is <hi>Lachrymae,</hi> or <hi>Dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſo;</hi> ſhe is as <hi>Rachel</hi> in her hard labour, ſhe no ſooner conceives, but is delivered; and no ſooner delivered, but conceives againe; her throbs and throws almoſt divide her ſoule from her ſelfe, but that her ſolace being in diviſion, that which killeth others, keepeth her alive; emptineſſe in the bowels, blackneſſe on the back, round about ſpectacles of miſery, all circumſtances to make ſorrow greater then her ſelfe. Surely our cauſe was, and is great, <hi>ſinne</hi> being the cauſe of our miſery, Let then our tears be many; let us put on the garments of lamentation; let mourning be the marke of our Foreheads; let our hearts be heavy, our bodies faint, our looks ſad, and our countenance ſolemne; and eſpecially upon our Faſt dayes, or dayes of Humiliation; let us all goe mourning to the Houſe of the Lord our God, with garments rent, and with ſackcloth cloathed; <hi>Let the Bride goe forth of her chamber; Let the Prieſts weep between the Porch and the Altar; Nay, howle ye poor Firr-trees, and let the Houſe of</hi> David <hi>mourne; and let all the Inhabitants of the land mourne, and weep, and lament; and let our lamentation be as the mourning of</hi> Hadadrimmon <hi>in the Valley of</hi> Megiddo: <hi>And let the land bewayle every Family apart; Let weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be in all the ends of our Nation, and complaining in the ſtreess of every City; Towne, and Country, crying in the chambers of every houſe, Woe, and alas, Woe unto us that we have ſinned.</hi> Nay, let all the Orders and Companies of every ſeverall holy convocation throughout this Land of <hi>England,</hi> from the Ruler to the Subject, from the Prieſt to the People, from the Honourable Councellour to him that draweth Water, from the Men of gray years to the yong Child and Suckling, all plentifully water their Cheeks with Tears. Let ſighs be their ordinary Language to our offended God, and cry unto the Lord to ſpare us from the Sword &amp;c. Our occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is juſt, our cauſe is good, for our <hi>ſins</hi> are great, and our God is incenſed, and therefore ſolemnity expects it, <hi>Call a ſolemne Aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But perhaps ſome will ſay, What needs all this adoe? what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29387:13"/>needs this ſad behaviour, or ſolemne Aſſembly? Doth not God ſea the heart? and if our bearts can but bleed in ſorrow for ſin, What need our eyes weep, our tongues lament, our countenances be ſad, or our whole behaviour ſolemne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The reaſon is, (though I might give you ſeverall, yet being in haſt, take this one for all, as the maine) Becauſe the Lord our God, is Lord as well of Body, as of Soule; and as well of Soule, as of Body: And therefore in performing any ſervice unto him, he expects-both in his Service and Worſhip, as in Prayer, our Knees muſt be bended to him, in ſigne of our humility; our Eyes, our Hands, our Hearts, and all muſt be liſted up unto him, in ſigne of our confidence. So in lamenting our <hi>ſins.</hi> Let our Eyes weep, our Breaſts ſigh, our Tongues complain, our whole Body faint, and our Soule languiſh: ſee <hi>Mary</hi> weeping, <hi>Peter</hi> weeping, and <hi>Jeremy</hi> never making an end of weeping for the <hi>ſins</hi> of his people. Beſides theſe outward circumſtanees doe moſt lively ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our inward ſorrows: Down, down then with all the ſignes and ſales of Vanity, and in true ſorrow and humility, humble your ſelves before God, and cry unto the Lord ſaying, praying, <hi>Enter not O Lord into judgement with thy ſervants, for in thy ſight no fleſh ſhall be juſtified. Keep us O God from the curſed cuſtome of ſinning, and from the direfull executioners of vengeance; eſpecially from the Sword,</hi> Good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <q>Call a ſolemne Aſſembly.</q>
            <p>It was an ordinary cuſtome in any common calamity, <hi>to rent their garments, put on ſackcloth, and mourne in aſhes.</hi> When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> found want of the favour of God, they put off their wonted Garments; as in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> in <hi>Amos,</hi> in <hi>Iob,</hi> in <hi>Ionah</hi> may be found: But not to ſtay at all upon the renting of garments, and cloathing with ſackeloth, nor to dwell any longer upon ſad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviours, heavy countenances, or ſolemne Aſſemblies; Ile onely wiſh you obſerve, how that the ſorrow and ſadneſſe of ſpirit, draws the Body, and all the abiliments of the Body, into the participation, and manifeſtation of griefe; and indeed, how is it poſſible, that our countenance ſhould teſtifie gladneſſe, when our hearts are heavy. And though I grant, that it is not needfull now to uſe ſuch ſhadows in the light of the Goſpel, which hath brought us greater liberty: So that whenſoever you reade, or heare of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29387:13"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 22.12.</note>
               <hi>Weeping, Mourning, Baldneſſe, or girding with Sackcloth,</hi> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by theſe ſignes, are but thereby noted out unto us; for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance neither conſiſts in ſackcloth, nor aſhes, nor in any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall thing, but onely in the heart: Thoſe who doe in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Repent, and are diſpleaſed with themſelves, they hate their <hi>ſins,</hi> and are touched to the quick with ſuch a ſenſe and feeling of ſorrow, that they abhor and deteſt themſelves, and their life paſt; and by theſe outward ſignes, they give teſtimony of their inward ſorrow; ſo that humbling themſelves before God, they therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſhew teſtimony of that diſpleaſure they had conceived in themſelves before men; ſo that indeed, the ſignes alone are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and the Ceremonies are indifferent; neither have we any Commandement to put on ſackcloth, or to pluck off our haire; but the occaſion of this Diſcourſe, and naming of theſe Signes and Ceremonies, is, That I might the better prevaile with you all, willingly, and in good earneſt, to put the truth of theſe ſignes in practice; namely, to have an unſaigned diſpleaſure with your ſelves, that you have ſo diſpleaſed your God; confeſſe your <hi>ſins,</hi> your rebellions, your offences, and that with a broken heart, and ſorrowfull ſoule, with an intent to leade a new life; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, as reſolutely to ſtrive againſt <hi>ſin,</hi> as we have formerly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved cheerfully under it; for if we judge not our ſelves worthy of puniſhment, we cannot come into favour with God: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as the poor Malefactor bows down his face, and cloaths him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in vile and baſe rayment, to move the heart of the Judge; ſo ought we, to run in all humility to Gods mercy, in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with unfaigned teſtimonies of our inward Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; for converſion begins at the heart: So the Prophet <hi>Joel. Rent your hearts, and not your garments;</hi> And therefore to leave the ſignes, to paſſe by the ceremonies, and cloſe up all in our mourning weeds, our heavy countenances, ſad behaviours, and ſolemne aſſemblies; let us be ſure to cloath mourning minds, and truely ſorrowfull ſoules. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is ſaid <hi>to weep a ſhower of teares.</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>a flood of tears.</hi> And I am ſure <hi>Jeremy wiſht for a Fountain of tears.</hi> Certain it is, that none of us can condole ſo much as we ought, for our <hi>ſins</hi> are many, and Gods plagues are mighty: and therefore a deluge of tears were little enough to bear the Ark of our ſorrow for our <hi>ſins.</hi> I have thus far brought
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29387:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>you ſorrowing towards this deluge, this ſea, this fountaine of ſorrow; let us ſtill follow on with paces of lamentation, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull remembrances of our <hi>ſins,</hi> which have forced the Lord to his Armoury, and to put on the garments of Vengeance againſt us. And for that purpoſe, I ſhall endeavour to robe your ſelves with mourning garments, and cloath them with the inward ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth of ſorrow, that your hearts thus rent, and torne to pieces with godly griefe, you may cry more earneſtly to the God of mercy, to ſpare this Land, and not adde to our afflictions, leaſt thoſe that have evill will at our <hi>Engliſh Sion,</hi> rejoyce and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph at our preſent miſeries.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Souls ſorrow, outward griefe.</note>The word <hi>Solemne,</hi> ſhews that our outward ſorrow ſhould te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie our inward griefe; ſo that, that which went before, was but the Signe; we now come to the Truth. For our part, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce not renting of cloaths onely, without the putting on of other robes; not ſo much wiſhing you to put on ſackcloth, as to put on Chriſt. <hi>Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> is the voyce of Scripture; not <hi>Scindite; Put on, not Rent off;</hi> the Originall being from that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul, Put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> which will be the better performed, if you pleaſe to acquaint your ſelves with this inward mourning; not <hi>Scindite Veſtimenta;</hi> but <hi>Scindite Corda: Rent not your cloathes but rent your hearts.</hi> And it was not without much reaſon. that <hi>Solomon</hi> gives councell, <hi>To goe to the houſe of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Eſt enim illie benedictio,</hi> there is performed that bleſſing which Chriſt promiſeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.4.</note> A bleſſing is promiſed no where to <hi>mirth,</hi> but to <hi>Mourning:</hi> our Saviour hath annexed this reward. And ſurely, the keeping under of the ſoule, is much available to all religious and devout offices: and I am ſure, there ought to be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in every ſoul. The whole courſe of our Saviours life, was ſpent in ſolitary ſorrow; and doubtleſſe, the cauſe of his ſufferings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in us, <hi>our Sins;</hi> we had need, all the dayes of our Pilgrimage, lament for our <hi>ſins,</hi> that brought upon our Ieſus a burthen ſo heavy; inſomuch, that not <hi>Ieremy</hi> onely, but all Man-kind, may Write lamentations: So that, <hi>Non finire, ſed ſemper reſervare la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymas debemus;</hi> We had need never make an end of mourning never end our ſorrows for <hi>Sin;</hi> intermit them we may, but ſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> let us keep our acquaintance with them. That of <hi>Hierome,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> confeſſe is true, <hi>Deteſtandae ſunt illae lachrymae, quae non habe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29387:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>modum;</hi> Mourning without meaſure is a Hell upon Earth: Yet again, <hi>Deteſtandi ſunt qui carent lachrymis;</hi> they are to be dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted that have no meaſure of this heavenly Manna; but happy were we, if we could for ever continue our mourning for <hi>Sinne,</hi> and for the abominations of the Land. God hath already given us the cup of his wrath to drink off, and we have taſted deeply of the cup of his diſpleaſure; we have ſeen affliction in the rod of indignation: this Land hath preſented us with ſad ſpactacles, whole heaps of ſlain. O how ſhould the remembrance of our late ſufferings, ſet open again the Fountains and Floodgates of ſorrow that rivers of tears might flow from our penſive hearts! And if the Lord ſhall again be incenſed, by reaſon of our <hi>ſins,</hi> which are as many, and great as ever; what can we expect, but having already begun to taſte of the bitter cup of his wrath and diſpleaſure, he will force us the next time, to drink it down to the dregs? But ſince that groans and ſorrow for <hi>Sin,</hi> is the onely way to appeaſe Gods wrath, being far better to deale with him by tears, then by words; and ſeeing there is no ſorrow to that of the ſoule, though the eyes of the body ſhould wax blind with weeping, Let us ſhower down rivers of tears, let us plentifully water our cheeks with tears, and ſigh, and ſob, and weep, and howle, and cry unto the Lord to ſpare us from the Sword; and let this our lamentation and mourning be <hi>coram,</hi> not <hi>clam,</hi> not onely privately, but openly, eſpecially upon our Faſt dayes, or dayes of Humiliation; for as ſolemnity expects it, ſo antiquity preſcribes it, the Aſſembly called muſt be ſolemne, <hi>Call a ſolemne Aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But perhaps ſome will ſay, God expects not this inward and outward ſorrow in his ſervice, this heart-breaking, and body-faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, our eyes weeping, and our ſouls languiſhing; for God wills, that we ſhew our ſelves glad and cheerfull when we ſerve him.</hi> Aaron <hi>was ſad for the death of his Sonnes; and</hi> Moſes <hi>reprehending him, becauſe he had not eaten that day of the Sacriifice; he told him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.19.20.</note> Quomodo potui comedere, aut placere Deo in ceremoniis mente lugubri? <hi>How could I eat, or pleaſe God in the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies with a mourufull mind? and the text ſaith, that</hi> Moſes <hi>reſted ſatisfied. The Starrs being called by their Creator to give their light, they are ſaid to doe it,</hi> Cum judicate, <hi>with delight, or cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29387:15"/>When we ſerve the Lord, we are bidden to ſerve him with alacrity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.17</note> 
               <hi>When we faſt, the Word bids us, Anoynt our heads, that we ſeem not to men to faſt;</hi> Unge Caput tunm. <hi>But the faſt here enjoyned, and the Aſſembly called, muſt be ſolemne. How ſtands this together, the Scripture bids us both be merry and mourn in the Service of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The anſwer may well be this, That all our felicity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in ſorrow for <hi>ſinne,</hi> we may very well be merry to ſee our ſelves ſad: Green Wood being put upon the Fire, both weeps and burns; a deep Valley is cleare on the one ſide, and cloudy on the other; and mans breaſt is ſad in one part, and joyfull in another.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpecifies two ſorts of ſorrow; one which grows from God; the other from the World: that gives life, this death. And furely that ſoule that ſorrows for his <hi>Sins,</hi> gives glory un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. It was commanded in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> that they ſhould cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate with great ſolemnity a day of expiation;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>23.27.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Et affligetis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas veſtras;</hi> and ye ſhall afflict your ſoules. It ſeems not to ſound well, that men ſhould make a great Feaſt, with afflicting their ſoules: but for Gods Friend, no Feaſt ought to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo great, as to offer unto him a ſorrowfull and a contrite heart; for as there is nothing more ſad then <hi>Sin,</hi> ſo is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo cheerfull, as to bewayle it. All our diſhoneſt actions are but carneſts layd down for griefe; for Vice is ever an infallible forerunner of wretchedneſſe; and all our unwarrantable aberra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions end at laſt, either in anguiſh, or confuſion: for <hi>Sin,</hi> on the beſt condition, brings but ſorrow with it; and for <hi>Sinne</hi> without ſorrow, is provided Hell. Then down to your Knees, and deſire of God that he would give you a taſt of the ſweetneſſe of tears, and your ſoules once taſting the ſweetneſſe of tears, will not leave them for a world; for tears are the delight of a penitent; and there is no true joy, but in ſorrow for <hi>Sin.</hi> So that all our feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city conſiſting in ſorrow for our <hi>ſins,</hi> we may very well be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to ſee our ſelves ſad; and if our ſorrow cannot move men to godlineſſe, yet it is forcible to move God to mercy: The broken heart, for griefe of <hi>ſinne,</hi> and love of righteouſneſſe, (however the world deſpiſe it) the Lord will not deſpiſe it; yea, it is the ſacrifice of God, acceptable to him in Chriſt Jeſus. Therefore ſaith one,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Lachrymae ſunt cordis ſanguis;</hi> Tears are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29387:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the hearts blood: And, <hi>Lachrymarum preces utiliores ſunt quam ſermonum;</hi> The prayers of teares are far more profitable then thoſe of words. Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayes, <hi>That our ſins are ſet downe in the table-book of Gods memory, but teares are the ſpunge which blot them out againe.</hi> In a word, thoſe teares that ſlow from a broken heart, are that ſalt brine that will eure your wounds, cheere your ſouls, eaſe your conſciences, and pleaſe your God; they take away all raw humors, and make us ſavoury meat for the Lord: nay more, they ſubdue the Invincible, and binds the Omnipotent; ſo S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierome, Oratio Deum leuit, lachryma cogit;</hi> who would not then mourn for <hi>ſin,</hi> and grieve, becauſe they cannot grieve enough? and be earneſt with God, in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtins</hi> expreſſion, <hi>Domine da mihi gratiam lachrymarum,</hi> Lord give me the grace of tears. Then weep for your ſelves, and weep for others, weep for the ſins of the times, for the abominations of the Land, <hi>and cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The text I took up for your uſe of purpoſe in theſe ſad times and God grant it may be as profitable unto you, as I'me ſure its fit for theſe ſorrowfull ſeaſons; and though I wiſh no end to your mourning, yet having led you thus far, ſorrowing for your ſins, and the ſins of the times; let us look back a little upon the Faſt enjoyned; which having done, I ſhall again take you by the hand, and leade you into the houſe of mourning, the place appointed, <hi>the Houſe of the Lord your God,</hi> and ſo goe along by the banks of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to the end or <hi>exit</hi> of the verſe, where we ſhall meet with nothing but <hi>lachryma,</hi> and <hi>ſuſpicia,</hi> Tears, ſighs, ſobs, ſorrows, deploration, lamentation, fit meditations for our ſorrowfull ſouls; for the end doth hold a correſpondency with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sanctifie a faſt.</note>Againſt ſome Vertues, ſome Emulators have not ſtuck to ſpeak; but againſt Faſting, no man ever opened his mouth. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> himſelfe, never denyed the nobleneſſe of Faſting; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo much commended it, that our Faſtings ſhould be aſhamed to ſtand in competition with theirs. And I find ſuch forcible Arguments upon this point, that, me thinks, its but a ſuperfluous labour to adviſe whether it be to be done, or no. Its but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous to adviſe a man that is ſick, to obſerve a dyet; ſo its as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29387:16"/>needleſſe a thing, to command a man to Faſt, who from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world took a ſurfet of eating. <hi>Ninive</hi> was ſaved by Faſting. And <hi>Joel,</hi> me thinks, propoſeth the like means, when he cryes unto the people, <hi>Convertimini ad me in jejunio,</hi> Turne unto me in Faſting, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of faſting.</note>For the antiquity of Faſting, we find, That when the Law of Grace was firſt publiſhed through the world, Faſting was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed. John <hi>came neither eating nor drinking.</hi> And the firſt ſtep of our Saviours pennance for our ſins, was <hi>Faſting;</hi> in token that our firſt hurt came by <hi>Eating.</hi> The firſt Law that God gave man after that he had Created him, was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>That he ſhould not Eat of the tree of Knowledge of good and evill:</hi> wherein two things were to be noted; the one, That man in this ſo great an happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhould not forget that he had a Lord and Maſter. The other had an eye to the repairing of his future fault, and that man might underſtand that he ſhould in Faſting find a remedy for that hurt which came unto him by Eating. And as a wiſe Phyſitian feeling the ſick mans Pulſe, finds out his ill diſpoſition, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that his ſickneſſe grew from that ill ripened Fruit, which even to this day is not yet fully digeſted, did preſcribe this <hi>Recipe,</hi> as a Medicine to cure this our Malady; to the end, that as a man did Eat to ſickneſſe, ſo he might Faſt to health: And as Gluttony did baniſh us from Paradiſe, ſo Faſting might recall us thither again. So that not Faſting was the cauſe of all evills, ſin, as you have it before, was the cauſe of all our miſery. Now, out not Faſting, I meane not abſtaining from the <hi>forbidden Fruit,</hi> was the ſin; ſo that all thoſe evills that are now in the world, are in recompence of that wrong which was done in Paradiſe unto Faſting. And not onely our firſt Parents ſmarted for it, but all their Poſterity even to this day; and if any thing help this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, it muſt be Faſting. The Prodigall cryes out, <hi>Fame perco,</hi> I dye by hunger; whereupon this preſently followeth, <hi>Surgam, ibo ad Patrem meum,</hi> I will ariſe, and goe to my Father; It was Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Hunger there you ſee, that reſtored him preſently to his former eſtate. So that if our ancient loſt liberty could poſſibly be repayred, it were no wayes better to be recovered, then by Faſting; and if by Faſting, the ſhip of this our life takes in no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29387:16"/>water; and without it, is overwhelmed and drowned. Let us lay the whole lading of all our ill, or good, upon our Faſting. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> proveth, That while Faſting continued in the World, God did ſtill better, and enrich it with new things: <hi>The firſt day he Created the Light; the ſecond, Heaven; the third, Earth; the fourth, Sunne, Moone, and Starrs; the fifth, the Fiſhes of the Sea, and the fowles of the Ayre;</hi> and though he gave them his bleſſing, yet he did not ſay unto them that they ſhould Eat. <hi>The ſixth, Beaſts of the field, and Man,</hi> and giving them licence to Eat, the Works of God, and the perfections of the World, were ended; wherein God gave man, as it were, a Watch-word, that <hi>Eating</hi> would be his undoing. And as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath it, <hi>If in that ſo happy an eſtate, Faſting was ſo neceſſary, what ſhall it be in this miſerable condition of ours?</hi> Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples ſaid unto Chriſt, <hi>Maſter, Why doe we and the Phariſees Faſt, and thy Diſciples Faſt not?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>While the Bridegroome is preſent, the Children are not to weep; but the time ſhall come wherein they ſhall not have him with them, and then they ſhall Faſt and Mourne:</hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our Saviour, and the enjoying of his moſt ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, did bridle their appetites, and keep their ſoules in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but in his abſence, he inferreth, that this muſt he done by Faſting. I might ſtay to tell you of miraculous effects by Faſting, in <hi>Niniveh,</hi> in <hi>Moſes,</hi> in <hi>Elias,</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> in <hi>Eaſter,</hi> in the Mothers of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> in <hi>Judith</hi> in others: and how <hi>David</hi> with Faſting, covered the faults of his whole life. <hi>Sola gula peccavit</hi> (ſaith Saint-Bernard) <hi>ſola jeju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, &amp; ſufficit:</hi> Onely Gluttony offended, let Grutteny onely Faſt, and it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth; not that the Vertue conſiſteth wholly in abſtaining from Meat, for our Saviour Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed, but when he was oppreſſed, with Hunger, he did Eat. And the like may every good Chriſtian doe; yet a man may deny that to deſire, which he may grant to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. So that, <hi>Carnis curam nè feceritis in deſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is:</hi> Let the cockering of your Fleſh be no part of your deſire: but the maine, or principall Faſting is, to Faſt from ſin, to which the other Faſting is but onely a preparative. So that all this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe touching Faſting, is but ſuperfluous, having ſuch forcible Arguments to move us thereunto. I rather therefore think bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29387:17"/>to adviſe you how it ought to be done, and that without treſpaſſing at all againſt my own eaſe, you your ſelves may ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſee, in that of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians, Sive come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datis, ſive bibatis, ſive quid aliud facitis, omnia in gloriam Dei facite:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</note> Whether ye eat, or drink, doe all to the glory of God. Which that ye may the better doe, in your Faſting obſerve theſe foure particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we muſt not onely doe good, but ſhun evill: let us not be like thoſe Hypocrites, whom the wind of vain glory rob'd of all the good they did: we are but duſt; and the Goſpel bids us beware of Winde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.16.</note> that we be not carried away therewith; this vain oſtentation of man, hanging our Conſciences upon other mens lips: but for our parts, we muſt not onely doe good, but ſhun evill.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt acknowledge, That our Faſtings and good works, are more from God, then our ſelves; <hi>Non poſſumns cogitare ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ex nobis:</hi> Of our ſelves we cannot ſo much as think a good thought. Mans poverty is ſo great, that he cannot ſo much as come to a good thought, and therefore may not make Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of that wealth which is none of his own: but God is ſo free in the works of Vertue, and ſo bountifull, That being at all the charge himſelfe, he gives thee all the gaine; onely he wills, that thou give the glory unto him, and take the profit to thy ſelfe. That workman ſhall doe ill, who having built a houſe with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans purſe, ſhould goe about to ſet up his own Arms upon the Frontiſpiece. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> made a Law, <hi>That no Maſter worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould ſet up his name within the body of that Building which he made out of anothers coſt.</hi> Chriſt ſets thee on work, and wills thee <hi>to Faſt, to Pray, to give Almes;</hi> but who is at the coſt of this ſo good and great a worke? God: thou haſt all thy materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls from him, the building is his, it is his Purſe that payes for all; give then the Glory and the Honour to him: <hi>Gloriam meam alteri non dabo:</hi> I will not give my Glory to another; content thou thy ſelfe with Heaven, which is promiſed unto thee, if thou doſt well, which is a ſufficient reward for any ſervice thou cauſt doe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Beware of Hypocriſie in Faſting. <hi>Faſting, Praying, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29387:17"/>giving of Almes,</hi> done onely for Gods ſake, is of that great price and eſtimation, that it is ill imployed on any other then God; and for that, God weighes all things in his hand, as in a ballance, and knows the weight of every good work, and the true value thereof; it grieves him that they ſhould doe theſe good things for ſo vile and baſe a price, and is ſorry to ſee thee ſo fooliſh, and poor a Merchant, that thou wilt part with that which is as much worth as Heaven to thee, for that which is leſſe then Earth; namely, that the World ſhould onely ſay, <hi>thou haſt Faſted.</hi> Why doeſt thou thus crucifie thy fleſh? why debarre thy belly of food? why being ready to dye for hunger, doſt thou not eat? why lifteſt thou up thine eyes to Heaven, for ſo poor a thing, as to win applauſe upon Earth? Thoſe works ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> that are done for God, are <hi>Gold;</hi> but done for the World, are <hi>Dirt;</hi> they lay up this their treaſure in the Tongues and Eyes of men, which is a Cheſt that hath neither Lock nor Key unto it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Faſting</hi> is a Plaiſter for our wounds, a Medicine for our Griefes, a Salve for our Sins, and a Defence againſt Gods Wrath; but you muſt take heed that you doe not make this Plaiſter, Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; this medicine, ſickneſſe; this ſalve, a ſore; and this defence, your deſtruction: for where God hath a Church, there the Devill will have a Chappell; and where he throws in Seed, there the other will ſow Tares.<note place="margin">1 King. 21</note> 
               <hi>Naboth,</hi> a Subject of King <hi>Ahabs</hi> had a Vineyard in <hi>Samaria,</hi> neer unto the Kings Pallace; the King had a mind unto it: <hi>Naboth</hi> will not part with it; the King grows ſad, refuſes his meat: <hi>Ieſubel</hi> comes to ſee him, makes a jeſt of it; takes Pen in Hand, diſpatches a Ticket to the Governours of that City, ſealed with the Kings Seale, to Proclaime a Faſt, ſubornes two Witneſſes to ſweare, <hi>That they heard</hi> Naboth <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God and the King:</hi> innocent <hi>Naboth</hi> is ſtoned to death, and his goods confiſcated. In which action, there are two things worthy our conſideration; The one, That the circumſtance of blaſpheming God and the King upon a ſolemne day of Faſt, was ſo grievous, that of force he muſt be condemned to dye for it, in ſo great veneration was Faſting in thoſe dayes. The other, That it ſerved as a cloak for the taking away of the Vineyard, and for the falſifying of Witneſſes, and injuſtice in the Judges: Who
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29387:18"/>ſhould have then ſeen the people to Faſt, would have thought it had been done out of Zeale, Gods Honour, and a deſire to doe him ſervice: but it was meerly a trick of the Devils, which he had plotted with himſelfe; he threw poyſon upon vertue, ſeeking to draw evill out of good. We muſt therefore beware, leaſt theſe our good actions receive not hurt by evill intentions, And therefore, farre be it from among any of you, that upon theſe ſolemne dayes of Faſting, there ſhould lurk under the ſable habit of a monrner, any falſe hearted, or hypocriticall masker; for it is to be feared, that among many in this Land of ours, even upon our ſolemne dayes of Humiliation, masking might be found in mourning. But the Faſt that God requires, you may ſee in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 58.5.6.7. <hi>Is it ſuch a Faſt that I have choſen? that a man ſhould afflict his ſoule for a day, and hang downe his head like a bulruſh, and lye downe in ſackcloth and aſhes. Wilt thou call this a Faſting or an acceptable day unto the Lord?</hi> Here the Prophet ſhewes, That God neither approves, nor condemnes Faſting in it ſelfe, further then when it is applyed to the right end. So that here is the abuſe in Faſting, when men put holineſſe in it, and in either, deſpiſing or neglecting true godlineſſe, they think that the bodily exerciſe alone fuſſiceth; but he proteſts, That this is not acceptable to him, to ſee one continue a day without meat, and to go ſorrowfully with his head hanging down <hi>like</hi> a bulruſh, and lying downe in <hi>ſackcloth and aſhes:</hi> he taxes theſe ſuperſtitious geſtures, wherein Hypocrites are wont to place a <hi>kinde</hi> of holineſſe; not that he condemnes theſe exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall rites, but <hi>rebukes</hi> theſe Hypocrites for ſeparating the truth from the ſignes. And in the next Verſes, he tells you what <hi>kind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of Faſt it is that God <hi>likes</hi> and allowes of, <hi>Is not this the Faſt that I have choſen? to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, to take off the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that ye breake every yoke? Is it not to deale thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that wander into thy houſe? When thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him, and hide not thy ſelfe from thine own fleſh?</hi> Here the Prophet ſhews firſt, what the Lord chiefly and principally requires in our Faſt. Secondly, by what means our ſervices may be acceptable before him. And thirdly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29387:18"/>How thoſe ought to be fitted and prepared that meane to Faſt: In a word, you may ſee here wherein the true offices of Piety, (which are principally commanded of God) conſiſt; namely, in comſorting the poor, and oppreſſed. We may likewiſe ſee here the duties God allows of in Faſting, what makes our faſts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of, approved, and acceptable unto God: namely when together with Faſting, Charity is joyned with it: The <hi>Faſt that God hath choſen, is to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe:</hi> Some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it, the wicked thoughts wherewith men are bound and intangled. And it may paſſe for currant; for the principall <hi>Faſting,</hi> is to <hi>Faſt from ſinne.</hi> But it ſeems <hi>Iſaiah</hi> meant other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; namely, That Hypocrites are very cruell and mercileſſe towards the poor, and lay very heavie yokes upon them; he calls that Knots, or Bands, which we commonly tearme Oppreſſions; to which that agrees which is added, <hi>to take off the heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> under the weight whereof, the poor and needy groane, and are in a manner overwhelmed therewith. The Prophet, me thinks, would bring us to this principle, namely, That our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences may be pure and ſound, and that we exerciſe our ſelves in ſhewing brotherly kindneſſe one to another; for if this order be duely obſerved, then <hi>Faſting</hi> added thereto, will be pleaſing and acceptable to the Lord. The Faſt that God hath choſen is, <hi>To deale thy bread to the hungry, to cloth the naked, &amp;c.</hi> For as in the obſerving of a <hi>Faſt</hi> (as you had before) we muſt not onely doe good, but ſhun evill; ſo we muſt not onely abſtain from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrong to the poor, from laying heavy yokes and knots upon them; but we muſt ſhew our ſelves liberall and lowly towards the afflicted, and ſuch as ſtand in need of our help. For there are two parts of equity and juſtice; firſt, That we offer no man any wrong. Secondly, That we imploy our riches and goods towards the maintenance of them that are in want and neceſſity, and theſe two parts muſt be joyned together; for it is not enough to abſtaine from violent courſes, unleſſe therewithall we ſhew mercy in releeving our poor brethrens wants: Neither is it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſuccour one, if you rob from ſome to beſtow upon others; for we muſt not releeve our neighbours wants by Thefts and Pillages; and if thou haſt committed any injuſtice, cruelty,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29387:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>or extortion, though oughteſt not to make amends by calling, in God to thee, as if thou wouldeſt make him partner with thee of thy ſpoyles: It is neceſſary then you ſee, that theſe two parts of equity and juſtice by joyned together, if we would have God to approve and allow of our Charity. Firſt, We muſt offer no man wrong. Secondly, We muſt imploy our riches and goods towards the maintena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of them that are in want; we muſt, together with abſtain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng from violent courſes, ſhew mercy, in releeving our poor brethrens wants. Doſt thou faſt? then deale thy bread to the hungry, for this the faſt that God hath choſen; and indeed, true Religion ſtandeth chiefly in Charity to the poor.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>To viſit the Fatherleſſe and Widow;</hi> for love is ſet forth in ſundry places, as the chieſe of all graces; eſpecially in the firſt of the <hi>Corintians,</hi> the thirteenth, to the end of the Chapter. Now where there are no acts of Charity, no giving of Almes to the poor, there can be no love,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.17.</note> as Saint <hi>John</hi> largely proveth, Almeſdeeds therefore, <hi>to feed the hungry, to cloth the naked;</hi> to diſtribute and give of our goods to the poor, is greatly required both in the Old and New Teſtament.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> chargeth the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> often, <hi>To give, and to lend freely to their poor brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 112.5.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> deſcribeth the righteous man by this, <hi>That he is mereifull, and diſtributeth, and ſcattereth abroad.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ov.</hi> 19.17.</note> Solomon</hi> makes the Lord his Debtor that giveth to the poor, ſaying, <hi>He that giveth to the poor, lendeth to the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.7.</note> And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> bids, <hi>to bring the poor wandring into thine houſe, and to break thy bread to the hungry.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7, &amp;c.</note> See Chriſt bleſſing the mereifull and commanding to give to him that asketh, and not to turn away from the pool that would borrow, and acknowledgeth the receipt of whatſoevel is given to the poor, as if it were given unto himſelf;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35.</note> 
               <hi>For I was hungry, and ye gave me meat: naked, and ye clothed me, &amp;c.</hi> And to move us hereunto; firſt, Let us conſider, that it is Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, of whoſe gift it is that we enjoy any thing. Secondly, The poor be our brethren; yea, our own fleſh:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 58.7.</note> then <hi>hido not thy face from thine own fleſh.</hi> Its inhumanity, me thinks, to diſdaine and deſpiſe thoſe in whom we are forced to acknowledge our own Image; for howſoever the rich may account of the poor, the poor by nature is as good as the rich, the rich are no better then they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29387:19"/>they are all alike by nature. So <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Our fleſh is as the fleſh of our brethren, and our ſons as their ſons, and though they be brought in ſubjection, they and their children, their lands and their vineyards;</hi> yet here is their happineſſe, <hi>the Lord is their portion, and Heaven their Inheritance. Lazarus</hi> ſhall paſſe from the Paws of Dogs, to the Hands of Angels; from the Porch of a Tyrant, to the Boſome of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Thirdly. Let the rich help the poor, and the poor will help the rich. But perhaps ſome will ſay, We ſtand no need of Beggars help; yes ſure, thou ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in need of their Prayers, and pitty hath ever a Prayer for him that ſtands in need of it. Let the rich then releeve the poor, and the poor will pray for the rich; for this is the reaſon why God made ſome men rich, and ſome men poor; he made the rich men his ſons and heires here upon Earth, to the end, that their younger brethren, the poor, might have their ſecure ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and he made the poor men heires of Heaven, that the rich might have there their ſecure happineſſe: So that the rich by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eving the poor, and the poor by praying for the rich, might both, by Gods favour, have equall portions in Heaven. God made ſome rich, and ſome poor, that the abundance of the rich might ſupply the wants of the poor, and the abundance of the poor ſupply the wants of the rich, and ſo their for might be alike. Take it in the Apoſtles words,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.14.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t veſtra abandantia,</hi> that your abundance may ſupply their want, and their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance may be for your want, that there way be equallity. Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>That God did not create the rich to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the poor, but the poor, that the rich might not be barren of good works; and if the Clouds be full, they will poure forth raine upon the Earth: the rich man muſt be like a Cloud, if he have abundance, let him diſtribute it liberally.</hi> Fourthly, To give to the poor, is a means to thrive the better, becauſe thus we obtain Gods bleſſing to the doubling and multiplying of what we give; for pitty was ever profitable to them that uſed it. <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the Waters, after a few dayes thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> find it:</hi> Give to the poor, and though it ſeem to be as a thing ventured at Sea, yet it ſhall bring the profit, even ſuch profit as is beyond eſteem, unſpeakable joy, and a Kingdom without a change.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29387:20"/>
            <p>And here it may be enquired, ſince we muſt give to the poor, firſt, Who ought to give. Secondly, How much. Thirdly, To whom. And fourthly, In what manner.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, Who ought to give; My anſwer is, That every one who is not a receiver of Almes, ought to be a giver of Almes. It is true indeed, That this duty is firſt, and chiefly commended to the rich, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17.18. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.33. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.14. But our Lord Jeſus Chriſt goeth further, and commandeth, <hi>That if a man have two Coats, to give to him that hath none, and he that hath meat, to doe likewiſe,</hi> Luke 3.11.</p>
            <p>Touching the ſecond. How much we muſt give; and for this, I find no certain direction any where ſet down, but onely,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6</note> 
               <hi>That we ſhould give liberally;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.2</note> and give a portion to ſix and to ſeven;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5, 42 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</note> and to give to him that aske<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h; and every man as God hath bleſſed him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the third, To whom we muſt give; Luſty rogues of either Sex onely excepted, who either muſt work,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3, 10.</note> 
               <hi>or elſe let them not eat:</hi> due Correction is more neceſſary to give to ſuch (if they ask) then Bread.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6, 10.</note> But theſe perſons excepted, the anſwer ſhall be, <hi>Give to him that asketh; Doe good to all, but eſpecially to thoſe that be of the houſhold of faith;</hi> The Fatherleſſe, the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, the helpleſſe perſons, the Aged, Halt, and Blind, and all that are in want, or needfull, are commended to your Charity.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But perhaps ſome will object and ſay, Would you have us to give to all that aske? we know, that the poor neer us are ſo bad, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cked; and ill-condition'd, that it is no Almes to give to them. And as for wanderers, the Statute, prohibits it; and beſides, being ſtrangers to us, we cannot tell whether it be Charity or no to give unto them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</hi> Theſe excuſes of thine, are no better then fig-leaves. I tell thee, thou muſt doe good to all; and if any be ſo bad, together with your Almeſ-giving, give them admonition, and exhort them to reforme. And as for ſtrange Beggars, in whom indeed you may be deceived, yet your Almes ſhall be no whit the leſſe acceptable that you give them, ſeeing they aske as Chriſts poor Members, and in the name of poor and helpleſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29387:20"/>perſons; <hi>And he that gives to a Prophet in the name of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſhall not loſe a Prophets reward:</hi> but they ſhall be ſure to beare the burthen of their diſſimulation, whereby they invade the Inheritance of the poor, to the robbing and deſpoyling them of a great part thereof.</p>
            <p>Touching the fourth, In what manner Almes ought to be given. The anſwer is, They muſt be given cheerfully, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all vain-glory, and opinion of merit, and onely of that which is our own, and that in due ſeaſon, or due time. Firſt, cheerfully, <hi>For God loveth a cheerfull giver;</hi> He that giveth grudgingly, as it were out of conſtraint, doth indeed the thing commanded; but becauſe he doth it not with an heart, it is no more accepted of, then Prayer made with the Lips, when the Heart is away. Secondly, without Vain glory, We muſt give, not deſiring to have our Charity taken notice of by others; for ſo <hi>the Phariſees gave Almes to be ſeen, and prayſed of men;</hi> of whom it was ſaid, <hi>That they had their reward.</hi> Thirdly, With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all opinion of Merit; Almes muſt be given in humility, we acknowledging this to be our duty, as a Steward is bound in duty to give to every one his Portion; for we are but Stewards under God of that which we have; our Goods are a Portion committed to our truſt, to uſe according to his will, as the Talents in the Patable. Now God, by whoſe allowance we have theſe Portions, appointeth us to uſe them ſo, as the poor, may have comſort of them: and thus, in the perſons of the poor, we render unto God ſome part of his own again, for Chriſt accepts it as done unto him. Pourthly, We muſt give of that which is our own onely, not of what we have unjuſtly gotten; for, as is ſhewed in the Example of <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cheus, things unjuſtly gotten, muſt firſt be reſtored,</hi> and then Almes are to be given; for in giving ſtolen goods, or ſuch as be gotten by oppreſſion, or deceit, man maketh God a party in the theft, or wrong, which he hath committed; when as indeed he is ſo far from this, that he expoſtulateth with ſuch for comming into his Houſe; ſaying, <hi>Will you lye, ſteale, commit adultery, and come and worſhip in this Houſe, &amp;c.</hi> The juſt God will not, in the perſon of the poor, accept of any thing unjuſtly gotten. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29387:21"/>and laſtly, We muſt give in due time, or due ſeaſon; <hi>For the bleſſed man is like to a</hi> Tree,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>that bringeth forth fruit in due ſeaſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</note> And, <hi>whileſt we have time,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>let us doe good to all.</hi> Some rely upon a laſt Will and Teſtament, thinking to be accepted in their giving then, when they muſt needs depart with all that they have. To give, when a man can keep his goods no longer, is no better, then to break off from any ſin, when he can no more commit it. But for ſuch as have neglocted this duty in their life, let them humble themſelves; and rather then not at all, give liberally at their Death; and ſo happily, as the Lord ſhall ſee the heart truely affected with peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, they may be accepted in their giving then. Thus you ſee, how Charity is a principall point of true Religion. And if any ſhall alledge, <hi>That their goods are their own, and therefore ſee no reaſon</hi> (<hi>like churliſh</hi> Nabal) <hi>to make that common, which God hath given to their particular uſe?</hi> I anſwer, That thy goods doe indeed appertaine unto thee; but upon condition, that thou dealeſt one part thereof to the hungry and thirſty; for thou art but a Steward: and ſure, the hungry are defrauded of their right, unleſſe their wants be ſupplyed. And this is one thing that ſanctifieth the <hi>Faſt.</hi> Another thing is <hi>Prayer;</hi> for <hi>Faſting</hi> is but the hand-maid of <hi>Prayer;</hi> but of this when we come to the period of the Text, <hi>Cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having upon ſecond thoughts, (though contrary to the Rules of Art) lookt a little back upon the <hi>duty enjoyned,</hi> the firſt part of my Text. I now come to the ſecond circumſtance of the ſecond part, which I called; <hi>The Method, or Order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed;</hi> of which the firſt being this, <hi>Call a ſolemne Aſſembly.</hi> The next is, <hi>Gather the Elders, and all the Inhabitants of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is to be obſerved, The <hi>generality of this Faſt.</hi> In the Verſe fore-going the Text, you ſee a command layd onely upon ſome private perſons, <hi>the Prieſts, and the Miniſters,</hi> they are to howle and lament: but private mournings is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing for <hi>Publick Sorrows;</hi> there muſt be an epidemicall lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by <hi>a ſolemne Aſſembly.</hi> And this Aſſembly muſt not be thin, <hi>vel duo, vel nemo,</hi> as the ſaying is, a ſmall Congregation
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29387:21"/>to ſerve God; but it muſt be populous, and full, made up of a multitude, <hi>Gather the Elders, and all the Inhabitants of the Land.</hi> Hence, let this be the point; Chriſts Schoole, is a Schoole for all ſorts; not onely the <hi>Elders,</hi> but <hi>all the Inhabitants.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.29.30.</note> 
               <hi>Let the tares</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>grow with the wheat,</hi> it may be they may wither and dye ere Harveſt: the meaning is, That it may be they may dye to ſin. Witneſſe the Jayler, who over night was <hi>ſcourging;</hi> ere morning, <hi>wiſhing and anointing</hi> the wounds of the Apoſtles. Witneſſe <hi>Zacheus,</hi> who of a pilling and powling Publican, and a grinder of the faces of the poor, preſently became a mercifull refreſher of their bowels. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe many others, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Every mans life is a Way, wherein, without intermiſſion, he walkes from the Wombe to the Grave; <hi>Ab utero ad Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum ambulamus omnes;</hi> and this is the way which <hi>Joſhua</hi> calls, <hi>the way of all fleſh.</hi> But in this way there is a great difference, for ſome are upright in it, and thoſe are declared to be ſuch, as walk in the way of godlineſſe to glorification. Others turn aſide after the crooked wayes of ſin, and thoſe walk on unto perdition; they goe ſinging, and in a moment tumble into Hell. Now the Lord our God, <hi>that would not the death of a ſinner,</hi> calls all to Repentance, whileſt we, not feeling thoſe privy nips, and perillous wounds, that ſin impaires our ſoules withall, doe ſwim in the fulleſt delights, that invention can procure us, and our ſouls cleaving to the midſt of our mirth, our way but beguyles us; and for not minding our Voyage, in ſtead of arriving at our wiſhed for Haven, we are suckt into the gulfe ere ever we are aw re; ſo that we had need labour for a Reformation, by the wholeſome Information of the Word; and Chriſts Schoole, being a Schoole for all ſorts, we had need all become Schollars in the Schoole of Chriſt, both young and old, and old as well as young.</p>
            <p>Firſt, young men; for the age of youth is indeed the age of right reformation; Bend a tree while it is but a twig, and it will ply which way you will have it; but let it alone untill it be a ſturdy Oke, there is then no dealing with it. Even ſo, ſettle the ſoule once upon the lees of ſinfull luſt, and cuſtome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29387:22"/>in ſinning proves another nature, and in the end becomes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible, incorrigible. Let a man through his youth ſet his face againſt Heaven, and blaſpheme Gods Religion; it ſhall be as eaſie for the <hi>Blackamoore to change his hue, or the Leopard his ſpots,</hi> as for that man that hath been alwayes accuſtomed to evill, ever to learn to doe well: I doe not ſay imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſible, for I know that it is the eaſieſt thing in the world with God to enrich a ſinner with his grace; and therefore we diſpute not his power, nor his mercy. Not his power, for God can in an inſtant make of a ſinner a Saint. Not his mercy, for Gods mercy knows no bounds nor limits. But it is not eaſie for that ſinner that hath been alwayes accuſtomed to doe evill, ever to learn to doe well; for, you know, the curſe is commonly paſſed out againſt thoſe who have been ſo long fruitleſſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>Never fruit grow on thee hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth</hi> neither in this World, nor in the World to come; reape they ſhall, bring forth they ſhall not; but they ſhall reape the fruit of Judgement, the fruit of puniſhment; other fruit they ſhall never bring forth, dead Trees, cut off from the land of the living; dead Branches, cut off from the Tree of Life. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, what can that ground expect that brings forth nothing but thorns and bryars,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8.</note> but that the end of it ſhould be to be burned? So that though ye rejoyce in your youth, O ye young men, yet remember you muſt come to Judgement. And ſure it is but an evill and wofull diviſion, when young years are given to Sathan, and old age to the Lord. Its the firſt fruits that God requires; And you may find Saint <hi>John</hi> writing to <hi>Young men, as well as to Elders;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.12 13.</note> 
               <hi>to Children, as well as to Fathers.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth the young man,<hi>Eccleſ</hi> 12.1</note> 
               <hi>To remember his Creator in the dayes of his youth.</hi> And <hi>David,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 9</note> to redreſſe his wayes:</hi> For indeed, the age of youth is the very Harveſt and Summer, in which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſleepeth, is the ſon of confuſion; but he that gathereth is the child of wiſedome.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.5.</note> It is with grace, as it is with grafts, there muſt be a time of in-ſetting, and a time of out-growing, and both theſe muſt be ſeaſonable before fruit can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; ſo that ſeed muſt be ſown in youth, which muſt come up in age; For nip a bloſſome in the Spring, and where is the hope of its Autumne? And indeed, where Sathan can make youth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29387:22"/>unprofitable, little good nay, much ſpirituall beggery may be expected in all the other ages of that mans life. Again, Call thy wayes to remembrance while thou art young, that thy Conſcience may be at peace when thou art aged; for aſſure thy ſelfe that the vanitles of youth will vex the heart for many yeares after.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.7.</note> See <hi>David</hi> Praying againſt <hi>the ſins of his youth,</hi> and not without a bitter ſenſe and ſting of them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.7. <hi>Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 13.16.</note> 
               <hi>It was the voyce of</hi> Ephraim, <hi>I was aſhamed yea, confounded, becauſe I did beare the roproach of my youth;</hi> for though for the preſent a man may be ſenceleſſe of his groſſeſt ſins; yet God will waken his Conſcience at laſt, and make the very thought of his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities as bitter, as ever the practice of them was pleaſant; the thought of them will fill him with trouble of Conſcience, and bring him not onely to doubt of his effectuall calling to Grace, but almoſt to a deſpaire of his ſalvation. And if he would be fenced againſt all theſe afterclaps, the time is now wherein he may prevent ſuch afflictions, by bearing Gods yoke in his youth: Now is the time wherein he ſhould take notice of that great bundle of folly which is naturally bound up in his heart. But alas! No age ſo much ſtops its eares, as this age of youth, charme the charmer never ſo wiſely: For whereas young men ſhould live as <hi>Nazarites, conſecrated to the Lord;</hi> they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther live like men that have vowed, and dedicated themſelves to the ſervice of Sathan, loathing or ſeorning to become Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in the Schoole of Chriſt, which indeed is moſt effectuall to cure the diſordered affections of youth: But thoſe that would be Trees of Righteouſneſſe, and known to be of the Lords own Planting, laden eſpecially in their age with the fruits of the Spirit, muſt in their youth, timely bud, timely bloſſome, and timely beare; that ſo their whole lives may be a fruitfull courſe, whereby God may be glorified, others edified, and themſelves receive in the end a more full conſolation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as young men, ſo old as well as young, muſt be Schollars in the Schoole of Chriſt; for though its true, that the age of youth, of all ages, is moſt ſubject to the dangerous diſeaſes of inordinate luſts: yet there is no age without its blemiſhes, not the hoary haire without its errors, <hi>David,</hi> ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29387:23"/>often as he conſidered his wayes, found alwayes ſomething that needed redreſſe; and there is none ſo well renewed in this life, but they may find ſomthing in themſelves that needs further reformation. Who can ſay, he hath in ſuch ſort cleanſed his Heart, as that he need not make it more cleane? Certainely, when ſins are lopt, they grow againe; when they are chaſed away, they may turne againe, and the fire of ſin being quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it kindles againe; ſo that we had need often lop our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous affections; if it be poſſible, alwayes. For let a man tell the truth as he finds it, and I dare ſay, he finds alwayes ſomething in himſelfe needing reformation. So that Old, as well as Young, ſhould come to this Schoole. For ſurely, its a double ſhame and ſin for an old man to be of an uncleane life, or to be ignorant of the Word, having lived till his head be gray, without making any progreſſe at all in the knowledge of godlineſſe. The neerer we draw unto the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the further off ſhould we be from the delights of <hi>Egypt;</hi> otherwiſe it will come to paſſe, in Gods righteous Judgement, that when in regard of our long journey, we are come to the very borders of that good Land, we ſhall be put back again, with thoſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and never ſuffred to enter into it. O miſerable condition of that man, whoſe body is declining to the Grave, but his ſpirit hath never learned to aſcend to him that gave it: he come (as I ſaid) to the very borders of <hi>Canaan,</hi> I meane, to the very point of time wherein Gods Children make their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py tranſmigration; but by reaſon of his ſins, he is thruſt back againe, and never ſuffered to enter, when he ſhould dye and aſcend to the bleſſed fellowſhip of God, the Father of Lights: he dyes indeed, but deſcends to the pit of utter darkeneſſe, <hi>where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> What a woefull caſe then is it, that men ſhould be thus ſould under ſin; nay, even ſpend and weare out themſelves in plotting and contriving who ſhould get themſelves ſureſt and deepeſt in? How are even the hearts of the Ancient, whoſe Faces Age hath wrick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, carried away, to ſeek abundance, deſiring onely to become Heires of the World, never ſeeking God, nor his Kingdom, for their Portion? And though this ſervice of profit ſeen ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29387:23"/>more ſweet and eaſie then the ſervice of righteouſneſſe; yet when this Maſter comes with his wages, then tell me what becoms of the lovers of the World, more then of the lovers of God?<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> ſurely they <hi>ſhall not fayle to receive the wages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe.</hi> O miſerable ſervice! nay, it is to be feared, that many of our gliſtering ſaints, our glorious profeſſors, who would be admired for their holineſſe, are too much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched with the ſorcery of this ſinne: But let them know, whoſoever they be, that for all their outward varniſh, and faire flouriſhes of devotion, and ſhews of ſeeming holineſſe; who, as if ſanctity were ingaged onely to their ſervice; being ſick of a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> touch me not, I am more holy then thou, that their ſins of hypocriſie, and covetouſneſſe, will ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh even the beſt things they have received, and darken the beſt duties they attempt: For indeed, a rare profeſſour is that man, that can avoyd an Earthly mind in Earthly matters; and while he layes up on Earth, hath a free mind to treaſure in Heaven. O that we could conſider how theſe hatefull poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous ſins make us even juſtly odious to our God; and therefore let us labour to ſee the poyſon of our own nature; and ſeeing it, ſtrive to bewayle it: And for that purpoſe, let Young and Old, and Old at well as Young, all become Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the Schoole of Chriſt; for true Knowledge is that which works Godlineſſe. <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe, <hi>who was learned in all the learning of the Egyptians,</hi> muſt ſtudy to ſeek the Lord with an inward affection. And though <hi>David</hi> had more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding <hi>then his teachers;</hi> yet he earneſtly deſires, to be further taught of the Lord his God; for the treaſures of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold wiſedome locked up in the Word, are ſo rich; that no man can attaine to ſuch meaſure of Knowledge, but ſtill he hath need to learne more: The Angels themſelves are but Schollars in this Schoole; and becauſe thou art Old, wilt thou ſcorne to learne with Angels? The very beſt, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his wayes, may finde ſomething in him to be amended. The Doctors and Maſters of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were but Fools in Chriſts eſteeme. The young man that thought ſo goodly of himſelfe, was ignorant of the way to Heaven, and would learne of our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29387:24"/>Saviour, how, or what to doe, to inherit Eternall Life. The Wiſeſt of Men, <hi>ſeeks for Wiſedome.</hi> And the Princely Prophet, <hi>begs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> Let then high and low, rich and poor, old and young, all, run to that Fountaine from whence thoſe Waters of Knowledge flow in abundance; for Chriſts Schoole is a Schoole for all ſorts; <hi>Not onely the Elders, but all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the generality of this Convocation, another Point may be this, That the Kingdome of Chriſt admits of no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, neither Prince, nor Peaſant, for they are both his Subjects, both the worke of his hands. His Vineyard admits of all ſorts of Labourers, from the Morning till the Evening; nay, to the very laſt Houre, the gates of mercy ſtand open for all; and Gods call is generall, <hi>Come unto me all you that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, and are heavy laden, &amp;c.</hi> He calls not onely the King, but the Subject; not onely the Lord, but the Slave; He calls the Poor, the Servant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.13</note> 
               <hi>and they receive the Goſpel:</hi> Nay, <hi>Chriſt came to call ſinners to repentance,</hi> without exception, <hi>even Publicans and Sinners.</hi> The God whom we ſerve, is no excepter of perſons; and the Kingdome of Chriſt admits of no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction. Its true indeed, there was a difference held, and a wall of partition was ſet up between Jew and Gentile, between People and People. Before the Flood were the Sons of God, and the Sons of Men: After the Flood, before the Law, there was the Promiſed Seed, and the Seed of the Fleſh: after the Law, before Chriſt, was held the diſtinction of Jew and Gentile: With the former, God made his Covenant, them he took into his teaching, and paſſed by the other: To them pertained the Adoption, the Glory, the Covenant, the giving of the Law, the Service of God, the Oracles, the Promiſes; Theſe had his Tempe, his Prophets, ordinary and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. This difference <hi>David</hi> meants of, in thoſe words, <hi>He ſhewed his Word unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>his Statutes and Judgements unto</hi> Iſrael: <hi>But he dealt not ſo with every Nation, neither have they known his wayes,</hi> Pſal. 147.19.20. But now in this laſt Age of the World, this Covenant of <hi>Grace and Life,</hi> is made common to all People; every man is now called to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:29387:24"/>and invited to come and drinke of Chriſts blood by Faith; the partition wall is now broken downe, the Vaile is rent, the gates of mercy wide opened, and that Myſtery which was kept ſeeret from the beginning of the World, is Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to all. The conſideration whereof, ſhould ſtir us up to an exceeding rejoycing, in that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 54.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>The barren and deſolate hath now more children then the Married Wife: that the place of the tents of the Church is thus enlarged, and the Curtains of her habitation thus ſpread out;</hi> ſo that the Dogs and Whelps may now clap their hands for joy that they are received into pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that the wings of Gods mercy are ſtretched out over them: The poor beleever, the thrall, the ſervant, the baſe in the world, may cheere up their hearts, that even they whom men ſo deſpiſed, are now ſo effectually called, to ſee the Grace and Salvation of God. He that parhaps is but a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to ſome meane man here upon Earth, is a free Citizen in the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> he that hath never a foot here below, is become a great purchaſer above. Here is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint that the Prodigall Son is entertain'd, and the ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Son neglected. The <hi>Eunuch</hi> need not now complaine and ſay, <hi>I am a dry tree.</hi> Nor the Son of the ſtranger.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 56.3.</note> The Lord hath ſurely ſeparated me from his people: but whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever cleave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h unto the Lord to love the Lord, and ſerve him, <hi>to them he will give a name better then of Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, even an everlaſting name, that ſhall never be put out:</hi> Thus you ſee. That the generall promiſes of the Goſpel, are Publiſhed and offered to all, without exception, bond and free, Publican and ſinner, ſtrangers and forreighners, are now <hi>Comites Sanctorum,</hi> fellow Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God: ſo that our ſins need not hinder us from approching to the Throns of Grace, if we can but come to the Lord Jeſus upon the Feet of Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, heavens gates are as wide as ever, and the call as univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall as ever; <hi>Not onely the Elders, but all the Inhabitants of the Land.</hi> So we ſtep on to the third Circumſtance, in the <hi>Method or Order of keeping this Faſt; the place of refuge, or Sacred Sanctuary, the Houſe of the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:29387:25"/>
            <p>I muſt now, like a faithfull Steward in my Maſters houſe, take by the hand all you the weary Sons and Daughters of the everliving God, and leade you into the Kings Wine-ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, there to refreſh and ſtay you <hi>with the Flagons of his Wine, to comfort you with his Apples, to ſtrengthen you with his hidden Manna, and to make you merry with that Milke and Honey which our ſo dearely loving Husband Chriſt Jeſus hath provided for us, to ſuſtaine us that we faint not through thoſe manifold temptations which encumpaſſe us in this barren Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi> namely, <hi>into this right Arke, or little Zoar, The Houſe of the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Colledge of the bodily Phyſitians, and the Prince of them, that Wiſe and Learned <hi>Galen</hi> preſcribes for the time of Plague, that of all Remedies to prevent the contagion, the beſt is, <hi>To fly, and ſhun the infected and corrupted Ayre, and to depart unto a wholeſome and purer Ayre;</hi> and that with theſe three Rales, <hi>Citò, Longè, Tardè;</hi> To depart ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, farre off, and returne ſlowly. And as this is Phyſically preſcribed, ſo it hath been as diligently practiſed by all ſorts of men: But becauſe by the corruption of our Nature (which is more then the corruption of the Ayre) we ſuffer our ſelves as with maine ſale to be carried away from the Creator to the Creatures, fixing all our ſenſes more upon the Aeriall corruption, then upon the inward cauſe of the contagion, the Plague of our ſins, and rottenneſſe of our bones and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, which we carry within our ſelves, and are more carefull to depart into the Country then unto the Lord, as if by the ſwiftneſſe of our Feet, we could out-run him who <hi>Rideth upon the Wings of the Cherubims,</hi> which often cauſeth, that the Lords Purſuivant doth often Arreſt us in the purer Ayre, as well in the Country, as in the City.</p>
            <p>In the time of Famine, the beſt Remedy is, To fly from places of ſcarcity, to places of more plenty. And this was practiſed by <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.5.</note> 
               <hi>who went into Egypt to buy Food;</hi> but becauſe of their ſins, trouble came upon them in their very firſt journey thither; and though after that they were nouriſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>and had Poſſeſſions in the beſt of the Land;</hi> yet were
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29387:25"/>they at laſt kept under <hi>with burthens,</hi> and by cruelty <hi>cauſed to ſerve;</hi> inſomuch,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>that the Egyptians made them weary of their lives by ſore labour in Clay and Bricke, and in all worke of the Field with all manner of Bondage which they cruelly layd upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the time of Warre, The beſt way to preſerve our goods from ſpoyle, and our ſelves from Captivity is, To fly to the beſt and ſtrongeſt Garriſons; and this was as diligently pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by us in the time of the late Warrs in this unhappy Land; but that proved ſo poor a ſafegard, as that which was there preſerved for a time, quickly became a Prey to others. And ſince in the ſtorms of miſery all theſe are ſuch poor ſhelters; I will therefore preſcribe you a better flight in the time of Plague, or Famine, or Warre, or any other common calamity, then that of <hi>Galen,</hi> or that of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Sonne, or that of our <hi>Engliſh;</hi> namely. To the name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> that Tower Royall; or as <hi>Solomon</hi> calls it, ſtrong Tower,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the Righteous runneth unto it, and is preſerved; even the Houſe of the Lord our God.</hi> And this was <hi>Davids</hi> practice in the time of Plague.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.25</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the time of Warre: And here, the Prophets directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the time of Famine,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.1.</note> 
               <hi>Gather the Elders, and all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Land into the Honſe of the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, that I may the better inſtruct you in this jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to this Houſe, I will branch the deſcription of this Houſe into theſe three ſeverall parts, which will ſtore us with clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of ſingular Meditations. Firſt, the Name of this Place, <hi>its an Houſe,</hi> and therefore a ſhelter againſt all ſtormes and tempeſts. Secondly, The property of this Place, <hi>its the Houſe of the Lord,</hi> and therefore able to defend us againſt all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults and violence. Thirdly, the ſafeneſſe of this Place, the owner <hi>is our God,</hi> God is our Father, and ſuch a Father as will not ſhut the doore againſt his children, that in time of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity fly to him for ſecurity. So that in comming to this place,<note place="margin">Exod. 24.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.3.</note> 
               <hi>we come to the Lord our God, ſtrong, mercifull, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, flow to anger, and abundant in goodneſſe and truth. We come to the Lord our God, the ſupream Phyſitian of our ſoules,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29387:26"/>who healeth all our iniquities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>We come to the Lord our God, to whom power belongeth, and whoſe alone is ſalvation. Who would not then run to this Place, this Houſe, this Tower Royal in the time of Warre, Plague, Famine, Sickneſſes, Diſeaſes, or any Calamity, or Miſery?</hi> O ye Righteous ſouls that thirſt, or may thirſt, by reaſon of the heate of the Plague, or at leaſt by reaſon of the heate of the Plague of ſinne, fly unto this place; Here be the waters of comfort, here are wells enough to be drawne off to coole the heate of a thirſting ſoule: This is the Place which God hath Proclaimed to the World, <hi>That if the heavy laden will but come he will eaſe them; if the thirſty will but come, he will refreſh them.</hi> O ye Righteous ſouls, who in the time of Warre, are in continuall feare and danger of your bodies impriſoning, of your goods plundering, of your ſons butchering, of your daughters deflouring, and of the pouring forth of your blood like water upon the ground; and not onely the perpetuall enſlaving of you, and your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, but that which is worſt of all, the violating of your Conſciences by Oaths and Ingagements, at the will of the Conquerour, <hi>fly unto this Houſe;</hi> here be the Armes and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the ſtrong men, and when you cry, your Enemies ſhall turne backe. O ye Righteous ſouls, who in the time of Famine are ready to dye for hunger, having pale and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Faces, lanke and leane bodies, hunger-ſtarved carkaſſes, and in this extremity know not what to doe; run to this <hi>Flace, this Houſe,</hi> the Maſter whereof <hi>can feed an</hi> Elias <hi>by Ravens;</hi> A <hi>Daniell in Dungeons; And the Widow and her Son with a Cruſe of Oyle that never waſteth:</hi> and here ſhall ye be ſure to finde ſatning food for your ſoules. In a word, In any ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, in all ſtraights and miſeries whatſoever, fly to <hi>this Place, this Houſe of the Lord your God.</hi> And in all kinds of diſtreſſe, let us approach this Throne of Grace; let us enter theſe Gates and Courts with joy; let our Prayers come unto him in his holy Temple; and let us all, like <hi>David, be glad when men ſay, Come lot us goe to the Houſe of the Lord;</hi> for there is ſalve for every ſore, there is medicine for every diſe aſe, and there is comfort at all aſſayes. In this world we are as Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29387:26"/>having here no continuing City; and while we are at home in the body, we are abſent from the Lord; in which Pilgrimage, <hi>many are the troubles of the Righteous;</hi> and if they fly to this ſacred Sanctuary, <hi>and there cry unto the Lord, the</hi> Lord <hi>delivers them out of all.</hi> And to hearren you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, know for your comforts, That the Lord whom you ſerve, is not like to the Princes and Rulers of the Earth, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not to be moleſted with requeſts from their diſtreſſed Subjects; but its joy to the Almighty, and he takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to heare their ſupplications, and is moſt glad when they aske, or beg of him the beſt things. What a comfort is this then to all afflicted ſouls, in the heat and height of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and depth of their miſeries, to have a place of refuge, and a place of refreſhment, and preſervation to run unto, and there refreſh their wearied members, and ſupplicate the God of Glory, and the God of all Conſolation.</p>
            <p>But now, though we have a place of ſafety to fly unto in the time of trouble and danger; yet a man may miſtake his way thither and then, never a whit the neerer: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, leaſt we ſhould erre in our way to this place, the Lord himſelfe hath given us a conſtant guide, and card of directi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to leade us thereunto, even the witneſſe of his holy Word, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itten, and Sealed, that can never deceive us, but is as a fiery pillar unto us in the darke deſert of this World, to ſhew us the way to that Heavenly <hi>Canaan; It is a lanthorne to our feet, and a light to our paths:</hi> let then our loynes be girded, and let us beare in our hands this ſhining light. But yet, though we have a place to <hi>fly to in trouble,</hi> and likewiſe, a <hi>guide to direct us the way;</hi> yet a man (eſpecially in miſery) would not willingly goe to a place, where he hath neither title, nor right, nor intereſt, nor friend, nor acquaintance, where he may expect, if not ſhutting the doore upon him, yet, at leaſt, poor entertainment, and miſerable comforters. Now to hearten us againſt theſe feares, the Text tells us, <hi>That we are of the ſame Family, or Houſhold,</hi> for the Maſter, or Lord of this houſe, <hi>is our God,</hi> ſo that it is, as it were, our own; for it is uſuall for Children, or ſervants, to call
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29387:27"/>their Fathers or Maſters houſe wherein they live, our Houſe, and there we ſhall finde our beſt acquaintance, and our choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt friends, <hi>even God, our Father; Chriſt, our Brother; and the holy Ghoſt, our Comforter.</hi> But ſtill, though we have a ſecure place of refuge to <hi>fly unto in danger,</hi> and a <hi>guide to direct us that we erre not in our way, and good right and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt thereunto, being of the ſame Family, and Friends, and acquaintance there alſo;</hi> yet being infected with the Plague of ſinne, and laden with iniquity, we may feare that we ſhall not be received; for thoſe in whoſe ſoules the Plague of ſin doth reigne, however they may come into the ſociety of the Church yet cannot be admitted to the Throne of Grace; And therefore to the end our ſins ſhould neither diſhearten, nor hinder us; know, That the Lord our God hath given us Chriſt the Righteous, to cover our unrighteouſneſſo, ſo that as pure and cleane we might come unto him; He hath put on us <hi>the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14.</note> that being adorned with his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and holineſſe, as <hi>lacob</hi> was with the goodly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his elder Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> we might with confidence betake our ſelves to this <hi>Aſylum,</hi> and in the name of Chriſt, might goe to the name of <hi>Iohovah;</hi> and in his name, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hath as much right to goe, as the King; the People, as the Prieſt; the Slave, as the Lord; the Servant, as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; and the infected, as the ſound; for Chriſt prayeth with us all as our Brother; he prayes for us all as our High Prieſt; and he is prayd unto by us all, as our Lord; he alone is the Eye wherewith we ſee the Father, the Hand to offer up our Prayers unto him, the Mouth to ſpeake unto him; and therefore let us goe unto him, by vertue of this right, that he is the Lord our God, and we of his Family and Houſhold.</p>
            <p>But for all this, <hi>though we have a Houſe to goe unto, and want not a guide, and be of the ſame Family, and ſtored with Acquaintance, and adorned with our Elder Brothers Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> yet, if we be lame, or have not Feet to carry us thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we are but like the Creeple at the Poole, obnoxious to all hindrances. And therefore, though the Feet of the Fleſh be ſufficient to carry us to the Church; yet we muſt have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29387:27"/>other Feet, even ſpirituall Legs, before we can come to this Houſe; namely, the Feet of Faith and Prayer: Faith is the firſt Foot;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>for if by Faith we ſtand,</hi> by Faith we may alſo goe to the Lord, who is faithfull; and how could we goe unto him by the Foot of Prayer, if we did not beleeve in him?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>For how ſhall they call on him, in whom they have not belce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Foot is <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is ſo ſwift a Foot, as that it diſpatcheth in an inſtant all the way betwixt Heaven and Earth, and as a fiery Chariot mounts into the preſence of the Almighty to implore his aſſiſtance; and though we live here in this vale of miſery, ſo farre off from our Fathers Houſe; yet being furniſhed with theſe two ſpirituall Feet, we may in a moment aſcend up thither, and there recreate our wearied ſpirits; though we live in this world, as in a waſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, if we be in want of any thing, with theſe ſpirituall Fees we may runne to our Fathers Houſe, and there provide our ſelves. If the Lord hath eaſt us down upon our bed of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that we cannot uſe the Feet of our bodies; yet he hath given us thoſe other Feet of <hi>Faith and Prayer</hi> to uſe in flead of them. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> being ſick of the Plague,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.2.</note> could not uſe the <hi>Feet of his Body;</hi> but with the <hi>Feet of the Spirit,</hi> he went unto this place. <hi>Ionah</hi> was lockt up in Priſon <hi>in the belly of the Whale,</hi> yet by the vertue of theſe Feet, <hi>out of the depth</hi> he aſcended to the holy Temple of <hi>Iehovah.</hi> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this <hi>though we know we have a Houſe to goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and no hinderance in the way, nor difficulty in the paſſage, nor want a guide to direct us, and have good right to the place, and friends and acquaintance to entertaine us, and robes to adorne us, and feet to carry us thither;</hi> yet if we know not how to behave our ſelves when we come there, though we come as ſuiters, we ſhall be but bad ſpeeders. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the next ſhall be, <hi>to teach you how to demeanc your ſelves in this Houſe of the Lord your God.</hi> And for this purpoſe, I ſhall for your ſakes, endeavour my ſelfe to binde you all to ſuch good behaviour in Gods Houſe, as becomes the glory of his publick ſervice and preſence; for the godly Chriſtian
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29387:28"/>ought with all care to lay before him the rules that tye him to a comely compoſure and carryage in the Houſe of God; and to ſtrive to faſhion his nature and practice ſo, as may become the Majeſty of his Publick Worſhip: for there be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things which in a ſpeciall manner muſt be lookt unto in performing theſe publick duties: And to this end, I ſhall give you ſome few Rules, which if you pleaſe to obſerve, you ſhall not onely be good <hi>Suiters,</hi> but good <hi>Speeders</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Firſt, All, of all ſorts, muſt come and appear publikely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, to doe him homage and ſervice, <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unita fortior,</hi> the more, the better; <hi>not onely the Elders, but all the Iuhabitants of the Land.</hi> This you may ſee in <hi>Deutoronomy</hi> 31.11.12.13. where you ſhall find, <hi>That all</hi> Iſrael <hi>were to come to appeare before the Lord their God in the place which he ſhould chuſe, men women, and children, and the ſtranger within their gates, that they might heare, and learne, and feare the Lord their God, and keep and obſerve the words of his Law:</hi> none exempted, all muſt come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We muſt come with all poſſible reverence, and look to our feet when we enter into the Houſe of God, and ſtrive to ſhew before all men our moſt carefull reſpect to God &amp; his holy Ordinances; <hi>for God will be ſanctified by them that come neer him,</hi> and he looks for it at our hands, by our reverent behaviour, to be glorified before all the people. See it your ſelves, in the tenth of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and the third: And <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the fifth, and firſt; and be perſwaded to ſhew a moſt holy and reverent feare of Gods name, and preſence; So that Princely Prophet. <hi>I will come into thine Houſe in the multitude of thy mercies: and in thy feare will I worſhip towards thy holy temple,</hi> Pſal. 5.7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We muſt come with a great deale of Zeale: In all publick duties that of <hi>David</hi> ſhould be true of us, <hi>The Zeale of Gods Houſe ſhould eat us up</hi> Pſal 69.9. And this ſingular Zeale we ſhould ſhew theſe ſix wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By loving Gods Houſe above all other places in the world, our heart, ſhould be fired in us in that reſpect; that we may true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay with the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8</note> 
               <hi>O how I love thy houſe! I have loved the habitation of thine houſe, and the place where thine honour-dwelleth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:29387:28"/>
            <p n="2">2. By reſolutely purpoſing to reſort to Gods Houſe with joy and gladneſſe, notwithſtanding the ſcornes and oppoſitions of worldly men. O that we were of <hi>Davids</hi> mind, <hi>glad, when men ſay, Come, let us goe into the Houſe of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 122.1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By ſtirring up others with all importunity to goe with us to worſhip God in <hi>Sion. The mountaine of the Houſe of the Lord ſhall be prepared in the top of the mountaines, and ſhall be exalted above the hils; and all Nations ſhall flow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it:</hi> (the word <hi>flow,</hi> declaring the zeale of the Children of God when they are called.) <hi>And many people ſhall goe and ſay, Come, let us goe up to the mountaine of the Lord, to the Houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he will teach us his wayes, and we will walke in his paths; for the Law ſhall goe forth of</hi> Zion, <hi>and the Word of the Lord from</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Iſay</hi> 2.2.3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By making haſt to Gods worſhip, going to the Houſe of the Lord with the firſt, and with willing hearts, with an holy thirſt after the means, flocking and flying thither as the Cloudes, or as ſo many Doves to their Windows. Up, <hi>let us goe and pray before the Lord, and ſeek the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Zachar. 8.21. And the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Thy people ſhall come wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly at the time of aſſembling thine army in holy beauty; from the wombe of the morning, thou haſt the dew of thy youth,</hi> Pſal. 110.3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By forwardneſſe and cheerefulneſſe in contributing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the maintenance of Gods Houſe and ſervice in the means thereof.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By grieving heartily, becauſe other men neglect and contemne the Houſe of God: The Zeale of Gods Children ought to be ſuch, when they ſee his Word ſleighted, as that they ſhould be like <hi>David, whoſe Eyes guſht out with Rivers of Water, becauſe men keep not thy Law,</hi> Pſal. 119.136.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We ſhould in all publick Duties, ſerve God with one conſent, and one heart; There ſhould appeare in Gods ſervants a wonderfull deſire of unanimity and concord, that when they ſpeake to God, it may be as the voyce of one man; when the Lord ſpeaks to them, they ſhould heare with one Eare: It is a marvellous glory in Religion, when people can come
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29387:29"/>to this, to ſerve the Lord with one ſhoulder; Let us all <hi>call upon the name of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>and ſerve him with one conſent,</hi> or as it were with one ſhoulder.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, and laſtly, look upon the fifty ſecond <hi>Pſalme,</hi> eighth and ninth verſes; and from thence we may gather three other Rules which in a ſpeciall manner fit us for a decent behaviour in Gods Houſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſhould alwayes be as green Olive-trees in the Houſe of the Lord; <hi>But I ſhall be like a green Olive tree in the Houſe of God:</hi> For howſoever it goe with men in the world, yet when we come before the Lord, our hearts ſhould rejoyce and revive, and our ſpirits be freſh and cheerfull, and our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſhould be healed of all the cares and diſtempers that were in them before. Gods Ordinances ſhould have ſuch a power over us as to make a ſuddaine freſh ſpring of deſires and holy thoughts in us; there is that power in the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God to effect this, if the fault be not in us, I meane, when theſe Ordinances are exerciſed in the power and life of them. Let us then rejoyce to have a place among the ſervants of God, that we may grow in the knowledge of godlineſſe, and be like green Olive-trees in the Houſe of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt truſt in the mercy of God, <hi>For I truſted in the mercy of God for ever and ever,</hi> bringing an heart ready to beleev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every good Word of God; and reſolving, that if the Lord will ſpeak comfortably to his ſervants, we will not diſhonour his conſolations through careleſneſſe and unbeleefe, but receive them with all our hearts, and eſtabliſh our ſelves in the ſafe keeping of his good word; Let us truſt in the mercy of God for ever and ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt reſolve to be thankfull, <hi>I will alwayes prayſe thee for that thou haſt done.</hi> Let us be thankfull with all earneſtneſſe for all experiences of Gods preſence and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards us in the means, vowing with <hi>David, to prayſe him for ever for them;</hi> and if the Lord doe with-hold hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power and preſence for a time, ſo as we feele not the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualneſſe of his Ordinances, yet we ſhould reſolve, withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſtemper, to wait upon the Lord, and obſerve him, according
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29387:29"/>to the ſeaſons of his grace, and alwayes prayſe him for that he hath done.</p>
            <p>Thus having hitherto endevoured to tye you all to ſuch good behaviour in the Houſe of the Lord in all your publick ſervice and worſhip of God, as ſhall become the glory of his preſence, wiſhing that theſe my weak and unskilfull labours might wooe ſome more excellent Wits and more skilfull Pens, to better this Diſcourſe, ſo needfull to be ſounded in our Ears in theſe unhappy and unmannerly times, wherein ſo many come ſo ſaweily, and irreverently into the preſence of the God of glory, never once conſidering with <hi>Jacob, How dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is this Place, and that this is no other but the Houſe of God.</hi> I ſhall now likewiſe endeavour to tye you all to the good-behaviour in your hearing of the Word of God; for which, theſe three directions will order you aright; whereof ſome will bind us to the good-behaviour before we come to heare, ſome at the time of hearing, and ſome after we have heard.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Before we come to heare,</hi> We muſt bring with us two things. Firſt, A reſolution to deny our own wits, reaſons, opinions, and conceits, and empty our heads of all perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our own skill, to judge of the things of God, being ready to beleeve and think in all things, as God ſhall teach us out of his Word;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>We muſt be fools, that we may be wiſe,</hi> humbling our ſelves at his very feet to receive his law.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3.</note> 
               <hi>They are humbled at thy feet to receive thy words.</hi> Secondly, We muſt bring with us a meek and quiet ſpirit, a mind quieted from paſſions and perturbations, and at reſt from the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiling cares of this world. The Word is able to doe great things in us, if we receive it with meekneſſe; <hi>Wherefore lay apart all filthineſſe, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe, and receive with meekeneſſe the ingrafted Word, which is able to ſave your ſoules,</hi> James 1.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>At the time of hearing,</hi> two things are to be obſerved. Firſt, We muſt hearken without diſtraction, we muſt heare as it were for our lives; we muſt incline our Ears, and ſhake off all impediments ariſing from our own drowſineſſe, or vain thoughts,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29387:30"/>or diſtracting objects; <hi>Encline your Eares, and come unto me: heare, and your ſoule ſhall live,</hi> Iſay 53.3. For indeed, the Preaching of the Word ſaveth the ſoule; it is able to make the ſoule immortall, if it be once ingrafted in us. For this cauſe, the Word is called,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>Incorruptible Seed, that endureth for ever,</hi> becauſe it maketh us incorruptible and happy for ever; for he that hath his ſoule ſaved, liveth for evermore. Now would you be ſharers in this unſpeakable bleſſedneſſe? the Word muſt then be ingrafted in your hearts, this heavenly plant of the Word muſt be ſet into your underſtandings and affections; for when a man heareth the VVord with underſtanding, it entreth into the heart, as the impe into the ſtocke; and when with love and affection he imbraceth it, it is cloſed about, that it may grow and proſper therein; but this Word cannot be ingrafted in our hearts, except the heart firſt be cleanſed; ſin muſt be put out, that the VVord may be ingrafted in; the filthineſſe of ſin, and all the ſprouts of malice, muſt be put away: of harſh, haſty, and churliſh; we muſt become meek, milde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.2.3.</note> and gentle. The Diſciples muſt become <hi>like little Children;</hi> that is, they muſt put away thoſe evill affections of Envy, Pride, deceit &amp;c. which grow upon them with yeares; otherwiſe, they ſhould but follow, and heare their Maſter in vaine, the VVord could not be ingrafted in them to ſave their ſoules. You may ſee the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> reproving the <hi>Jewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>That they came to holy duties in their ſins.</hi> So that firſt of all, there muſt be a putting away the evill of their doings; and then, a comming together to heare the Lord to their comfort. No wiſe man will ſow his Corne, or plant his delicate Fruit-trees, but will have the bryars and thornes firſt taken away, and whatſoever filthy ſtuffe may hinder the proſpering of his ſeed, and thriving of his plants: He will not poure Wine or Milke into filthy Veſſels; Every man cleares his Table books of the old writing, when he intends to put in any new matter. Now the VVord of God is ſeed, the Preaching of it is a Planting, it is VVine and Milke, and a writing in the table of mens hearts; all filthineſſe of ſin therefore muſt be removed, this ground muſt be cleared
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29387:30"/>from the bryars of Anger, Hatred, &amp;c. that the VVord may be Planted in; we muſt, like the Diſciples, and the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, leave off all, that we may attend the VVord of God; we muſt put away worldly things, which cauſe pollution in the heart; we muſt be like <hi>Zacheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19.8.</note> who that he might heare Chriſt to his ſalvation, put away <hi>Extortion, Bribery, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion;</hi> Or like the beleeving <hi>Epheſians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 19.19</note> who put away their curious Arts;</hi> Or like <hi>Saul,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4.</note> who ceaſed from going on in his perſecuting courſe, that he might heare Chriſt ſpeaking unto him.</hi> And thus the Word is able to make our ſoules Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; for tis a great deceit, to think to retaine our ſins ſtill, and yet to heare the Word unto ſalvation: And if ſo, then what ſhall become of thoſe men, that ſet down their reſolution to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in theirſins for a ſeaſon, &amp; are reſolved to trade in Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſſe, Whoredom, Covetouſneſſe, &amp;c? ſurely there can be no ground in ſuch mens hearts for the Word of God to grow up to the ſaving of their ſoules; the ſeed may happily be ſown amongſt them, but it cannot poſſibly enter to doe them good.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But it may be objected, That if the Word cannot profit any, but ſuch as put away all ſin, it cannot then profit any man that heareth, ſeeing no man can ſo put away his ſins as that his ground may be cleare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Anſwer is this, That every godly perſon doth cleere the ground of his heart from all ſin, ſo as that he is not pleaſed with any ſin, but he hates it, and himſelfe for commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it: he ſtrives againſt it, and he is dayly grieved, and poures forth his ſupplications for the pardon of it? You may look for this at your leiſures upon the firſt of Saint <hi>John,</hi> the third and third, and fifth, and eighteenth; and he that will not once put his helping hand to the removing of his ſins, that he may make roome for the Word of God to be grafted in him, need never look for any comfortable event of his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but having thus ſhaken off all impediments, all diſtracting objects, and hearkning unto the Word without diſturbance, hearing, as it were, for our lives; thus heare, and your ſoules ſhall live.</p>
            <p>Secondly, VVe muſt prove all things, and keep that which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29387:31"/>is good, we muſt heate with judgement, and hearken for our ſelves; its ordinary with moſt men to heare for others, and not for themſelves: but we muſt have a ſpeciall care to look to that Doctrine which in particular concerns us, to lay that up in our hearts, and apply it effectually; and this is a rule of ſingular thrift in godlineſſe, if we doe marke what ſin in us the Lord reproveth, or what comfort is eſpecially fitted to our hearts, or what direction doth chiefly concerne us; and he hath an honeſt memory that will be ſure to keep theſe things, though he forget all the reſt; but he hath a wretched memory, and heart too, that forgets theſe things, though he could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat all the Sermon <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>After we have heard,</hi> two things likewiſe muſt be done; Firſt, we muſt by Meditation labour to make thoſe things we have heard, and which concerns us, faſt, that they ſlip not out of our minds; and we muſt take heed, that neither the Devill ſteale away the good ſeed, nor our own hearts, through neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, loſe it, the VVord being let into the heart, muſt ſetledly continue, and not be broken off by the wild beaſts of vain ſpeeches and cogitations, nor blowne out by the guſts of ſtrong winds of Sathans temptations, or of his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that will immediately after we have heard the word, be offering other objects, for our minds to be taken up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>The bleſſed man doth not onely Reade, but Meditates upon the Word; David</hi> hid the word in his heart, even as he that hath bought a Pearle of incomparable worth hideth it: And as the Husbandman, having caſt his Seed into the ground, harrowes it in; ſo this Heavenly Plant of the word muſt be ſet into the underſtanding and affections, it muſt enter into the heart (as before is ſaid) like the Impe into the Stocke, and being imbraced, and cloſed about with love and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it then thrives, and grows, and proſpers. <hi>David</hi> is a notable example for this, how often doth he expreſſe his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the word, in his 119. <hi>Pſalme?</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22</note> 
               <hi>the Law to have been his delight,</hi> as it is indeed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every bleſſed man; for the hearing of the word is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; neither is it ſufficient to keep thoſe things we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:29387:31"/>heard for an houre, but it ought to be our delight, and our dayly worke; we ſhould alwayes be thinking and rumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of what we have heard, till there be a ſure impreſſion of the word in our hearts. Let then every one of us gage our ſoules, and try, and ſee whether we finde our ſelves to be ſuch, as to whom the word is thus powerfull to ſave our ſoules, that we goe not on upon falſe grounds in our hopes, about this unſpeakable bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Doth thy heart cleave before the word Preached, through trembling and terrour, in reſpect of thy ſins, and the ſins of others? Is it ingrafted in thee? Doth it enter into thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding? and is it cloſed about with a moſt earneſt love and affection? Doth it remaine with thee, after the hearing of it, by ſerious Meditation? and doth it grow? and is it vigorous in thy life, over-topping all ſuperfluous branches of ſin? then thou mayeſt truely comfort thy ſelfe, it ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be thy ſalvation. But if thine heart be hardened, and not to be moved before the word; if thy underſtanding be ſo blinded, as that thou haſt no apprehenſion of that which is taught; if thy affections be ſo benummed, as that thou art without all love unto it; if thou give way to world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vaine diſcourſes, works, or ſports, after thou haſt heard, inſomuch, that all departeth out of thy memory againe ſo ſoon as thou haſt received it; if all teaching be neglected, and thou ſwimmeſt in the ſtreame of thine owne corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; then look not up to the joyes of Heaven, for no part of them belongs unto thee: for though Food being eaten is able to ſave the life; and Apparell put on, to keep the body warme; and a Treaſure poſſeſſed, to enrich a man; yet he that Feedeth not, ſhall be Famiſht with Hunger; he that goeth Naked, ſhall be pinched with Cold; and he that hath wealth, and will not uſe it, is but a poor miſerable man: ſo he that maketh no better uſe of the word, which is the onely ſatning Food of his Soule, his Soule ſhall be hunger-ſtarved, and periſh, notwithſtanding all his hearing. And this is the caſe of moſt men in theſe times, wherein ſin, and the neglect of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, hath gotten ſuch an head, through a long continued
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29387:32"/>cuſtome, that though the heardeſt Oke is cloven with wedges, and the flintieſt Stone made hollow with continuall dropping of water; yet there is not one heart, amongſt many, penetrated by the VVord: and if there be any trembling ſometime, as it was with <hi>Felix,</hi> when <hi>Paul Preached,</hi> it is but for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the word is not retained, but flown from, as it was by him; ſo that there can be no growth of this Heavenly ſuckle in theſe mens lives; but branches of ſinne will be ſo luxuriant, that the word will be farre over-topt by them, and kept perpetually at under. And therefore, whoſoever doth deſire the word to be ſaved thereby, let him tremble at it, and yet embrace it; let him prepare his heart better to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine it; let him ſtirre up the ſpirit of his mind to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it; let him not loſe ſuch precious ſeed, for want of harrowing in, by due Meditation; and let him cheriſh it in his inward thoughts continually, that it may grow, and proſper, and more ſhew it ſelfe in his ſpeeches, actions, and company, then thoſe bryar-like ſprouts of his owne naturall corruptions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt ſee to it, that we be doers of the word, as well as hearers; we muſt not onely know, but obſerve and doe; for Knowledge without Practice, will availe nothing; and ſo much of the truth as is put into practice, is ſure for ever, the reſt may be loſt; and it is a ſingular help to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, to ſet upon his obedience while the Doctrine is yet freſh in his mind; for delay will compaſſe him about with many difficulties, and he will want thoſe inward incitations that might ſtirre up his heart with power and ſtrength to obey: And that this is the duty of every man, as well to doe, as to heare;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 1.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6.</note> ſee that in Saint <hi>James, Now ye heare theſe things, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are ye if ye doe them.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That every man ſhall be judged, not by his hearing, but by his doing, by his works;</hi> Then up and be doing, every one of you, whilſt time and ſtrength permits; for not onely that Fig-tree which had no Fruit, was accurſed; but that Tree likewiſe which brought not forth <hi>good Fruit, was to be hewen downe, and caſt into the Fire,</hi> Luke 3.9. And thoſe who have not <hi>fed the poor,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29387:32"/>and clothed the naked, &amp;c.</hi> will be bidden, <hi>Depart ye ourſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting fire,</hi> (Mat. 25.41.) Then what ſhall become of thoſe ſhadows and Ciphers among Chriſtians, who place their Religion onely in hearing? ſurely they want all ſubſtance of grace, and <hi>being put into the Ballance,</hi> as <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> was, <hi>they ſhall certainly be found too light,</hi> when the <hi>rewarding of every one ſhall be according to his works;</hi> then can they expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>tribulation and anguiſh, which ſhall be to every ſoule that doth evill.</hi> And it is to be feared, if inquiſition were made, more then our common ſort might be taxed for this neglect in doing, even ſome of thoſe, who pretend a great deale of Zeale to the Word, and are frequent and attentive hearers, and will runne to Meetings, and make glorious ſhewes of Devotion, giving Religion a thouſand good words; but for this duty of doing, <hi>procul abſit</hi> they have no heart unto it, Covetouſneſſe ſtill prevailes in them; and ſome of them, who would be thought, rare Profeſſors, can perhaps ſometimes be content to <hi>drinke a draught of ſtollen Waters,</hi> as well as others, making Religion a pretext onely, the more covertly to wallow in the mire of their ſins; but ſuch Kind of Profeſſors, what Zeale ſoever they may ſhew to the world, are but Painted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, beautifull onely outward; and woe unto them that are ſuch, for notwithſtanding all their gliſtering ſhewes, <hi>they are but whited Sepulchers, and comely out ſides; not like unto Chriſts Spouſe, all glorious within, but full of rottenneſſe, and corruption.</hi> But as for you, be you both hearers, and doers; alter you the courſe of your lives, breake off your ſins, ſhake off the bands of Sathan, diſſolve the Cloudes of your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, fly wickedneſſe, ſhun evill, doe well, doe good, and aſpire to ſuch perfection in doing the will of your God, as that you may not onely ceaſe from evill, but fill your lives with <hi>good workes;</hi> and thus ſhall you be bleſſed, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> in the very deed; for he that doth the Word, is bleſſed; he is no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger under the Curſe, a Vaſſall of wrath, and a Child of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; but bleſſed with Gods favour and love, and in the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine way to that unſpeakable happineſſe that ſhall hereafter be revealed: But he that heateth the Word, and doth it not,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29387:33"/>deceives himſelfe, cheats and couſens his own ſoule, and is but a forgetfull Foole, a very Childe, and no Man; he dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieth with the Word, as a Babe with a Looking glaſſe, behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it not for any end, but to ſport it ſelfe therewith, never intending any thing about the Face to rectifie it, or to ſet it in order. Saint <hi>John</hi> doth divide the whole world into two ſorts of Perſons; <hi>Qui ex Deo eſt non peccat; Qui peccat ex Diabolo eſt:</hi> The Children of God, and the Children of the Devill; the one hears Gods Word, the other heares it not: He that is of God, heareth Gods Word;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 8.47.</note> 
               <hi>Ye therefore heare it not, becauſe ye are not of God:</hi> And to be hearers of the Word of God, is a great pledge or teſtification that we are the Children of God; eſpecially our hearing of Gods word, being accompanied with theſe foure concurring Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Audire,</hi> to heare the word; <hi>Bleſſed are they that heare the Word of God:</hi> this is the firſt ſtep; and he that doth not put a Foot forward to this, he is not to be accounted a Child of God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, <hi>Audire cum frequentia,</hi> to heare the word fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and often: The Earth that is extraordinary dry, and ſcorched with heat; the drops of water which it receiveth, it turneth into Toads. So he that ſeldome frequents Sermons, it is to be ſcared, they <hi>worke</hi> little good upon him, if not turne to his hurt. For the word of God is the Soules ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance, and being Miniſtred ſlowly, it is no marvaile if the Soule not onely grow leane, but fall into a Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</p>
            <p>The third is, <hi>Audire cum attentione,</hi> to heare diligently, and with attention, freeing the Soule from all worldly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances; for as the Eye cannot joyntly, and at once, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold both Heaven and Earth; ſo the Soule cannot attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at one and the ſame time, behold the things of the world, and of God. <hi>If any Man love the World, the love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abideth not in him.</hi> When a great and principall River is divided into many rivolets, or little ſtreames, ſo much the leſle water will every one of them have: The like ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29387:33"/>with that Heart, which is divided into many cares and deſires; <hi>Fooliſh and noyſime luſts, drowne men in deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perdition,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.9. And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>When thou ſitteſt with a Prince, obſerve what is before thee: And put a Knife to thy throat, if thou beeſt a man given to appetite,</hi> Prov. 23.1.2. A Chriſtian ſitting at the King of Heavens Table, is, the hearing of his Word, this is that board to which wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome inviteth us, where the Bread of wholeſome Doctrine is ſet before us, which ſtrengthneth our hearts; and the wine of Grace, which cheereth and comforteth our Soules; at which Table, whoſoever ſhall come to ſit, muſt conſider with attention that which is ſet before him, caſting out of his minde all other worldly things. Thoſe Miniſters that were employed for the apprehending of our Saviour Chriſt, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Preaching to the People, they hearkned unto him with that earneſt and diligent attention, that they had quite forgot to put in execution, that which was given them in charge by the Phariſees: And being demanded by them, why did ye not bring him along with you? they returned this Anſwer, <hi>Never man ſpake like this man.</hi> The glorious Doctor Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> before that he had unwinded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe out of the error of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> he went on purpoſe to heare Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> but not with any intention to give any credit to his Doctrine, but onely to pleaſe his Eares with the Elegancy of his Phraſe; and being raviſhed with the ſweetneſſe of his expreſſions, had his Heart taken as well as his Eare, his attention ſupplyed the fault of his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; this was that putting of a Knife to the throat. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> goes a little further, and calls Gods word not onely <hi>Cultrum,</hi> but <hi>Gladium,</hi> not a <hi>Knife,</hi> but a <hi>Sword, Take unto thee the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God,</hi> that thy Soule be not diſtracted with the troubleſome buſineſſes of this world, freeing it from all worldly cares and moleſtations.</p>
            <p>The fourth is, <hi>Audire cum conſervatione,</hi> to heare with a retention, and to lay up the Word in our Hearts, to locke it up in the cloſet of our Soules; and ſo, <hi>Bleſſed are they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29387:34"/>that heare the Word of God, and keep it.</hi> The Phyſitian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaires of that Patients Stomacke, that cannot keep its meat, but throwes it up, as ſoon as it receives it. So he that hears a Sermon, ſhould retire himſelfe into his Chamber, and there imprint it in his memory. Many take no pleaſure in Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or care any further for them, then to look upon them, to ſmell at them, and to have them in their Hands while they are ſweet and freſh, and lovely, and then throw them by; but the Bee drawes from them both honey and was: So, many heares Sermons for pleaſure, for delicacy of words, for gravity of Sentences, and for gracefulneſſe in the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; but this is but to make a Noſegay to ſmell at for a while, and preſently to caſt it away; but we muſt heare with retention, we muſt ſeale it up in the coffers of our Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance; <hi>For bleſſed are they that heare the Word of God, and keep it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, <hi>having learnt how to behave our ſelves in the Houſe of the Lord our God, in his Publick Service and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and particularly <hi>how to comport our ſelves in the Hearing of the Word, both to our Comfort, and Profit;</hi> We come now to the greateſt, and the moſt excellent ſervice that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of us, and that is <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is that very Art of Arts that adornes a Chriſtian. And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the holineſſe of the Temple, conſiſted in the Prayers, which then had their force there.</hi> And here you ſee, <hi>That the Aſſembly gathered into the Houſe of the Lord,</hi> (their exerciſe there) is, <hi>Sighing, Sobbing, Praying, Crying; Cry unto the Lord.</hi> And to this, the Angels whet on our diligence; and the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by <hi>Prayer,</hi> permits us familiarly to poure out our hearts before him; for <hi>Prayer</hi> is nothing elſe but an opening of our hearts in the preſence of God, and the beſt remedy we have to releeve our cares, anguiſhes, miſeries, oppreſſions, and troubles, is, to lay them all up in his boſome; <hi>Caſt thy burthen upon the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, and he ſhall nouriſh thee:</hi> And therefore, whenſoever we feele our ſelves deprived o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods benefits towards us, whenſoever we finde a want, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with holding of Gods wonted favour and mercy from us, by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29387:34"/>reaſon of our ſins; whenſoever the height of our ſinnes, brings downe the weight of Gods Judgement upon us, whether it be by Plague, Famine, Warre, or any other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, let us run <hi>to this Houſe,</hi> and importune the God of glory, and compaſſion, for this is the onely buſineſſe of this <hi>Faſt, and of this Solemne Meeting;</hi> which brings us to the laſt Circumſtance in the Method, or Order, <hi>And cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good cauſe had all this People to figh, and weep, and cry continually, for their Land was ruſſeted with a blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Famine: And for us of this Land,<note place="margin">Lamen. <hi>2.1.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>How hath the Lord darkened the Daughter of Zion in his wrath and hath caſt downe the beauty of Iſrael and remembred not his foot-ſtoole in the day of his wrath! He hath cut off in his fierce wrath all the herne of Iſrael; he hath drawne backe his right hand, and a Fire was kindled in</hi> Jacob, <hi>which devoured round about; he hath bent his Bow like an Enemy, his right kand was ſtretched out as an Adverſary; He hath deſpiſed in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of his wrath, the King and the Prieſt.</hi> So that well may we take up a lamentation, ſuch as was not in the dayes of our Fathers; for alas, no lamentation can proportion our affliction, ſo that a Deluge of Teares, is little enough for the Ocean of our miſeries. Let then ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row be our individuall companion, with this we begun, with this let us end; nay, never let us make an end of mourning for the abominations of this Land; and let us all learne that laſt leſſon of our Saviour, to weep for our ſelves, to weep for our ſins. And for this cauſe, I ſhall ſtill leade you on with paces of lamentation to the Houſe of mourning, where we are <hi>to cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will ſtay no longer to look upon the behaviour of this People, <hi>whoſe teares did not onely runne downe like a River Day and Night; but their very Hearts cryed unto the Lord They poured forth their Hearts like Water before the face of the Lord; they lifted up their Hands towards him for the lives of their young Children, that fainted for hunger in the Corners of all their Streets; the ſervices they brought
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29387:35"/>unto the Lord were not onely Prayers, but Teares; they did not onely Pray, but Cry.</hi> And ſince we have ſo ſinned, and have been ſo puniſhed, doth it not now concern us? and is it not now high time for us to betake our ſelves unto this Sanctuary of Prayer? nay, what manner of Prayers ſhould we now ſend up to Heaven? ſurely not ſuch, as moſt what we uſe to make, ſuch cold, and frigid ones, as if they were onely for faſhion ſake, and as if there were an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency in us, whether or no they found acceptation from the Lord; and People that are in the fiery Furnace of affliction, under the torrid Zone of Heauens indignation, to be ſo luke-warme; nay, ſo very cold in their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; what doth this argue, but either deſperation, that their praying is to no purpoſe; or elſe mindleſneſſe under the heavy hand of God? whereas there is no better meanes for the removing of this Hand, then <hi>Prayer:</hi> For what ſin doeth, <hi>Prayer</hi> undoeth, eſpecially <hi>fervent Prayer.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſins of our Nation being ſo great, and loud, as that the cry of them hath brought downe ſuch horrible Vengeance upon us; who can tell whether the cry of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prayer unto God for mercy, may not yet enter into his Eates; For this reaſon, <hi>Let us cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we muſt thus imitate their behaviour in miſery; ſo the next is, their Remedy, which likewiſe mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be ours; <hi>They caſt their burthen upon the Lord,</hi> knowing full well, <hi>that he was able to help them, being the Lord;</hi> and as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as able, <hi>becauſe their God.</hi> In treating of which, the utmoſt of my intent ſhall be, to divide ſuch ſhares of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row among you, as that your very ſoules may be even cut aſunder w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thin you; being indeed, <hi>your onely remedy in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and the onely way to appeaſe your angry God; <hi>for the broken and contrite heart, he will not diſpiſe.</hi> And therefore, let us ſigh, and weep, <hi>and cry unto the</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p>As the cauſe of this Peoples miſery, was <hi>Famine;</hi> ſo their caſe, in regard of any Earthly ſuccour that could be expected, was helpleſſe, and remedileſſe; <hi>For the Heavens were become as Braſſe, and the Earth as Iron unto them,</hi> the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29387:35"/>Lord their God, who comprehends all in his Fiſt, had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from them the bottles of Heaven, and ſtopped the ſpouts of Raine; now being ready to dye with hunger, they mingle their Bread with weeping, ſeeking to relieve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by tears and groans; <hi>And cry unto the Lord.</hi> Hence the Point is this.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obſ.</note>
               <hi>That godly ſorrow, and holy affliction, is the beſt remedy in any ſorrow and affliction, whether it be from Men, from Sathan, or from God himſelfe; whether it be in Body, Eſtate, Name, Mind, or ſoule of a Man; whether it be on parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, or on our Selves, or on our Friends, or thoſe that are about us, or on the whole Land, as on Church, or Common wealth;</hi> This is the moſt ſoveraigne Remedy in all diſtreſſe, and extremity whatſoever; this inward godly griefe, is a ſalve for every ſore, and a playſter for every wound: To Weep, and Cry, and poure out our Hearts before God, is the courſe that this people here took, and that which we muſt take in the like, or any other ealamity: and according to the meaſure of the affliction, and as it is more publick, or private, ſo muſt be the meaſure of our lamentation. To this, there is a promiſe made in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa</hi> 61.1.2.3.</note> That when our Hands cannot help our ſelves, nor our Tongues prevaile with others; yet then we may relieve our ſelves by our Prayers unto God; for in that place the Lord undertaketh, <hi>that Mourners ſhall be comforted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is great cauſe why God ſhould ſo deale with ſuch kind of Perſons. For firſt, He is full of pitty and compaſſion; and therefore the Prophet <hi>Joel,</hi> bids us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>Rent our Hearts, and not our Garments:</hi> that is, bring inward ſorrow, that may cruſh and breake the Heart, and then turne unto the Lord; which if we doe, we ſhall be ſure of reliefe; <hi>becauſe the Lord is mercifull</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and our God is ready to forgive.</hi> When we ſee our Children weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mourning, and conſeſſing their faults, we cannot but have our bowels of compaſſion carning towards them; what ſhall we then thinke of God? He is our Father, we are his Children, and be is farre more mercifull then we can be,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29387:36"/>for he hath no other bowels, then the bowels of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and therefore when we Mourne in an holy manner, certainly he will ariſe, and have mercy upon us; he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſlay, when he ſees our Eyes full of Teares, and our Hearts full of ſorrow, for the ſighs and groanes of his people will not let him have reſt in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This godly mourning muſt needs be a ſpeciall remedy in all manner of afflictions, becauſe it makes our Prayers very forcible; it ſets an edge upon our Petitions, and makes us pray heartily, ſervently, and ſtrongly <hi>When</hi> Jacob <hi>wept in his Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12 4.</note> it was ſo effectuall, <hi>that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayled.</hi> When Gods people joyned together to poure forth buckets full of Teares drawne from the bottome of their Hearts before the Lord,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam</hi> 7.6.</note> they were marvellouſly helped; for the great meaſure of their Teares, made their ſupplication more ſervent. And therefore when our Saviour was about the principall point of his Mediatorſhip: then did he gather ſtrength unto himſelfe by this means, <hi>He did offer up Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with ſtrong crying and tears unto him that was able to ſave him from death,</hi> Heb. 5.7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This godly ſorrow muſt needs be very effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, becauſe it is exceeding forcible againſt ſin; for when ſorrow comes into the Heart, ſin goes out, it will not lodge there, unleſſe it be cockered, and much made of. When every one laments his iniquity, and mourns over Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, whom by his ſinnes he hath pierced, then there is a Fountaine opened to waſh us all from our ſins, that have made a wicked ſeparation betwixt us and our God. And ſeeing then that this godly ſorrow is a means to make God pitty us and to make us call earneſtly upon him, and to expell ſin, which might hinder us from prevayling with him, it muſt needs follow That of all remedies in time of diſtreſſe, this is the beſt and ſureſt.</p>
            <p>Since ſorrow is our onely ſafery, and the beſt and ſureſt remedy in diſtreſſe; Let us a little reflect upon our ſelves and miſeries and apply this ſoveraigne Balme to all our wounds. There are many afflictions abroad at Sea, Ships
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29387:36"/>taken, Merchants ſpoyled, goods ſeized, Marriners impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; many at home, in our Townes, nay, in our owne Families, as loſſes, eroſſes, ſickneſſes, diſeaſes, parting with friends, diſcontents; nay, there are many things amiſſe in our owne Hearts, and here is medicine for every one of our maladies. Let us then get it, and uſe it, and all argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and helps that may continue and increaſe it. Thus the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> when <hi>Jonah</hi> threatned diſtruction againſt their City within <hi>forty dayes;</hi> they humbled, and abaſed themſelves and fell to mourning, and uſed Faſting to help it forward; and to further them to this remorſe and griefe for their great and hainous tranſgreſſions: they had grieved the Lord by their iniquities, and therefore now they would grieve themſelves with contrition for them, and neglect no means to further them in the worke of humiliation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.5, 6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>They Proclaime a Faſt, they put on Sackcloth from the greateſt to the leaſt; they neither eat nor drinke; they cry mightily unto God, and every man turnes from his evill way and from the wickedneſſe that is in their hands: And when God ſaw that they turned from their evill wayes, than God repented of the evill that he ſaid he would doe unto them, and he did it not.</hi> And ſince we of this Nation have ſeen and felt affliction, and juſtly may feare danger to be neer us ſtill; let us betake our ſelves to this mourning: if we refuſe to doe it, and ſhall continue to be hard-hearted; ſuppoſe the devouring, bloud-letting Sword ſhould come againe into our Land; ſuppoſe the Plague like a loaden ſpunge ſhould come fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through our Townes and Countries, ſprinkling poyſon whereſoever ſhe comes; ſuppoſe pale, meager Famine ſhould come, which is the very Engine of deſtruction, and brings terrour to mortalls, death to all things: Are not we likely to he taken away with any of theſe, and to have, not our bodies onely, but our ſoules in danger alſo, and that, of Gods wrath and everlaſting diſpleaſure? Let us therefore ſeek to have our hearts mollified by this excellent meanes, and for this end the better to move us; let us conſider of the bleſſings which God hath been pleaſed plentifully to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29387:37"/>poure downe upon this people, as they did in the day of their humiliation,<note place="margin">Nehem. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> of whom <hi>Nehemiah</hi> makes mention. Let us likewiſe ſeriouſly recount how many mercies we have enjoyed, and how much they have been abuſed; how many afflictions we have felt, and how little we have been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd; how many deliverances we have had, and yet how careleſſe, nay, how rebellious we have been, notwithſtanding them all. Let us weigh with our ſelves, what hurt our ſins have done unto us; how many good things they have turned from us, and how many evills they have pull'd upon us; and above all, let us remember what a huge weight, and multitude of miſeries, they have brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Saviour; namely, debaſement, and humiliation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of the greateſt glory, for the greateſt infamy, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and ſufferings, aſſaults and temptations, the heavy burthen of our guiltineſſe, and the grievous puniſhment due for our deſerts, the rage and violence of moſt malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, and the wrath and diſpleaſure of the moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, torments of Body and terrours of ſoule, and death it ſelfe, a painefull death, a ſhamefull death, and a curſed death. And becauſe commonly ſad ſpectacles call ſorrow before it come; let us look back againe upon that ſevere whip of Gods Juſtice, the late Scourge of theſe three Lands; and imagine you ſee your Children flame before your Eyes, ones Head off, anothers Arme, a third crying unto you, and the little one hanging upon you, and then tell me, if it be not hgh time to weep and mourne with them of <hi>Ziglag,</hi> whoſe foules were grieved, <hi>and they wept, till they could weep no more, every man for his Sons, and for his Daughters,</hi> 1 Sam. 30.4.6. But eſpecially to lament for our ſins of all things elſe moſt hurtfull to man, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining our ſoules, and drawing deſtruction after them, unſheathing Gods Sword, and violently forcing him to his Armory, <hi>to put on the Garments of vengeance,</hi> as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh. And as thus the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tropes of our ſins have hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried downe Gods Judgements upon us, and have cryed to God for vengeance; ſo now, let our miſeries cry unto him
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29387:37"/>for mercy; and let us implore Gods gracious power, and that with an howling lamentation, to ſtay his further threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (and juſtly merited) puniſhments, from any more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing horrour throughout our Nation: And for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, let us weep, and ſob, and ſigh, <hi>and cry mightily unto the Lord our God:</hi> And the more ſorrow, the better for us, for ſuch moyſture will diſſolve the clouds of our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and the more ſhowers of griefe fall from our Eyes and Hearts, the cleerer and fairer will the wayes of our Hearts be for the feet of the Lord to walke in. Let us then ſollow the Apoſtles councell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 4.9</note> 
               <hi>Suffer affliction, ſorrow, and weep:</hi> And if any thing keep us from this mourning, away with it; Let our laughter be turned into mourning, and our joy into heavineſſe; for we cannot caſt downe our ſelves ſo low, but God will raiſe us up againe. Seeing then ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is the onely Antidote and Soveraigne Remedy for all our poyſonous Diſeaſes; let there be weeping, and crying in every Towne, in every Street, in every Houſe, in every Chamber, <hi>Cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But perhaps ſome will ſay, Is Godly griefe a Salve for all So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es a Remedy for all Diſeaſes: Suppoſe Warre, as lately it did, ſhould againe thunder in this Land? Surely, to weep, and lament in the time of Warre, is no ſigne of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; it rather argues that Men are faint-hearted, want cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and fortitude; ſo that this wringing and wayling, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unbeſeeming the perſon of a Man of Valour: let us therefore truſt in God, and be ſtout, and of a good courage, and never mourne for the matter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h it argue want of Courage, to lament for ſinne? It r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther argues want of Faith, not to lament for ſinne. What doe you thinke of <hi>Jacob,</hi> was he a Coward? you cannot ſay ſo of him; for the holy Ghoſt gives him this commendation, <hi>That he had ſtrength and courage not onely to prevayle againſt men, but with the Angel of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> (Gen 32.28.) And his conflict was, <hi>he Wept, and Prayed.</hi> So that that which we thinke weakneſſe, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture calls ſtrength; <hi>For by his ſtrength he had power with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29387:38"/>God,</hi> (Hoſea 12.2.4) What doe you thinke of <hi>David,</hi> was he a Coward? there is none, I thinke, will ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace that worthy and renowned Captaine of the Lord of Hoſts: And yet he himſelfe in his <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> often makes mention of his Teares, and ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>That he watered his couch with his teares: And that his Eyes did guſh out with Rivers of teares.</hi> What will ye ſay to all Gods People, of whom it is ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.11.</note> 
               <hi>That they ſhould mourne as they did for</hi> Joſiah, <hi>in the Valley of Hadadrimmon?</hi> and as one mourneth for his Firſt-borne, the onely Heyre and hope of the Family, Will you condemne all Gods people for a generation of Cowards? nay, this is ſo farre from bewraying any want of Courage, that we may boldly ſay, That when men are fulleſt of ſuch Teares, then are they fulleſt of Fortitude. What ſhall we thinke of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, had he no Heart? was he deſtitute of Courage? that could not poſſibly be: And yet, when he was to exerciſe the fulneſſe of his Power, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſuch a worke, as no creature durſt attempt; when he was to offer up himſelfe to his Father, as a Sacrifice for the fins of the World; when he was to encounter the Lords wrath, and his juſtice; the Devill, Death, Hell, and Damnation, and all the Powers of Darkeneſſe, that ſame time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>he Wept, and that abundantly:</hi> And I hope none will ſay, that then our Saviours ſtrength fayled him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his bitter Tears and Cryes. Surely thoſe that doe not weep when there is cauſe, they are without Heart, and utterly voyd of true Valour, and ſubject to marvellous fears, and violent diſtempers, which ariſe from a baſe mind. For what is the reaſon they are ſo afraid of Death? but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not mourned for their ſinnes, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the ſting of Death, which if they had done, they would then triumph over Death; and ſay with Saint <hi>Paul O Death where is thy ſting?</hi> (1 Cor. 15.55.) their heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would then ſtand faſt, as the ſtrong mountains, and not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> afraid of any evill tidings, <hi>No not of the Peſtilence th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> walketh in the darke; nor of the Plague that deſtroyeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> noon-day,</hi> Pſal. 91.6.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:29387:38"/>
            <p>Againe, Since ſorrow is our onely ſafety. This makes exceedingly for the comfort of thoſe that are Mourners in <hi>Sion;</hi> they are in favour with God, and out of the reach of all danger, ſo that nothing can befall them for hurt. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourne,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for they ſhall be comforted,</hi> Matth. 5.4. More happy is the poor man that weeps for his ſinne, then the greateſt Potentate that rejoyceth in abundance.</p>
            <p>And though we have cauſe enough of ſorrow, if we ſhould flay to looke into the Calendar of theſe dayes, and ſee and find the ſinnes of this Land to be aſpiring ſinnes; to ſee Drinking, Cheating, Whoring, Swearing, as common as Breathing; which though they may be wincked at by the Eyes of Men; yet are they crying in the Eares of God. But to paſſe by theſe, and likewiſe Covetouſneſſe, Oppreſſion, whoſe Houſes filled by cruelty and deceit, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion of the Rich, Wantonneſſe of ſome, and Prophaneſſe of all, enough to ſit every Pious ſoule in Mourning, for the miſeries of <hi>England:</hi> And to look onely upon the woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diviſions amongſt us touching matters of Religion, not medling at all with that remnant of <hi>Baal,</hi> I meane, our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; though me thinks, its ſtrange, that after ſo long Preaching of the Goſpel, there ſhould be ſtill ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of Popery; nor with our hollow hearted bypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erites; nor with the Atheiſts of our times, who neither ſeek the Lord, nor enquire after him. Let us onely look upon our new Apoſtates, and ſee what numberleſſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are carried away from true Religion to Fancies: yet I reckon theſe Separiſts to be ours, however they may be ſomewhat Sun-burnt, Tand, and Tackt with private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (though I hope the cloth is ſound, they yet hold faſt the Foundation;) but runne through the Streets of every Towne, and you ſhall ſcarce meet with two of one Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and yet all would be thought Religions, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Holineſſe; by which meanes, the ſeameleſſe Coat of Chriſt is miſerably rent and torne, and too many (God grant they prove not irreparable) diviſions are in this poor
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29387:39"/>
               <hi>Reuben.</hi> O how ſhould thoughts of theſe things open the very ſluces of ſorrow, and cauſe Teares to trickle downe all cheekes, that the Children ſhould take delight in the Mothers ruine, and Rayes of the glorious Goſpel ſhould ſuffer ſuch diſmall Eclipſes by the ſtrange and unheard of interpoſitions of thoſe that would be deemed the onely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours and lovers of it: For ſurely there can be no greater cauſe of lamentation, then the miſeries and calamities of Gods poor diſtreſſed Church and People. Hence the Point ſhall be this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the greateſt affliction that ſhould touch the Hearts of Gods People, ſhould be the affliction of his Church and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> this of all others goes neereſt the Hearts of the Saints. For this, ſee <hi>Ieremies Lamentation,</hi> for the judgements of God on his Church, and on <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> his owne City, and for the miſery and calamity that lay upon the whole State; ſee them thus bewayling their heavy eaſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.48 49. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Mine Eye caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out Rivers of Water, for the deſtruction of the Daughter of my People: Mine Eye droppeth without ſtay and ceaſeth not; Mine Eye breaketh my Heart, becauſe of all the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of my City.</hi> For when Gods Inheritance was ſpoyled, ſome put to the Sword others led Captive, the Temple of God rized, and the exerciſes of Religion aboliſhed; this was it that wrought upon <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> and made him to grieve, and breake forth into theſe wiſhes, <hi>O that my Head were full of Water, and mine Eyes a Fountaine of Teares, that I might weep Day and Night, for the Slaine of the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my People.</hi> (Ierem. 9.1.) as if he could not have his fill, nor weep enough for the deſolations of <hi>Zion</hi> and the miſerable overthrow thereof, which he fore-ſaw. And this was it that went neer the Heart of good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> who being in great proſperity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehe.</hi> 1 4.</note> 
               <hi>Cup-hearer</hi> to the mightieſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch in the World, and in ſpeciall favour with him; yet for the <hi>affliction and reproach</hi> wherein the Church of God was, he conceived ſuch inward ſorrow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>That be was ſad in the Kings preſerce.</hi> which was a thing, that he muſt, and would have forborne, if poſſibly he could. <hi>Moſes</hi> goes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29387:39"/>He doth not onely Mourne, but is content to lay downe his proſperity, and to expoſe his Eſtate to a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt overthrow ſo that he might help forward the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <hi>of the afflicted Iſraelites, and ſave them from the hands of their Oppreſſours:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 11.24.25.</note> For he knew he could not be in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> if he ſhould joyne with them, whom he ſo cruelly handled; <hi>But he choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the People of God, then to be called the Sonne of</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs <hi>Daughter. Eſther</hi> ſeems to goe ſomewhat beyond him, for ſhe reſolves with her ſelfe (for the cauſe of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who were all appointed to ſlaughter) to adventure her life in going to the King in their behalfe; <hi>I will goe,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>though it be contrary to the Law, and if I periſh, I periſh,</hi> Eſther 4.16. and God bleſſed her boldneſſe with an happy ſucceſſe; ſhe ſaw the deliverance of her People, and the confuſion of her Enemies. But our Lord Jeſus Chriſt goes beyond them all, for when he was in ſupreame excellency, he was ſo affected with the woefull caſe of his Elect, into which they had brought themſelves by their owne rebellions againſt him; that he humbled himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>and tooks on him the forme of a Servant,</hi> and ſubmitted himſelfe to many ſorrowes, diſgraces, and ſufferings; not onely while he lived, but principally at his Death, that ſo he might deliver his People from the wrath to come, and from Eternall Death, which they had deſerved and muſt have otherwiſe endured: But for proofe, enough; if you will have Reaſons, take theſe three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is great Reaſon why the <hi>affliction of the Church, and People of God</hi> ſhould ſo affect us; In regard of the Communion that is betwixt God and them: For they are called the Lords Flocke, his chiefe Treaſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven, his Firſt-borne, yea, the very Apple of his Eye; and therefore being ſo deare unto the Lord, they ſhould be deare unto us; and we ſhould have a tender care over them, and mourne in our hearts for any evill that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls them, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> did, <hi>That the Lords Flocke ſhould goe into Captivity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:29387:40"/>
            <p>Secondly, There is great Reaſon <hi>why the affection of the Church ſhould ſo affect us.</hi> In regard of the Communion that is betwixt them and us; for we are their members, and neerer then bodily members: And ſurely we ſhould have greater care of the whole Church, then of our ſelves, becauſe it more concernes Gods glory; and yet in caring for them, we care for our ſelves too, and in labouring to prevent their afflictions, we prevent our owne, and in weeping for others miſeries, we get Armour of proofe that will keep off miſery from our ſelves. And that there is no danger in thus doing for the ſervants of God, may appeare in <hi>Exodus;</hi> one would have thought that there had been ſome great miſchiefe toward <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> when they muſt fetch out of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſuch a People, from ſuch a King, not onely by Petition, but by command, and threatning, <hi>If he would not let them goe;</hi> one would have imagined that <hi>Pharah,</hi> a proud man, would never have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured this at their hands; and yet, if ye will trace them, though you may find them in perill, yet you ſhall find them of all others the moſt ſafe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is great Reaſon, <hi>why the affliction of the Church ſhould ſo affect us,</hi> and muſt needs ſo worke upon our Hearts, becauſe of the inſultations and triumphs of the wicked againſt them, when they cry out, <hi>Where is now their God?</hi> And this was it which <hi>Moſes</hi> did urge to move God to ſpare his People, when he threatned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them for their Idolatry,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>He intreats God to remember his great name, and to ſpare them, leaſt the</hi> Egyptians <hi>ſhould ſay That he had brought them out maliciouſly to flay them in the Mountaines, and to conſume them from the Earth, or that he was not able to bring them into the Land of</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan. This is it that goe, to the Heart of the Faithfull, when they heare prophane Perſons reviling the Hoſt of the Living God: O theſe are they (ſay they) that ſtand ſo much for the exerciſes of Religion; and for comelineſſe of Order in the Church, doe we not ſee that their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Religion are aboliſht? and that they themſelves,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29387:40"/>ſome out off by the Sword, ſome Exiled, and the moſt of them pittifully pinched with poverty and neceſſity? Theſe, and the like doſpightfull and bitter ſpeeches, doe wound the very Hearts of ſuch as love Gods glory, and deſire the proſperity of his Saints, and ſo cauſe them much to bewayle the tribulation of the Church.</p>
            <p>Seeing that the greateſt Afflictions which ſhould touch the Hearts of Gods People, <hi>is the affliction of the Church.</hi> Firſt, Then all careleſſe Perſons are to be reproved, who, ſo it goe well with themſelves, regard not the Church at all, let it ſinke or ſwim, all is one to them, ſo they may be free from danger, and ſit quiet in their owne Houſes, whatſoever becomes of others, they regard not; <hi>They Drinke Wine in Bowles; but no Man is ſorry for the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of</hi> Joſeph (Amos 6.6.) This was a great fault in the late times of our unhappy Warres, when the Sword devoured, and many Chriſtians were taken away, and ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe on every ſide; yet the moſt of us did Eat, and Drink, and were Merry, as if all things then went well with us: The fault is little amended in theſe dayes; for though we know that many of our Brethren are in Exile, ſome Impriſoned, others in Diſgrace, many in Penury and want, and perhaps men of farre better Parts then our ſelves; yet if we can but ſatiate our ſelves under out owne Vines and Fig-trees, it matters not what becomes of others, never once troubled at other Mens miſeries; but this argues ſtrange inſidelity, and is ſuch a ſinne, as the Lord will purſue even unto Death, if it be not reformed. See the threatning of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, In that day,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>did the Lord God of Hoſts call unto weeping, and Mourning to Baldneſſe, and girding with Sackcloth. But behold Ioy and Gladneſſe, ſlaying Oxen, and killing Sheep, Eating Fleſh, and Drinking Wine; Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for to morrow we ſhall dye. And it was declared in the Eares of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> (but what followes thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?) <hi>ſurely this iniquity ſhall not be purged from you tiſt ye dye, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Iſa. 22.12.13.14. We had
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29387:41"/>need then redreſſe ſuch things as are ſo dangerous to the whole Land.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a greater fault then this; For many doe not onely walke ſecurely in the affliction of their Brethren, but deſire the continuance and increaſe of it, in hope that they ſhall enlarge their Poſſeſſions, and better their Eſtates by other mens harmes; but ſurely thoſe who have but a glimpſe of Chriſtianity in them, would rather wiſh the well-fare of others, then deſire and thirſt to live upon their ſpoyles.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There are a ſort which are worſe then theſe, who come juſtly under this reproofe; and ſuch are they as long for ſtirres, and mutinies, and inſurrections; of this ſort are they, who under any Government of Church or State, Cry, Downe with Magiſtrates, and downe with Preachers. Of this ſort likewiſe are thoſe who cry ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of too much P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enty, as a ſtop to their greedy deſire of Gaine; and of this ſort alſo are they that murmur and repine at the Rich, and multiply ſpeeches of diſcontentment, becauſe Wealth (ſay they) is unequally ſhiſted, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that Tumults may ariſe, that they may get proviſion from ſuch as fall into their Hands; but theſe have bloody Hearts.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There are yet worſe then theſe, who doe not onely wiſh for ſuch troubles on Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth before they come; but rejoyce at them when they are come: and when others Eyes are full of Tears, their Mouthes are full of Laughter. As <hi>Jeremy</hi> chargeth the <hi>Moabites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.26.27.</note> 
               <hi>He magnified himſelfe againſt the Lord:</hi> Moab <hi>ſhall wallow in his vomit, and he alſo ſhall be in deriſion. For diddeſt not thou deride.</hi> Iſrael, <hi>as though be had been found among theeves? for when thou ſpeakeſt of him, thou art mooved</hi> This was there manner of dealing, and this is the property of all ſuch wicked <hi>Moabites,</hi> they cannot ſpeake of the calamities of the Faithfull, but they are wonderfull affected with joy; theſe have cruell hearts, and ſhall be met withall as <hi>Moab</hi> was.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:29387:41"/>
            <p>Fifthly, There are a fort that are ſtill worſe then theſe, who not onely rejoyee at the troubles, but at the fins of thoſe ſhat are religionſly affected; and if they ſlip, through infirmity, and fall into any ſin, they are as glad, as if they had go ten a Kingdome, and came home in triumph.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, There is a ſixth ſort that are worſe then all theſe, one higher degree then any I named yet; which is, When men are ſo ſarre from grieving, that it goes ill with Gods ſervants, that if they be ſomewhat amiſſe, they will make them worſe, and help forward their miſery; and for this end, incenſe and miſ-informe ſuch againſt them, as they know will inflict puniſhments upon them; and all theſe ſeverall ſorts have of late been, and ſtill are, Thornes in our Eyes, and Pricks in our ſides, billowes and brands of Sedition; and few there are but have ſhared in ſome of theſe common calamities. O that all theſe ſeverall ſorts and companies, were become ſtrangers to our Land; but I paſſe them, as fellowes not worth any longer ſaluting.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is an Uſe of Comfort; <hi>For if the afflictions of the Church, of all other afflictions, goe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereſt the Hearts of Gods Children;</hi> Then ſurely this is for great comfort unto them that can mourne for the Calamities of the Church; For this is a notable teſtimony, that they are feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing members, and have in them the life of Chriſtianity, when others troubles are theirs, others loſſes theirs, others reproaches theirs, others ſufferings theirs, and when any diſtreſſes, and ſtraits of others are made theirs. And they that thus lament for <hi>Sion,</hi> ſhall be comforted with <hi>Sion;</hi> God hath promiſed them ſingular conſolation, it is their Portion and they may confidently expect it.</p>
            <p>But it may be demanded, <hi>If Sorrow be our onely ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and beſt Remedy in miſery and trouble; How long muſt we continue our humiliation, our ſorrow, our mourning, our crying?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Anſwer ſhall be this, Never ceaſe mourning, till God ceaſe afflicting; never make an end of crying, till God make an end of puniſhing; never ceaſe Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29387:42"/>till God give Conſolation VVhen the Lord mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth unto us occaſion of Griefe, let us never ceaſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he againe revive our Hearts; we muſt not begin in the Spirit, and end in the Fleſh; but having a good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, we muſt goe on with our worke, and bring it to perfection; and if God give us an heart to mourne, ſet to it, and never give over, till he ſet us free. Hence the Point ſhall he this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That we ſhould never make an end of Mourning and Weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till God make an end of afflicting and ſcourging.</hi> For this, Looke upon <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and ſee him never making an end of Weeping; <hi>Mine Eye</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>droppeth without ſtay, and ceaſeth not, till the Lord looke downe and behold from Heaven. Mine Eye breaketh my heart,</hi> Lam. 3.49 &amp;c. And ſo he exhorteth the People; <hi>Let teares runne downe like a River Day and Night, take thee no reſt, neither let the Apple of thine Eye ceaſe. Ariſe, Cry in the Night, in the beginning of the Watches, poure out thine Heare like Water before the Face of the Lord,</hi> Lam. 2.18.19. But for Proofe, enough.</p>
            <p>If you will have Examples for this continued forrow and mourning, Then firſt take theirs who are mentioned in <hi>Nehemiah, Who Wept at the Hearing of the Law, till they were bid to rejoyce.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 8 9.</note> It was a notable commendation of that People, that they would not leave off, till they had war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to leave off. The next ſhall be <hi>Mordecai,</hi> who when Queene <hi>Eſther</hi> ſent him Garments to Clothe him, and would have his Sackcloth to be taken from him, <hi>he would not receive them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſther</hi> 4.4</note> but humbled himſelfe ſo long, till he was aſſured of deliverance. The third ſhall be <hi>Iacob, Who would never let goe his hold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.26. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>but ſtill wraſtled with the Angel, and continued weeping and praying, till he obtained a bleſſing.</hi> The laſt ſhall be the Weman of <hi>Canaan, who ſtuck ſo cloſe to her buſineſſe and was ſo importunate with Chriſt for her Daughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>15.22.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and would never deſiſt, nor let her Suit fall, till ſhe had prevailed with our Saviour.</hi> I might produce you a cloud of witneſſes; but theſe ſhall ſerve. <gap reason="missing" extent="9 pages">
                  <desc>〈9 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:29387:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:29387:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:29387:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:29387:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29387:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:29387:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:29387:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:29387:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:29387:46"/>worldly helps, the deeper diſtreſſes we be in, the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort they will afford us: ſo in Spirituall helps, the greater extremities we be in, the more comfort will they miniſter unto us; when we are helpleſſe and hopeleſſe, then Faith works wonders, and never ſhewes forth it ſelfe ſo mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and powerfully, as when it workes alone. Wealth, Strength, Friends, and all other outward things, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comforts, (when miſeries lye heavy upon us, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to caſt an Eye to them, expecting ſome reliefe and comfort from them) will but deale with us, as the High Prieſts did with <hi>Judas;</hi> when all went well with him, then they hug'd him, and who but <hi>Judas,</hi> they then made ſhew of all favour and friendſhip towards him; but when in the horrour and anguiſh of his ſoule, he makes his moane unto them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.45.</note> 
               <hi>Crying out, that be had ſinned, betraying Innocent bloud;</hi> they then ſet him packing with a cutting, and uncomfortable anſwer, <hi>What is that to us?</hi> And ſuch cold comfort ſhall we receive from any Earthly props and ſupports whereon we reſt, and ſtay our Hearts; when we have moſt need of them, they will ſtand us leaſt in ſtead: So that we may truely ſay of them, as <hi>Job</hi> did of his Friends, <hi>Miſerable comforters are ye all,</hi> Job 16.2. But as for thoſe that live by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, they are underlayed with better props and ſupporters then the world can afford; for when they have none other to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, they can deliver themſelves by Prayers, by tears, by ſighs, by cryes, and by calling upon Gods name, <hi>out of the loweſt Dungeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if no diſtreſſe, no breaking, no cruſhing can hinder Gods People from Praying and Crying?</hi> Then firſt, This may ſerve to ſhew us the difference betwixt the wicked, and the godly, in times of outward or inward affliction, when they drinke both of the ſame Cup, and are plunged into the ſame miſcries. Caſt a wicked man into a Dungeon, and lay him full low, where he can meet with no worldly help; and what courſe will he <hi>take?</hi> You ſhall ſee, that either he will blaſpheme God, and bite his Tongue for
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:29387:47"/>madneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.15.</note> as they that are ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations;</hi> or, elſe he will grow deſperate, and make away with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as <hi>Judas, Achitophel,</hi> and other monſters have done: But let a godly man be layd as faſt and low in the ſame Dungeon, and he will be full of joy, when the other is full of deſperate griefe, and ſing <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and poure forth many Prayers and mighty Cryes in ſtead of the others im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation; and blaſphemous ſpeeches. Take one example for all, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> had both dealt unfaithfully (though in a farre different degree and manner) with their Lord and Maſter, and were both brought into great perplexity; but <hi>Peter</hi> goes out, confeſſeth his fault, weeps bitterly, and gaines exceedingly by it: <hi>Iudas</hi> on the other ſide, ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth deſperately, and ſpeedily diſpatcheth himſelfe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by doth manifeſtly appeare the different carriage of the Faithfull, and of Inſidels when they are both overbarthened with ſorrowes and miſeries.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Can no diſtreſſe, no cruſhing, nor breaking, hinder Gods People from Praying and Crying?</hi> This is for ſingular comfort unto the Children and ſervants of God, that no croſſe can befall them to hinder their Prayers, or ſtop the paſſage of their cryes from the Eares of the Almighty, but all ſhall quicken and inflame the ſpirit of Prayer in them: ſurely the iſſue of their trouble muſt needs be good, when it is watered with Teares, and ſanctified with requeſts; if they can wait till their harveſt come, ſuch a ſeed-time muſt needs bring them a plentifull and bleſſed crop of comfort. And therefore, if you have the holy Ghoſt in your Soules, and Prayer in your Hearts; if you have Teares in your Eyes, and ſighs in your Breaſts, then bleſſe God for ſo good an inſide, for its your preſent help in trouble, its your meat in Famine, your preſervative in Plague, your ſtrength in Warre, your help in Affliction, and your comfort at all aſſayes; therefore in all diſtreſſe, fly unto God, end in Prayer, <hi>and cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And no wonder if theſe people in the time of Famine, <hi>fly unto God,</hi> in this their woefull, wretched, and miſerable
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29387:47"/>eſtate, when all outward and worldly comforts fayle them, and lay their burthen upon him, becauſe they knew that he was able to feed and help them (though the ciſternes of the world were growne dry) being the Lord; and as willing, as able, being their God. For the majeſty of God is ſo glorious, that it would make them fly from him, and his eſſence is ſo incomprehenſible, that it is a light that none can have acceſſe unto, and an huge Sea, that will drowne ſuch as will adventure to wade into it; but the Knowledge of Gods ſufficiency and power to help, and of his mercy and free favour, whereby he is ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to help, thats it that encourageth them to come before the Lord, and call upon his Name with ſtrong cryes, and earneſt requeſts, with ſighs, and ſobs, and groanes, <hi>and cry unto the</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p>Whence the point is this, <hi>That the knowledge of Gods power and mercy, is the onely cauſe that brings Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods preſence, and makes them call upon him in trouble.</hi> When they are plunged in miſery, in diſtreſſe, then God ſhall be ſure of their cuſtome and company, like theſe people here, who when all their hopes were periſhed, then they run to God, and caſt all upon him, whom they knew was able to bring Water out of the Flint, as well as out of the River; and Bread out of the Clouds, as well as out of the Barne. <hi>Canaan</hi> they knew could not maintain them without Gods bleſſing; and with it, a barren Wilderneſſe could; and therefore to him they fly, and cry, <hi>They cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p>For this, look onely upon <hi>Pſalme</hi> the ninth, and tenth Verſe, where the Prophet ſheweth how they come to ſeek unto God: <hi>They that know thy name will truſt in thee, for thou never fayleſt them that ſeek thee.</hi> How come they to ſeek God? They firſt truſt in God, by the Knowledge of Gods Name; which name is, <hi>the Lord, ſtrong, gracious, and mercifull,</hi> and till men come to know this Name, they can never come to truſt in God, nor to ſeek God, but by the right underſtanding and applying of the Name of God.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29387:48"/>Nothing in diſtreſſe can hinder them from crying unto the Lord, becauſe they <hi>know</hi> that there is no evill; but in his name they may have an Antidote againſt it; no fore, but there they ſhall have a ſalve to cure it; no diſeaſe, but there they ſhall have a remedy to help it; no wound, but there they ſhall have a Playſter to heale it; no ſickneſſe, but there they ſhall have a cordiall to comfort it, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke to recover it; no doubt, but there they ſhall find a refolution for it, nor no good thing, but there they may get a certainty of obtaining it. And therefore to hearten you in all aſſayes, in all diſtreſſes, miſeries, and calamities whatſoever, to <hi>fly to this Name,</hi> which will be like an Oyntment poured forth to fill and delight the hearts of the Faithfull with the odour of it. And though I cannot give you a definition of the Lord your God, yet take that deſcription of the name of God, notably and comfortably ſet downe to my hand in <hi>Exodus,</hi> where you may heare the Lord himſelfe Proclayming his Name in theſe ten ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall properties,<note place="margin">Exod. 34.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord, the Lord, ſtrong, mercifull, and gracious, ſlow to anger, and abundant in goodneſſe and truth, reſerving mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſins, and not making the wicked innocent, viſiting the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Fathers upon the Children, and upon the Childrens Children, unto the third and fourth Generation.</hi> Then what miſery, what trouble, what diſtreſſe, what affliction, what calamity can hind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r us from comming to the Lord upon the Feet of Faith and Prayer, <hi>to cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Are you layd in the low Dungeon of miſery, as <hi>Iona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was, <hi>in the Dungeon of Hell, in the bottome of the Sea, in the belly of the Whale?</hi> Are your Enemies mighty, your ſufferings many, and your oppreſſions and preſſures heavy? <hi>then cry unto the</hi> Lord, <hi>for he is the</hi> Lord, <hi>ſtrong, all power is in him, and from him, and for him: he is the mighty God, and he doth not onely uſe his might for our Salvation, but for our Enemies deſtruction.</hi> If then your troubles be great, and your Enemies mighty? be not diſmayed, your God is greater and mightier to help you out of them, then they
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29387:48"/>are to hold you ſtill in them; and he rides upon the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, full of Majeſty, and full of ability to deliver you, and to ſet you free from the ſtrongeſt bonds <hi>of affliction.</hi> Come but once to know Gods all-ſufficient Power, then no affliction or tryall ſhall make you faint; The leaſt <hi>affliction,</hi> if God ſupport us not in it. will be too ſtrong for us; but the greateſt, nay, the ruſhing in of all at once upon us, if this ſtrong God be on our ſide, ſhall not be able to hurt u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or daunt us; and therefore, when our Hands cannot help us, nor our Tongues prevaile with unreaſonable men, let us fly unto this ſtrong Tower, the Lord our God, <hi>And cry unto the</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And now leaſt any poor <hi>afflicted</hi> ſoule, hearing of Gods Power, ſhould ſay, <hi>I know that God is ſtrong and powerfull, but what is that to me? it may be, he may uſe his power to my overthrow. Nay,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>God is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as well as powerfull:</hi> and therefore why ſhould any be diſcouraged by miſery, ſince miſery is the very object of mercy, and the Eye of Divine pitty is ever fixed upon it? For the God whom we ſerve hath no other riches then the riches of his mercy. And this was the argument that <hi>David</hi> ſo often uſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.2.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Have mercy on me, O Lord, for I am weake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O Lord heale me, for my bones are vexed; my ſoule is alſo ſore troubled; but</hi> Lord <hi>how long wilt thou delay? Returns,</hi> O Lord, <hi>deliver my ſoule, ſave me for thy mercies ſake.</hi> And in an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther <hi>Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.1.</note> Incline thine Eare, O</hi> Lord, <hi>and heare me, for I am poor and needy.</hi> And if we come but crying unto him, our very miſery will be ſufficient to work upon him for mercy: ſo that he will be ready to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine us, like the Father of the Prodigall, with an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde plangis?</hi> why weepeſt thou my Sonne?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> 15.20</note> 
               <hi>I will clothe thee with the beſt Rayment, and put my Gold Ring upon thy finger, and thy Fare ſhall be the daintieſt morſell:</hi> nay, he will <hi>like</hi> that Father of the Prodigall, <hi>ſtand ready to receive us with his armes u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>foulded to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbrace us; with his hands open, to invite us with gifts with his head inclined to afford us the kiſſe of peace, and ſhew forth his love unto us upon every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:29387:49"/>as the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> teſtifieth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4.</note> ſaying, <hi>In thee the Fatherleſſe ſhall find mercy.</hi> Let us then lift up our ſoules, and cry continually in all ſtraits, and troubles to this God of mercy, for the Lord our God is good, and gracious, and mercifull, and of great <hi>kindneſſe</hi> unto all them that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, <hi>Then cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But leaſt that any poor ſoule ſhould be diſheartened, as unworthy to cry for mercy, by reaſon of his owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and ſpots, and ſtaines, and leproſie of ſin; The next, to hearten and encourage him is, <hi>That the Lord, as he is ſtrong and mercifull, ſo he is gracious, that is, loving, and ſhewing mercy without any merit.</hi> Art thou not worthy of mercy? Haſt thou not deſerved the leaſt favour at Gods hand? what of that? God tells thee for thy comfort, <hi>that he is gracious.</hi> The Lord our God is ſo gracious, as that he will not tarry till we deſerve favour, nor till we be worthy of mercy; but even while we are unworthy, will freely ſhew forth his goodneſſe and mercy towards us. How worthy was <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9 1.</note> 
               <hi>when he was even breathing ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> threatning and ſlaughter againſt the Diſciples of the Lord!</hi> And therefore it is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.</note> That he beleeved in him that juſtifieth the ungodly;</hi> noting thereby, that ſinne cannot hinder Gods favour from offenders, but that through Faith they ſhall be juſtified, and made as innocent in Gods account, as if they had never offended at all: Then let us not, when we are in diſtreſſe, be diſcouraged, or diſmayed; by reaſon of the ſouleneſſe of our ſinnes; but let us go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Lord, and come but penitently, and he will ſhew himſelfe gracious, notwithſtanding them all; <hi>Then cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. But ſtill the wounded ſoule perhaps may ſay, <hi>Alas, I have provoked God to wrath, I have incenſed him, and juſtly drawne his heavy hand upon me by my ſins; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though the Lord be gracious, with what comfort or hope can ſuch a ſinfull wretch as I goe to cry to that God I have ſo hainouſly offended?</hi> Haſt thou provoked and offended thy God? yet let not that diſmay nor hinder the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but goe, <hi>cry
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:29387:49"/>unto the</hi> Lord, for he tells thee himſelfe, <hi>That he is ſlow to anger,</hi> that is, long ere he be provoked. Witneſſe the cryes of <hi>Sodome,</hi> which pierced the Eares of the Almighty; yet ſo loath was <hi>God</hi> to ſhowre downe <hi>Fire and Brimſtone;</hi> as that he expoſtulates the matter, as if he had bin jealous of his owne Eares, and anſwers with an <hi>Ego vadam, &amp; videbo; I will goe downe and ſee whether they have done altogether according to the cry that is come unto me.</hi> And thus, as he is hard to be provoked, making as though he ſaw not our ſins, becauſe he would have us to amend; ſo, when he is provoked, he is as eaſie to be appeaſed. And this is ſeen in <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> (a notorious ſinner) in the City of <hi>Iern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> who was grown ſo ſhameleſſe, as that the whole City ſuffered in regard of the bad report that went of her; yet ſhe no ſooner ſtands at his Feet behind him <hi>weeping;</hi> but Chriſt preſently tells <hi>Simon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 7.38.</note> 
               <hi>that many ſins are forgiven her.</hi> For we can no ſooner fall out with our ſins, but <hi>God</hi> falls in with us. An Earthly Father will not take every advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt his Child; and when the Child is grieved that he hath committed a great fault, good Parents are eaſily ſatisfied. The Lord our God pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tieth us, as a Father his Children; and whenſoever we kindle his wrath againſt us, one Teare of true Repentance, will quench all the Flame thereof. And to this <hi>David</hi> giveth ſufficient teſtimony, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> Lord <hi>is ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe, he will not alwayes chide, nor keep his anger for ever.</hi> And this he himſelf found by good experience, for when after many mercies received he had grievouſly provoked the Lord in that matter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and did not repent, but ſtill lay in his ſin; inſomuch, as God was angry with him: <hi>David</hi> no ſooner begins to make confeſſion of his ſin, but God forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with tells him by the Prophet,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>That he had put away his ſin:</hi> ſo that the Lord was more ready to offer him pardon, then he was to aske it. And therefore, ſince the Lord is ſlow to anger, and eaſie to be intreated; let not our ſins (though never ſo many) hinder us from Crying to the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:29387:50"/>
            <p n="5">5. But ſtill ſome poor ſoule perhaps may ſay, <hi>Tis true indeed, I know there is no fault on Gods part, he is ſlow to anger, and eaſie to be intreated; But what am I the better, when I cannot fit my ſelfe to ſeek for mercy as I ought to doe? Alas, I am weake, and full of infirmities, I come farre ſhort every way, I cannot Pray as I ought, my Prayers are few, and cold, and weake; I cannot keep Gods Word, my memory is fraile and ſlippery, &amp;c.</hi> What of all this? let no weakneſſe nor infirmities diſmay thee, for the Lord himſelfe tells thee in the next place, <hi>that he is abundant in goodneſſe,</hi> or <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in kindneſſe;</hi> and it is the property of <hi>kindneſſe</hi> to take ſmall things in good worth, and to paſſe by infirmities and weakneſſe, and to be eaſie to be intreated; <hi>he will not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax;</hi> if we can but once come to be humble in heart, though we cannot attaine to that meaſure of ſanctification, as others have; nor poure out our Soules in Prayer as we ſhould: yet God will take all in good part; he that will reward a Cup of cold Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he will reward a cold Prayer, for God looks not for perfection from poor weak creatures, that are full of imperfection; And therefore ſince he is abundant in kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, let not our infirmities and weakneſſe hinder us from <hi>crying unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. But the poor <hi>afflicted</hi> ſoule may perhaps ſtill ſay, <hi>Though the Lord be abundant in goodneſſe and kindneſſe; yet how ſhall I know that this goodneſſe and kindneſſe of God ſhall be performed unto me; for I have Prayed, and Cryed and waited long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd yet am never the neerer: ſo that though he be good, and yet not good to me; kind, and yet not kind to me, what am I the better?</hi> Haſt thou Prayed; and Cryed, and wayted and hath not God ſeemed to regard, nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thy requeſts, in releeving thy wants, eaſing thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, removing thy preſſures? &amp;c. yet Cry ſtill, and in the Lords due time thou ſhalt be ſure of reliefe; for he never promiſeth, but he performeth, if we perſevere with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fainting; And ſo he himſelfe tells thee in the next place, <hi>that he is abundant in truth;</hi> As he never threatens
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:29387:50"/>any thing, but he executes it; ſo he never promiſeth any thing, but he performes it. You may beleeve him without an Oath: <hi>But I have ſworne by my holineſſe,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>that I will not forſake</hi> David; And never any yet could charge him with breach of promiſe; hath he promiſed, and ſhall he not performe? Then cheare up your hearts, and pluck up your ſpirits, your God hath promiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10.</note> 
               <hi>that thoſe that feare him, ſhall want nothing that is good.</hi> Againe, he hath promiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15.</note> That <hi>if we call upon him in the day of trouble, he will not onely heare, but deliver.</hi> And who ever did ſo, and found not according to his expectation? Then why ſhould not we reſt upon his promiſe? hath the Mouth of the Lord ſpoken it and ſhall he not doe it? for take away his Truth, and take away his God head. What then? though in theſe hard times, our money is gone our goods gone, our lands and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions gone, our liberty gone, our Friends gone, and all our outward ſlayes be gone: But is Gods truth gone? Hath he not promiſed to provide for us when we are poor, as well as when we are rich; when we are in ſickneſſe, as well as when we are in health? Hath not he ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>I will not leave thee, nor forſake thee?</hi> Did not he provide for us in our Infancy? and ſhall we not truſt him in our Age? Let every man in all trouble and diſtreſſe, confidently, and humbly ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> Lord <hi>is my helper, I will not feare what Man can doe unto me.</hi> We have his promiſe to heare, and help, and not to leave and forſake; but to deliver, when we call upon him: And ſince his promiſe is paſſed, he will performe it; <hi>for he is abundant in truth.</hi> And therefore, <hi>let us cry unto the</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But the poor ſin burthened ſoule, may perhaps ſtill ſay, <hi>What though the</hi> Lord <hi>be abundant in truth, and never promiſeth, but doth performe? Whats all this to me, whoſe ſoule muſt needs be loathſome unto him, being all ſpotted with ſin, wallowing in the puddle of iniquity, and that with conſent, and delight to?</hi> For this, goe look upon <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 7.</note> and others, whoſe ſoules thou ſhalt find as filthy and loathſome as thine; but when once they fell to bathe, and waſh them
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:29387:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the River of Repentance, and to ſwell and rinſe them in a <hi>Iordan</hi> of ſorrow; then ſee how <hi>God</hi> dealt with them, and be not diſmayed, though thy ſins be of the deepeſt tincture, for there is mercy in ſtore for thee: And ſo he himſelfe tells thee in the next place, <hi>That he is a God reſerving mercy for thouſands;</hi> giving us to underſtand thereby, that he hath Flouds of mercy for all that ſtand in need of it. Never went any to God for mercy, but he found mercy, if he ſought in Faith, as God bids him; for he hath mercy in ſtore for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. With Earthly Kings, he that coms not firſt, ſpeeds worſt: but it is not ſo with the King of Heaven, he hath ſufficient for thoſe that come to him laſt, as well as for thoſe that come to him firſt; his Fountain is never dry, the well-ſpring of his mercy continually Flowes, he can comfort thouſands, as well as one perſon, and yet his ſtore not be leſſened one whit. Surely there are many thouſands in Heaven, that were once as bad as we are; and yet now they are in a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of reſt; they are now gone from miſery, to mercy; from a wretched life, to a far better being, and quite out of the reach of all ſin, and ſorrow. Then who would not come to ſuch a Phyſitian as hath wrought ſo perfect a cure upon ſo many, and that of free coſt, and never ſuffered any one to miſcarry that was willing to be his Patient? Men did lye at the Poole of <hi>Betheſda</hi> many Yeares, expecting to be healed; we need not lye ſo long at the gates of Heaven for the outing of our ſoules; but we are ſure to be perfectly helped, when we are truely humbled, and fitted for help. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let not our ſins diſcourage us, ſeeing there is mercy in ſtore, our God being a God <hi>reſerving mercy for thouſands,</hi> nor hinder us from comming to that God of mercy, whoſe mercy knows no limits, <hi>And cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. But ſtill the poor <hi>afflicted ſoule</hi> over-laden with ſin, perhaps may ſay, <hi>I know that God is a God of mercy, and hath mercy in ſtore for thouſands; But alas, my ſins ſinke me, my miſeries doe not ſo much trouble me, as my ſins, which are many and grievous, and ſins of the largeſt magnitude, and of long continuance: With what face then, or hopes, dare I
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:29387:51"/>come, and cry unto the</hi> Lord? For that, courage Chriſtian, thou whoſe ſoule is thus wounded with ſin; for hadſt thou all the ſins and ſores that might be, thou needeſt not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned from comming unto the Lord, ſeeing he himſelfe tells thee in the next place, <hi>that he is a God forgiving iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tranſgreſſion, and ſin;</hi> and if he ſhould not ſhew himſelfe to be ſuch a God towards the militant Church, he ſhould loſe both his name, and his people at once; but he pardons all theſe kinds of ſin, he pardons iniquity, that is, originall ſin, and the perverſneſſe of our nature, that cleaves ſo faſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; he pardons tranſgreſſion, that is, ſins of rebellion and preſumption; and he pardons ſin, that is, ſins of cuſtome, and ſuch as are grown to an habit; and if any one be weary of this burthen, God will give him a ſpeedy diſpatch, <hi>the heavy laden,</hi> if they come unto him, <hi>le will eaſe them.</hi> And this a man may boldly claime at Gods hand, and intreat him to be God, for that he could not be, unleſſe he ſhould performe this for us: And therefore, though nothing trouble thee ſo much as thy ſins, and though they be never ſo many, great, and grievous, and of long continuance; nay, though thou wert more leprous then <hi>Gehezi,</hi> more uncleane then <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue,</hi> and more blind in ſoule then ever <hi>Bartimcus</hi> was in body; yet courage ſinner, and remember that thy God, <hi>is a God forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin,</hi> and therefore down on thy Knees, and ſall to thy Prayers, <hi>And cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. But for all this that hath been ſaid of Gods goodneſſe towards his choſen; the poor <hi>afflicted ſoule</hi> may perhaps ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (as unbeliefe is full of objections) and ſay, <hi>Alas, we ſee how wicked men proſper, hold up their heads, and flouriſh in the world; they have their Barues full, and Cubbords full, and Cheſts full, and all things goe with them according to their hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: whereas Gods Children ſinke, and are trampled under foot, the Righteous are wrouged, and the Church over-run by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly of the World?</hi> Nay, ſaith God, in the next place, let not that trouble nor diſhearten thee, <hi>For I am a God that holds not the wicked innocent;</hi> let them take their ſwing, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:29387:52"/>make havock for a time, God may ſpare them long, yet will viſit them at the laſt;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>For God is jealous, and the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeth,</hi> even the Lord of anger; <hi>the Lord will take vengeance on his adverſaries, and he reſerveth wrath for his enemies: The Lord is ſlow to anger, but he is great in power, and will not ſurely cleare the wicked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.12.</note> And as <hi>Habakkuk</hi> ſaith, <hi>He hath ordained them for judgement, and eſtabliſhed them for correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Whereas thoſe that are his, he corrects but for a time; but his anger never aſſwageth towards the reprobate, though for a long time he deferre. And therefore grudge not to ſee the wicked flouriſh <hi>like a green Bay-tree,</hi> for a time; paſſe but by a little and upon your return, <hi>his place will not be found,</hi> for God holds not the wicked innocent. But for you, though you be afflicted here, you ſhall be comforted hereafter; for, <hi>through many afflictions we muſt enter into the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> This is the Kings high-way to happineſſe and there is not a Saint in Heaven, but hath led this way, and beaten this path before us; For Stones cannot be ſquared for Pallace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, without the ſtroke of the Hammar; and we muſt be content to endure the ſtroaks of Gods Hammar of afflictions, that we may be poliſhed, and ſquared, and made lively Stones fit to be layd in the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> What matters it then, to ſee <hi>Dives</hi> here <hi>flant it in Purple, and fare deliciouſly every day</hi> when at laſt, <hi>he muſt be tormented in flames;</hi> while <hi>hunger-ſtarved</hi> Lazarus, <hi>though afflicted here, yet his comfort is hereafter, and is tranſported from the Porch of a Tyrant, to the Boſome of</hi> Abraham. Beſides, though God uſeth many wayes to bring us home unto him, yet none more then <hi>afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> It was <hi>Hunger</hi> that drove the Prodigall home to his Father; And ſurely nothing ſo opens the Eyes of the ſoule, as miſery and trouble. O how correction opens thoſe Eyes, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity kept ſhut! O how often doth the paining of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, work the ſaving of the Soule! O how often doe miſſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes like the Rungs in <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, ſerve to mount out ſoules up to Heaven! Let God then wound us, ſo he will but heale us; let him ſtrik our Bodies with ſickneſſe, with ſores, with reſtraint, ſo he will but with theſe wounds heale out
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:29387:52"/>Soules. Let come what will come ſo it but chaſe us to God, drive us home to his Houſe, end in Prayer, and make us cry unto the Lord.</p>
            <p n="10">10. But ſtill the <hi>afflicted ſoule</hi> goeth on, and ſayeth, <hi>Though God tell us that he holds not the wicked iunocent, and will not ſurely cleare them, but ordains them for judgement, and reſerves them for correction; yet we dayly ſee, that they doe not onely flouriſh here in this world, but goe to their graves in peace, and are not (to any outward appearance) in trouble like other men.</hi> Well, ſaith God, in the tenth, or laſt place, Say they doe, yet will I meet with them in their Children, and puniſh their ſins in their poſterity, <hi>Viſiting the iniquities of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the Children, and upon their Childrens Children, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third and fourth Generation;</hi> they ſhall be ſure to taſt of the bitter Cup of Gods wrath here, as their Fathers doe in Hell. Thus, if this name of God, in theſe ten ſeverall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, were but rightly underſtood and applyed, were it but as oyntment poured out and ſpread upon our hearts, there is nothing in diſtreſſe, nothing in trouble, nothing in miſery could hinder us from crying to the Lord, conſidering he is ſtrong mereifull, gracious, abundant in goodneſſe and truth, and forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion, and ſin, &amp;c. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further enlargement, upon theſe proparties, in their ſeverall particulars, I will onely clap them altogether, and make Application, and ſo haſten you again to the Houſe of Mourning, <hi>to cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is the Lord thus ſtrong, and mercifull, and gracious? &amp;c. then why ſhould a Chriſtian trouble himſelfe at any thing that befals him here? Hath he crafty enemies? let him goe cry to the Lord for direction, his wiſedome is infinitely beyond their policy. Hath he ſtrong enemies? let him goe cry to the Lord, he is mightier and ſtronger then they all. In a word, hath he any outward <hi>affliction,</hi> or inward <hi>corruption</hi> that doth annoy or trouble him? let him goe cry to the Lord, and have recourſe to his God and there he ſhall find remedy for all; nay, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever mans eaſe be, if he hut ſeek the Lord, he ſhall have help.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.18.19.</note> So ſayes that Princely Prophet. <hi>God is neer to all that call upon
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:29387:53"/>him, yea, to all that call upon him in truth. He will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him; he alſo will heare their cry, and will ſave them.</hi> And though their hearts be ſo oppreſſed, that they can utter no words, thats no matter. God will have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their very deſires; and ſurely their teares ſpeak high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and their ſighs cry loudeſt in the Ears of God. Let us then groane for a broken heart, and ſigh, and fob, and weep, and cry, <hi>Cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having done with this peoples behaviour <hi>in the time of Famine;</hi> and likewiſe with the <hi>Remedy they uſed, they eaſt their burthen upon the Lord:</hi> as alſo with the <hi>Motives</hi> inducing them thereunto, <hi>becauſe he is able, being the Lord, and willing becauſe their God.</hi> Let us now cloſe up all in our mourning garments, and robing our ſoules with the inward ſackcloth of ſorrow, not onely Pray, but Weep; nor Weep alone, but Cry, <hi>Cry unto the Lord.</hi> From whence the Point is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They who would not have God to ſhut his eares againſt their Prayers, muſt be ſure that they not onely Pray, but Cry; and that their Petitions proceed from a broken heart, and an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit.</hi> For till the heart be even pulled in pieces by godly ſorrow, and rent in ſunder with godly griefe, ſin and luſt will not out, and then there can be no acceptance looked for from God, either of us, or of our ſervices. The <hi>ſacrifice of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17.</note> 
               <hi>is a ſorrowfull ſpirit, a broken, and a contrite heart, O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.35</note> And therefore did Chriſt <hi>groane in his Spirit,</hi> when he Prayed for that poor man in the Goſpel. So did <hi>Hannah,</hi> ſigh and weep ſore,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>and poured out her ſoule before God.</hi> And there is good reaſon to move us to labour thus to be inwardly touched; for till we have a ſenſe and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our wants, we may well ſpeak, but we can never Pray; till the heart be pained with ſin, its impoſſible it ſhould be fervent for the pardon of it. He that hath no feeling of poverty, cannot earneſtly intreat for a ſupply of his neceſſities. He that hath no feeling of his ſickneſſe, can never be an inſtant ſuiter for the means of health. So he that hath no feeling of his ſpirituall poverty, can never covetouſly hunt after thoſe true treaſures, which onely enrich his ſoule to all eternity
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:29387:53"/>And he that hath no ſenſe of his ſin-ſick ſoule, can never ſeek to that true Phyſitian, who onely can apply Phyſicke to his bleeding heart, and ſin-ſick burthened ſoule.</p>
            <p>This ſerves for the reproofe of thoſe, that come with drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie verball Prayers, thoſe that come with words of courſe to intreat God to pardon their ſins, and ſtrengthen their Faith; but never poure out their ſoules before God, but onely ſpend a little breath, and they ſpeed accordingly; for their cold Prayers, bring but cold ſucceſſe: And this is true, not onely of the wicked, but even of the godly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.3.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>David roared and cryed,</hi> but was never the better, <hi>till he confeſſed his ſin, and was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly grieved for the ſame;</hi> and then, both ſin and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were removed at once. Therefore let us ſtrive with the Lord in our Prayers, and Supplications, labouring for this fighing and crying, this inward ſorrow which is ſo needfull; that doing as this people did in the time of Famine, we may ſpeed, as they did, in this time of our calamity. <hi>For thus ſaith he that is high and excellent, he that inhabiteth eternity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe name is, the Holy one; I dwell with him that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to give life to them that are of a contrite heart.</hi> And the longer we wayt and cry, the greater meaſure of comfort we ſhall have, and the longer it ſhall tarry with us: And therefore, ſince ſervency in Prayer is ſo requiſite, let us not onely Pray, but Cry, <hi>Cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for our comforts, we ſhall find God as ready to heare, as we are to cry; and if we ſend up our Petitions unto him, with ſighs and groans, he will ſend down ſpeedy, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table help unto us, and we ſhall be ſure of good ſucceſſe, even above that we can ask or think: As it is in the <hi>Lamentations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lamt. <hi>3.5.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt heard my Voyce, thou dreweſt neer in the day that I called upon thee.</hi> Whether we deſire the ſuppreſſion of our enemies, or ſubduing of our own corruptions, or whatſoever elſe, we ſhall be ſure to ſpeed well; God will draw neer unto us by his mercifull preſence, and with gracious deliverance, if we draw neer unto him in our miſeries and afflictions. So ſaith our Saviour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever asketh, receiveth; and he that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29387:54"/>ſeeketh, findeth; and to him that knocketh, it ſhall be opened.</hi> Let us then <hi>knocke</hi> at Gods preſence Chamber-doore, and though we be never ſo mean, never ſo contemptible, we ſhall have no repulſe; <hi>For he will fulfill the deſires of thoſe that feare him, he will alſo heare their cry:</hi> their ſins, though never ſo many in number, or groſſe in nature, cannot hinder Gods favour: Witneſſe the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who lived many years without the true God:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>yet whoſoever returned in his miſery, and ſought God, he was found of him.</hi> Another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Gods goodneſſe in this regard, we have in <hi>Jonah,</hi> who though, for his Rebellion, <hi>he was caſt into the Sea; yet God heard him out of the belly of the fiſh, and ſet him upon the dry land again.</hi> A third ſhall be that notorious Theefe, who had ſpent all his life in the Devils ſervice; yet no ſooner cryes, Lord <hi>remember me;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42.43.</note> but Chriſt, (not once caſting him in the teeth with his ſins) gives him this good, and quick, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable diſpatch. <hi>To day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> The laſt for this, ſhall be <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> who had been a moſt wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and miſerable ſinner;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.</note> yet, <hi>When he cryed to the</hi> Lord <hi>in his diſtreſſe, he heard him, ſet him free, and reſtored him to his Kingdome.</hi> Here then is comfort for every diſtreſſed ſoule, let us but call upon the name of our God, and then help and comfort is at hand; <hi>for God is neer to all that call upon him in truth,</hi> though it be not with ſuch ſtrength of Faith as we ſhould; yet if we ſeek him, he will be found of us, and he limits us not to time, conditions, or things; but we may look for help at all times, in all ſtraits, and in all things; and when we have moſt need, then we ſhall be ſure of the beſt help: But now, if we would be certain of this comſort, we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe three Rules.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 11.14.</note>Firſt, We muſt put all wickedneſſe out of our hearts, and out of our hands; we muſt humble our ſelves, and turn from our wicked wayes; we muſt remove our ſins, and then God will remove our croſſes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 4.8</note> So Saint <hi>James</hi> exhorts, <hi>Purge your hands ye ſinners, and purifie your hearts ye double minded:</hi> And this is it we muſt doe, if we will have God to draw neer unto us: for God will not dwell in an heart defiled with ſin, he will
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:29387:54"/>turn both eyes and ears from us, if we continue in our evill wayes; becauſe that when our Tongues cry for mercy, then our Sins cry for vengeance: and though we cannot come to him without iniquity, yet we may come to him without the love and liking of iniquity, we may come with ſhame and ſorrow for our iniquity, and then our ſins neither hinder our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor ſtop, or keep back Gods favour from us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We muſt ſeek God according to all his means, as we find in the <hi>Canticles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1.2. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Who when the Church had loſt Chriſt,</hi> that is, the feeling of his love, and the ſenſe of that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which formerly ſhe had with him; ſhe then uſeth all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and publick means, and at length commeth to conſerence with Gods ſervants (which few will doe, till they be driven to it of neceſſity) and then having wayted a while, <hi>ſhe finds him whom her ſoule loveth.</hi> The ſame muſt be our practice; if one medicine will not ſerve the turn, uſe another; Pray, Faſt, Meditate, Confer, and then at laſt the Lord will be found in mercy; but as we are ſlack in uſing any of the means, ſo ſhall we fayle in our comfortable expectation of favour from God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We muſt uſe the means diligently, and in good earneſt; for if we have a baſe account of Gods mercies, its juſt that we ſhould goe without them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James.</hi> 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>The Prayer of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous avayleth much;</hi> but upon this condition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.12.</note> 
               <hi>if it be fervent. God delivereth the poor when he cryeth;</hi> but if they would have hearing, there muſt be crying. God poures forth Floods of grace, but upon whom? The Prophet tells us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 44.3.</note> 
               <hi>Onely on the thirſty ground. God filleth the hungry with good things;</hi> but they muſt be hungry; they muſt be ſuch as feel themſelves pincht and ſtarved with ſpirituall famine.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.53.</note> Chriſt <hi>was ſent to Preach the acceptable yeare,</hi> but not to the mighty and States of the world. To whom then? even to <hi>Priſoners, and Captives,</hi> that is, to ſuch as could grieve and mourn for their Captivity. Hence is it, that a number reade, and heare, and pray, and yet prevaile not; becauſe they doe it ſo drowſily, and careleſly, the Lord deſers to help them, becauſe they are not fit for help; becauſe they doe not ſtrive and wraſtle in their Prayers. Let us therefore uſe all the means with conſtancy and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:29387:55"/>and then we ſhall obtain our hearts deſire, even above that we can ask or think; for if we would not have God to ſhut his ears to our Prayers, we muſt not onely Pray, but Cry. Let us then (having firſt waſhed our hearts and hands from unrepented ſins) goe unto the Lord, and cry unto him to give us the aſſurance of eternall life, and the joy of the holy Ghoſt, and then come life or death, it matters not much; for though our name, and liberty, and riches, and all, be taken away from us, yet we ſhall be ſetled in the aſſurance of an happy iſſue out of all our ſtraits and difficulties, for the Lord our God will maintain our cauſe againſt all thoſe that ſtrive with us, and will ſtand on our part, and fight againſt thoſe that fight againſt us; according to that of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, He watcheth over them night and day and waters them every moment; and he will contend with them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.3.</note> 
               <hi>that contend againſt his people;</hi> and ſo ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther free them from their oppreſſions and miſeries; or elſe, (which is beſt of all) take them to himſelfe; where they ſhall be ſure to have joy without ſadneſſe, pleaſure without paine, wealth without want, health without ſickneſſe, life without death, and a Kingdom without a change. The conſideration whereof, me thinks, ſhould ſtrike terrour into the hearts of thoſe that are injurious unto the ſervants of God: they may be bold where the hedge is low; every Dwarfe will adventure to leape over there; but let them know, that God is a wall of fire about thoſe that are his, and he will maintain the right of his children; and therfore it muſt needs at laſt goe ill with ſuch, as liſt up themſelves againſt them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.58</note> 
               <hi>O Lord thou haſt maintained the cauſe of my ſoule;</hi> there is our ſtay: Let us be ſure we have a good cauſe, and lay it before Gods judgement ſeat; and then, though we be overborne, God will not be overborne, but he will ſtand on our ſide even he that loves goodneſſe, and hates wickedneſſe, and will be avenged on thoſe that bend themſelves and their endeavours to doe miſchiefe unto his people.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.59</note> Again, all our wrongs are known unto God; <hi>O Lord thou haſt ſeen my wrong;</hi> nothing is done, ſpoken or imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt any of Gods Children, but God takes knowledge of it; there is not one practice, ſlander, or deviſe of cruell
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:29387:55"/>wolves againſt the ſheep of Chriſt; but God ſees it, and markes it, and it belongs unto him to judge the cauſe of his ſervants,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20.12.</note> 
               <hi>and to reward every one according to their works;</hi> He muſt and will give them full pay, and for that end keeps all upon juſt and due record; ſo that as the works of the righteous ſhall ſtand for them, ſo ſhall the works of the wicked he written in great Capitall Letters againſt them, that all the world may take notice of them at the laſt day. How may we then cheare up our hearts in all diſtreſſe? for howſoever our Adverſaries be buſie and watchfull to plot and procure our hurt; yet they cannot be ſo vigilent for our hurt, as God is watchfull for our good; and therefore we may be ſure to have an happy iſſue out of all our troubles if ſo be we can but make our moan to God, and wait patiently for his mercy. And though God knows our griefes and oppreſſions before hand, and purpoſeth to deſtroy our enemies; yet would he have us to prefer our Bill of complaint, and goe on in our ſuite againſt them, <hi>and ſtill cry unto the Lord.</hi> Neither is this to be reſtrained onely to corporall adverſaries, but it holds much more ſtrongly for ſpirituall enemies. Say a man be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with ſin and Sathan, who play the Tyrants over him, his ſoule being even ſcorched with the flames of Hell; let him but bemoane his Caſe before the Lord, and it will be a marvellovs eaſe unto him: Therefore in all ſuch extremities likewiſe, let God be our refuge and Tower-Royall, let us caſt all our cares and ſorrows upon him, who is both able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to beare them, and in due ſeaſon will both free us from them, and in the end make us gainers by them, if we <hi>cry unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To come to the cloſe. In the firſt of the <hi>Chronicles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.9.10.</note> Jabez <hi>the ſon of</hi> Aſhur, <hi>is ſaid to be more honourable then all his brethren;</hi> the reaſon is, becauſe his Mother <hi>bare him in ſorrow,</hi> and his name is a name of ſorrow; and it is there ſaid, That <hi>Jabez called upon the God of Iſrael to be delivered from evill,</hi> and the Lord (ſaith the Text) <hi>heard him, and granted the thing that he asked.</hi> And is the Lord ſo ready to hear, and willing to grant? how then comes it to paſſe, that we who have been ſo
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:29387:56"/>ſeverely ſcourged with the whip of Gods indignation, after all theſe years of ſufferings, of puniſhments, and of diviſions amongſt us, the hand of the Lord ſhould be ſtretched out ſtill? for though, thanks be to God, we are no way diſquieted with any ſound of war, nor alarmes to Battell in our Nation; yet, the reformation of Religion, which was one main thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended at the beginning of our unhappy differences, and as hopefully expected, and prayed, and ſought for, hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſo eclipſed, as that whereas before there were different opinions amongſt us, (as indeed there was never Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the wrinkles of diviſion) ſo now men are grown to ſuch variety of conceits about Gods ſervice, as that we have almoſt as many religions as men; inſomuch, that we who ſhould have all one God to our Father, all one Church to our Mother all one Chriſt Jeſus to our elder Brother, are ſo far from unity, amity; and unanimity amongſt our ſelves, in reſpect of theſe woefull diviſions, as that opinions muſt either be ſuffered to take wall of Scripture, and ſubſtance give way to circumſtance, which God ſorbid; or elſe, as branches, we cannot grow together; nor, as members, agree together; nor, as brethren, love and live together; nor, as Chriſts Sheep, Feed and Fold together. And what is the reaſon that after all this while we are not yet helped, but Religion, in ſtead of being reformed, muſt ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive new and more wounds then before? Surely the cauſe is this, Becauſe we have not ſo mourned as we ought in theſe our common calamities, for the ſins of the times and for the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Land; becauſe we have not ſighed and groaned heartily for the ſins that cleave to our ſoules; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God would have been as ready to heare, as we to cry; for good ſuiters are alwayes good ſpeeders: but it ſeems we have howled upon our Beds, as the Lord himſelfe complains in <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.14.</note> And though theſe rents in our Church be ſufficient of themſelves to open the floud-gates of ſorrow, and clothe all our dejected ſoules with the garments of heavineſſe, and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of mourning; yet there are other miſeries and troubles, (though not fit to ſtand in competition with theſe) that lye ſo
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29387:56"/>ſadly upon us, as might well fill our eyes with tears, our breaſts with ſighs. To name them were ſuperfluous; what eare heart not of troubles, and loſſes, and croſſes on Land, and on Sea, at home, and abroad? and where is any mourning <hi>for the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of</hi> Joſeph? where are our tears that ſhould cry aloud, and pierce the ears of the Almighty? ſurely we have not ſo mourned as we ought to have done. It is a Prodigy to ſee Fountains dryed up in Winter, but far more prodigious muſt it needs be, to ſee our eyes, hearts, breaſts, and all, dry, in theſe ſo many winters of our common miſeries, and theſe long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſtormes of our afflictions. I know there is few or none of us, but will ſigh at the loſſe of his goods by enemies, at the parting with his eſtate, at the Impriſoning of his Perſon, at the baniſhing of himſelfe and friends from their native homes, there is none of theſe but ſeems to take away the very life of our ſoules from us; and yet few of us ſigh for our own, or other mens ſins, the cauſe of all our woe. But ſurely all cauſes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then effects, are to be lamented; ſin is the cauſe, loſſe, but the effect: And though tis true, that reaſon doth informe, and affection doth inforce a kind of lamentation, weeping, and mourning for the loſſe of goods, liberty, or friends, &amp;c. yet grace doth commend, and God doth command another fighing, ſobbing, crying, both for our own, and nationall ſins; for nature doth teach us to weep for naturall cauſes; but grace for ſpirituall: and if the leaſt of our boſome ſins be fire in the hand, and a ſerpent in the heart; how much more then are common ſins to be lamented, being the unfruitfull thornes that choke the good ſeed of vertue and grace? And yet it is to be feared, if inquiry were made, that many would be ſound in this great and ſtill continued miſery, whoſe mouthes, in ſtead of prayers and cryes, belch and breath out nothing but the unſavoury ſpeeches of the ſoule, corrupting not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany onely, but the very Ayre in which they breathe; whoſe eyes, in ſtead of tears, are the open windows to let in whole loads of ſin into their minds; whoſe ears, in ſtead of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and conveying the good Word of God to their ſoules, are the doores of their own deſtruction; whoſe breaſts, in ſtead
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:29387:57"/>of ſighs, are the very ſtore-houſe of corruption; nay, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition made, it is to be feared, that many of us would be found in theſe our publick maladies (though the times have long called to mourning) ſcarce to have layd aſide our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſins, not parting with our ordinary impieties in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary judgements. Good <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> refuſed to take his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt eaſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.11.</note> 
               <hi>while the Arke, and Iſrael, and Iudah abode in tents.</hi> I pray God none of us have preſumed to take unhoneſt cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſince our miſeries have bin ſo great, our plagues ſo mighty, Gods judgements ſo weighty, and our danger ſo eminent. Let then all of us ſhew our ſelves by an holy mourning, that we are ſo far from participating in ſuch mens ſins, and in the wickedneſſe of the world, as that in conſideration hereof we may be found not onely ſighing, but weeping, and bemoan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the increaſe of iniquity, and deploring the ſins of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And no doubt but many might be found amongſt us, who ſometimes ſend out a naturall ſigh or ſob, in regard of ſome outward thing; as in regard of ſhame, and puniſhment, in regard of wants and diſtreſſes, or in regard of the hand of God upon them by ſickneſſe, paine, ſores, or the like;<note place="margin">Exod. 8.8</note> as <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> did, when the hand of God was on him, then he cryed, <hi>I have ſinned, and take away this plague;</hi> but he never cryed, take away the hardneſſe of mine heart, and the curſedneſſe of my nature. Nay more, perhaps ſome may be found who ſometimes ſigh and groane for ſome actuall ſin, when they feel it preſſing and lying heavy upon their Conſciences; yet theſe men but groane as the bruit beaſt doth, that is preſſed with ſome heavy burthen; but they fetch not their ſighs from under that corruption that cleaves to their Hearts; ſo they groane not with their Hearts ſoundly, when they ſigh for their Sins. But if we would have true comfort in ſighing and groaning for Sin, we muſt down to the root of all Sins in our ſelves, and fetch our ſighs from under that corruption that cleaves inwardly to our ſoules, and thats the ſighing of a Child of God; and ſuch loud-tongued ſcalding Sighs, and ſalt briniſh tears, flowing from the Heart-breaking of a Sin-burthened ſoule, will be both pleaſing to God, and yeild
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:29387:57"/>comfort to us. Let us then ſigh and groane heartily for thoſe Sins which are ſo deeply ingrafted in us; let us weep for our ſelves, let us weep for others; let every remembrance of Sin, both our own and others, make freſh bleeding wounds in our Hearts: Let ſorrow clothe us, let mourning cloud us, let weeping be in every corner; let nothing be heard in our ſtreets but the Voyce of wayling, and while our miſeries are ſmarting, and our calamities laſting, let nothing remaine to the godly but ſorrow and weeping, that ſo we may eſcape unhurt, in the devaſtation of the wicked; for the Saints are alwayes priviledged men, their ſorrow is their ſafety, their lamentation the cauſe of their preſervation: So in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 9.4 &amp;c.</note> mourners ſhall be marked, <hi>Set a Marke, ſaith God upon the Fore-heads of them that Mourne and Cry for all the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Land, and by this Marke ſhall be preſerved.</hi> Examples to all Poſterity, and Saints hereafter in Eternall Glory</p>
            <p>And thus having clothed you in <hi>the Garments of heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and robed your ſoules with the ſable livery of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> I cannot, I ſuppoſe, leave you in a better habit, <hi>then that of Sorrow;</hi> nor in a better Poſture, <hi>then that of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation;</hi> nor in a better Place, <hi>then the Houſe of the Lord your God;</hi> where if you Cry earneſtly, no doubt but he will heare graciouſly. And ſo let Lamentation Seale up our Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord Heare our Prayer, and let our Cry come unto thee:</hi> AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
